<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="//www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
      xml:lang="en"
      xml:base="//smus.com">
  <title>Boris Smus (Notes)</title>
  <link href="//smus.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="//smus.com"/>
  <updated>2018-08-28T15:25:15-00:00</updated>
  <id>//smus.com/atom.xml</id>
  
  <entry>
    <title>For long form content</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="/notes/2018/for-long-form-content/"/>
    
    <updated>2018-08-28T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>//smus.com/notes/2018/for-long-form-content/</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>Hi!</p>


        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Lynched on Twitter</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="/notes/2018/lynched-on-twitter/"/>
    
    <updated>2018-08-26T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>//smus.com/notes/2018/lynched-on-twitter/</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>Last week, a <a href="https://twitter.com/borismus/status/798350680951910400">sarcastic twitter
reply</a> I posted two
years ago was picked up by an account called Blue Check Watch, looking for
verified twitter accounts disparaging white people. As a result, my account has
become inundated by a hybrid human-bot army of white supremacist trolls. Most
responses accused me of anti-white racism, completely missing what I thought was
obviously a sarcastic tone. Sadly, many of the attacks are really nasty and
ad-hominem. One user
<a href="https://twitter.com/CascadianDennis/status/1033190496456269824">posted</a> "Why do
people who say this always look like this?", alongside my twitter profile photo.
Others are
<a href="https://twitter.com/1CE1CEB4BY/status/1033197950703464448">explicitly</a>
<a href="https://twitter.com/NationDixie/status/1033395244014944256">anti-semitic</a>
messages that do not bear repeating here. Ominously, I received an email from
Twitter informing me that they have investigated <strong>my tweet</strong>, flagged for violating
their TOS and "have not taken any action at this time."</p>

<p>Writing my snarky tweet two years ago, I was a bit uncertain whether it was
within the bounds of social acceptibility. A white guy telling another
white guy that white guys are "the worst", was intended to poke a bit of fun at
the self-flaggelation associated with progressive politics. There is only so
much self-censorship one can do while still remaining authentic. In a surprising
twist, my tweet was offensive to a group I hadn't even thought about in a way I
could not have predicted, two years after the fact.</p>

<p>Twitter lynchings are not new, but it's different when it happens to you. It has
not had any serious consequences (yet?), and until it does, I will continue to
view this as a funny story, and not something truly traumatic, as it is often
framed in the press. Still, this experience serves as a good reminder of a few
points:</p>

<ol>
<li>Twitter's UI for threaded conversations is terrible, and hardly anyone of my
virtual lynch mob even bothered to look to the tweet I was responding to.</li>
<li>My tweet was five words, twenty four characters. It was meant to be pithy,
because that is how twitter works. But brief posts beget brief responses,
which is fine between friends, but not fine when the whole world is watching.</li>
<li>Relatedly, sarcasm is hard to convey in this situation. Only two responses
suggested that maybe I was being sarcastic, imploring my attackers, "Don't be
lazy."</li>
<li>The fact that tweets have no expiry date means anything you have ever posted
can be used against you in surprising ways. It took two years for my tweet to
be picked up. James Gunn's incriminating posts were ten years old. Social
norms change quickly, and this is one argument in favor of ephemerality.</li>
<li>On that same note, it seems that the white supremacy movement has really
embraced the internet over the last couple of years in some sick symbiosis
with the POTUS. At the same time, it's striking that the result of someone's
pathetic search for anti-white sentiment yielded such a lackluster example.</li>
<li>Despite a general willingness for my views to be challenged, I don't have
energy or desire to engage with this mob. I made no attempts to respond to
any of my attackers. They appear to be victims of confirmation bias, stupid
and/or malicious, and I have little faith that they will listen.</li>
<li>There are some really nasty people on the internet. If triggered, they will
sherlock your religion, your employer, your family, and try to hit you where
it hurts the most.</li>
</ol>

<p>Lynchings aside, I've been trying to use twitter less in favor of consuming and
producing longer form content, like books, blogs, and conversations. Given that
my account is currently being inundated with anti-semitic spam, I have very
little incentive to continue using the service. One thing that has been keeping
me on the platform is the potential reach I can get through 6K followers. I
should remember that in the grand scheme of things, this is a small number, 5
orders of magnitude less than the lovely POTUS. I shouldn't grow attached.</p>

<p>And so, just in time for my tenth twitter anniversary, it's time for me to make
some changes. At the very least, I'll be taking a long break.</p>


        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The difficult middle</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="/notes/2018/the-difficult-middle/"/>
    
    <updated>2018-07-21T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>//smus.com/notes/2018/the-difficult-middle/</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>Monism gives life meaning through a single all-encompassing doctrine. Examples
include some political ideologies, religions, and <a href="https://meaningness.com/non-theistic-eternalism">variants of
rationality</a>. History has not been kind to those that have
fervently followed such doctrines. But once you see flaws in Monism, it can be
tempting to decide that life has <a href="https://meaningness.com/extreme-examples-eternalism-and-nihilism">no meaning at all</a>, falling
into the trap of Nihilism.</p>

<p><img src="https://i.imgur.com/WXdU3ef.gif" alt="Stuck" /></p>

<p>The choice between these two extremes is a false one. <a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/erGipespbbzdG5zYb/the-third-alternative">Rationalists know
this</a>. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Middle_Way">Buddhists know this</a>. Philosophers know
this too. David Chapman writes a <a href="https://meaningness.com/">whole blog</a> devoted to exploring
the space in between. But I have found <a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/users/vl/notes/berlin.html">Isaiah Berlin</a>'s synthesis to
be the most compelling:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Sobered by the 20th century’s failed utopias, [Berlin]
  argued for a more modest liberal pluralism that makes room for multiple,
  genuinely conflicting goods. Family and work, solidarity and autonomy, tradition
  and innovation are really valuable, and really in tension.  – <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2018/04/steven-pinker-enlightenment-now/554054/">Alison
  Gopnik</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>In this view, we are condemned to an eternal balancing act, sometimes peering
too far into the meaningless abyss, and other times relaxing too deeply into
meaningful certainty. On balance, I hope to end up in this difficult middle.</p>


        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Required reading for VR enthusiasts</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="/notes/2018/required-reading-for-vr-enthusiasts/"/>
    
    <updated>2018-06-03T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>//smus.com/notes/2018/required-reading-for-vr-enthusiasts/</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>Several books, movies, and articles have helped to shape my opinions on Virtual
Reality. I've was initially surprised by some former colleagues that it is
possible to view these works as aspirational rather than cautionary. I generally
prefer the dystopian interpretation. </p>

<ul>
<li>📚 Ray Bradbury - <a href="http://www.veddma.com/veddma/Veldt.htm">The Veldt</a></li>
<li>📚 Neil Stephenson - Snow Crash</li>
<li>📚 Stanislav Lem - The Futurological Congress</li>
<li>📚 Vernor Vinge - Rainbow's End</li>
<li>📚 Ernst Kline - Ready Player One</li>
<li>🎥 Black Mirror S3 E2: <a href="http://www.theverge.com/2016/10/25/13401020/black-mirror-season-3-episode-2-playtest-recap">Playtest</a></li>
<li>🎥 The Matrix</li>
<li>🎵 Father John Misty - <a href="https://genius.com/Father-john-misty-total-entertainment-forever-lyrics">Total Entertainment Forever</a></li>
<li>📜 <a href="http://slatestarcodex.com/2014/06/03/asches-to-asches/">Asches to Asches</a></li>
<li>📜 Robert Nozick's <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Experience_machine">experience machine</a></li>
</ul>


        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Balancing technological pessimism</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="/notes/2018/balancing-technological-pessimism/"/>
    
    <updated>2018-05-16T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>//smus.com/notes/2018/balancing-technological-pessimism/</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p><a href="https://pessimists.co/">Pessimists archive</a> is a podcast that chronicles
pessimistic reactions to emerging technology as it was becoming mainstream.
Technology here is defined broadly, covering a broad range of topics: bikes,
coffee, pinball machines, vaccines, recorded music. The podcast is very
accessible, focused more on social and psychological issues and less on the tech
itself. </p>

<!--more-->

<p>In response to unreasonable technological enthusiasm ever present in my
industry, I have myself tended towards pessimism. After we launched Cardboard,
my small HCI team in Google Research became the de facto home of VR at Google.
Once word got out, engineers and designers flocked to our ranks, self selecting
for interest in VR. Suddenly I was surrounded by hundreds of VR enthusiasts,
while I was skeptical about the vision of VR as <a href="https://youtu.be/dxbh-TM5yNc?t=3m">&quot;the last
platform&quot;</a> and concerned about the social
implications of broad VR adoption.</p>

<p>I began to see myself as <a href="https://www.quora.com/World-War-Z-2013-movie/World-War-Z-2013-movie-Do-the-Israelis-really-have-a-10th-man-doctrine">the tenth
man</a>,
posing the question: what if VR isn't really a thing? I ended up much more
excited about <a href="https://atap.google.com/spotlight-stories/">Spotlight Stories</a>
without a headset, thought a bunch about augmented reality through audio, and
became increasingly alienated from my colleagues gushing with optimism, rushing
home to play Vive games in their carefully instrumented basements. This podcast
would sure have helped me put my VR pessimism into perspective. </p>

<p>One critique I had of the podcast concept is hindsight bias. All of the
technologies covered by Pessimists Archive ended up being successful, and time
has proven the doubters wrong. But how many emerging technologies were
successfully booed out of existence, or simply rejected by the market? And how
many market successes come at a significant cost that prescient pessimists
warned us about?  TV and smartphones come to mind.</p>

<p>That said, I highly recommend the podcast series. The episodes are short,
entertaining, and informative. I feel better equipped to recognize and overcome
the traps that ensnared previous generations of techno pessimists.</p>


        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>How rationalists can win</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="/notes/2018/how-rationalists-can-win/"/>
    
    <updated>2018-04-12T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>//smus.com/notes/2018/how-rationalists-can-win/</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>The belief that <a href="https://wiki.lesswrong.com/wiki/Rationality_is_systematized_winning">"rationalists should win"</a> is widely held in the
rationalist community. So: does being a good rationalist actually help you win?
Certainly in some domains, like engineering and science, which focus on
quantification, systematization, and prediction. There, having a hyper-rational
mindset is clearly an advantage. As for winning at life, which I will take that
to mean leading to greater success in survival, evolution, and human
flourishing, I don't think rationality helps very much.</p>

<!--more-->

<p>The rationalist doctrine always favors quantification and optimization over
intuition. From a rationalist perspective, humans are buggy <a href="https://www.wired.com/2016/01/marvin-minskys-marvelous-meat-machine/">"computers made of
meat"</a>. We are full of cognitive biases that cloud our judgement, and
cause us to do reliably poorly on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Newcomb%27s_paradox">simple tasks</a> related to
probability. So even if you don't really know what probability to assign, it's
better to <a href="https://putanumonit.com/">"put a number on it"</a> and then <a href="https://wiki.lesswrong.com/wiki/Shut_up_and_multiply">"shut up and
multiply"</a>.</p>

<p>The problem with the above approach lies with the words "systematic" and
"predictable". Herb Simon's idea of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bounded_rationality">Bounded Rationality</a>, suggests that
our human ability to be rational, to systematize and predict is inherently
limited. These limitations may come from our limited brains, but may also be
fundamental in nature. Chaos theory makes it really difficult for even the most
advanced computers to predict even simple systems, such as the position of the
<a href="http://awesci.com/double-pendulum-and-why-we-can-never-predict-weather/">double pendulum</a> after a small amount of time.</p>

<p>The world is far more complicated than one pendulum attached to another.
Insisting on making every decision in life based on a <a href="/making-better-decisions/">series of sound logical
steps</a>, one quickly becomes paralyzed by the
complexity of myriad tiny choices. Gerd Gigerenzer's <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ecological_rationality">ecological
rationality</a> suggests that many things that appear illogical are actually
done for good reasons, ultimately leading to good outcomes. This idea is
directly at odds with the rational propensity for first knowing what is true
(epistemic rationality), and then making decisions in a series of logical steps.</p>

<p>Instead of being dogmatic about rationality, we should be better
consequentialists. Consider outcomes. Are rationalists more satisfied with their
lives than non-rationalists? Are they more productive?  Do they have fewer
regrets later in life? Do they have better relationships? Make more money?  Have
happier children? Impact their domains of knowledge more effectively?</p>

<p>It <a href="http://slatestarcodex.com/2018/04/02/are-the-amish-unhappy-super-happy-just-meh/">is hard to answer</a> the above questions definitively, but suppose we
had solid data, and it was clear that, Buddhists were more relaxed, Protestants
more productive, Amish happier, and Singularitarians more innovative than other
groups. Imagine we had a sense of expected consequences of being an adherent to
each type of lifestyle. Imagine further that you could take a personality test
and see how likely you would be to benefit from each. Then the rational thing to
do would be to choose one of the irrational doctrines to follow based on
expected outcomes if you were an adherent.</p>

<p>Of course, you want to remain open to changing your mind, so allow yourself to
indulge fully your chosen beliefs for a while. At the top of every year, wake up
as late as your doctrine allows and nurse your hangover, unless your beliefs
prevented you from drinking the night before. If your beliefs favors ice baths,
partake in the polar bear plunge. Then take a moment to re-evaluate your
beliefs.</p>


        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>A respectful truce?</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="/notes/2017/a-respectful-truce/"/>
    
    <updated>2017-08-24T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>//smus.com/notes/2017/a-respectful-truce/</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>It's a fact that men greatly outnumber women in software engineering. As for
why, there is a fundamental disagreement between social constructivists and
evolutionary psychologists. </p>

<!--more-->

<p>Constructivists say that it’s because of systematic oppression against women.
Boys in the 80s grew up with computers, learned programming and made life a
living hell for their female classmates in CS101. <a href="http://www.npr.org/sections/money/2014/10/21/357629765/when-women-stopped-coding">Planet Money</a> has the
scoop. Evolutionary psychologists say that it’s because men and women have
evolutionarily caused <a href="https://heterodoxacademy.org/2017/08/10/the-google-memo-what-does-the-research-say-about-gender-differences/">differences in interests</a> and point to studies
indicating that progressive countries have larger gender representation gaps
because women are free to choose <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2017/08/07/contra-grant-on-exaggerated-differences/">careers based on interest</a>. I find
it likely that both positions contribute in part to the gender representation
disparity. Compelling arguments can be made for and against both, and both are
rooted in academic disciplines <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Replication_crisis">that are dangerously squishy</a>. As a
result, I don’t think we currently have a good scientific way of determining
this.</p>

<p>So what; science, schmience! Followers of the evo psych and constructivism are
at war. One continuously pisses the other off with their inflamatory rhetoric.
It is true that white males are historically privileged, but hammering “white
male privelege” into their heads predictably puts white males into a defensive
stance. Similarly, discussing how evo psych means that women are less interested
and therefore less capable of software engineering will predictably annoy
females, especially those rightfully proud of their software engineering
prowess, and tired of dealing with similar allegations for their whole career.</p>

<p>I've spent way too much time reading and thinking about this lately, and it
saddens me to conclude that the wisest course of action is to avoid discussing
this topic entirely (oops, too late). Scott Aaronson, Sarah Constantin and
Stacey Jeffery propose a <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=3389">respectful truce</a> between the two camps.
Advocates of evolutionary psychology should:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>do everything they can to foster diversity, including by creating environments
  that are welcoming for women, and by supporting affirmative action, women-only
  scholarships and conferences, and other diversity policies and also agree
  never to talk in public about possible cognitive-science explanations for
  gender disparities in which careers people choose, or overlapping bell curves,
  or anything else potentially inflammatory."</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Meanwhile, social constructivists should:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>avoid libelling [white men] as misogynist monsters, who must be scaring all
  the women away with their inherently gross, icky, creepy, discriminatory
  brogrammer maleness.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Truce?</p>


        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The end of endings</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="/notes/2017/the-end-of-endings/"/>
    
    <updated>2017-07-31T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>//smus.com/notes/2017/the-end-of-endings/</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>Despite the obnoxious title, <a href="https://a16z.com/2017/07/15/popularity-addiction-thompson-alter/">this a16z podcast</a> was unusually insightful.</p>

<p>One big theme in the podcast can be summarized as an end of endings: a trend
away from one story with a coherent, finite arc, towards something neverending.
Amorphous TV shows like Lost, as well as Hollywood's discovery that a coherent
franchise like Star Wars can be milked for many more dollars are examples of
this. The stats backs it up: Hollywood moved from 10% of the hits of the 90s
being sequels to 50% today, as can be seen in the <a href="http://www.boxofficemojo.com/yearly/">box office data</a>.
Looking at TV shows through the same lens, each show is a one hour long movie,
followed by tens of sequels. And successful franchises aim to immerse their fans
(especially kids) into their universe with figurines, games, lunch boxes, bed
sheets.</p>

<p>The end of endings also shows up in user interfaces, and is epitomized by the
infinite scroller. Millions of souls fixate on the next pretty picture, the next
baby picture, the next outrage. Entertainment that never ends!</p>

<p>This is interesting in the context of attention. In the realm of meditation, the
challenge is to focus on something mundane, like your breath. In the realm of
entertainment, the challenge is to snap out of an immersive world carefully
constructed to consume your attention for as long as possible.</p>


        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Intelligence, aliens, and self-improvement</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="/notes/2017/intelligence-aliens-and-self-improvement/"/>
    
    <updated>2017-07-10T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>//smus.com/notes/2017/intelligence-aliens-and-self-improvement/</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>I recently enjoyed a podcast about intelligence, aliens and learning where Kevin
Kelly was interviewed by Sam Harris. Here are some things I liked about it:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Kelly makes a great argument that with text we already have no way of knowing
what is true. We have to rely on the source. My fears of audio and video fake
news are reduced.</p></li>
<li><p>It's obvious that the world is changing quickly, which means lifelong learning
is necessary. One thing I haven't systematically understood is how I learn
best. How would you even figure that out?</p></li>
<li><p>Chimpanzees are amazing at <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zsXP8qeFF6A">short term spatial
memory</a>, and do better than
humans in these cognitive tasks on average.</p></li>
<li><p>Currently, the best Chess players are human-computer hybrids. Harris claims
that computers alone will eventually be better than these hybrids, but 
his claim that "the ape will just be adding noise" is unsubstantiated.</p></li>
<li><p>About mid-way, the two discuss the analogy between AI and aliens. I haven't
thought of this either. But I wondered how salient that analogy was given that we
have a largely shared environment with whatever AIs we create. To the extent
that the AIs truly are alien, I wonder how much of a unifying force these
alien AIs could be for humanity. </p></li>
<li><p>I strongly agreed with Kelly when he says that building machine systems
enhances our self-understanding. Building VR rendering and head tracking
systems, you benefit from some human visual perception basics. Human
psychology is critical for building user interfaces. You need an understanding
of how human hearing works to build good lossy audio compression.</p></li>
<li><p>An interesting thought experiment that superscedes Asimov's laws of robotics:
what if we built AGIs that were terribly worried about what people think. Then
we reduce the machine menace problem to merely the evils of humanity. </p></li>
</ul>


        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Convincing the inconvincible</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="/notes/2017/convincing-the-inconvincible/"/>
    
    <updated>2017-06-20T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>//smus.com/notes/2017/convincing-the-inconvincible/</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>I highly recommend two <a href="http://loveandradio.org/2014/02/the-silver-dollar/">podcast</a> <a href="http://loveandradio.org/2017/02/how-to-argue/">episodes</a> on the theme "how to argue",
featuring Daryl Davis, <em>the</em> black friend of white supremacists. Mr. Davis is
remarkably lucid in dealing with very difficult issues, and presents great tips
for convincing the inconvincible. </p>

<ol>
<li><p>Gather your information. Understand their position as well as you do your
own. Expect to hear things you will disagree with and keep your cool. </p></li>
<li><p>Invite them. Have a conversation not a debate. Debates get people's guards
up. Instead seek to understand them. People want to be heard and speak their
mind freely without retaliation. </p></li>
<li><p>Look for commonality. You can find something in 5 minutes and then build on
it. Look to other issues. Politics? As you find more commonality the
differences matter less. </p></li>
<li><p>Talking is not fighting. When the talking stops the ground becomes fertile
for violence (cf. Sam Harris). The longer you talk the more commonalities you
can find. </p></li>
<li><p>Patience.</p></li>
<li><p>Make a good first impression. Be respectful. </p></li>
<li><p>Don't be condescending or insulting even when you hear things you don't like.
Expect opinions that are ridiculous and facts that are wrong. Keep cool. </p></li>
<li><p>Don't explain somebody else's movement. Let them explain it and address the
points that they themselves define. Let them finish and don't cut them off
even though you probably know a lot about their ideas already. </p></li>
</ol>

<blockquote>
  <p>"While you are actively learning about someone else you are passively teaching
  them about yourself." – Daryl Davis</p>
</blockquote>


        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Remembering my personal wiki</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="/notes/2017/remembering-my-personal-wiki/"/>
    
    <updated>2017-06-01T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>//smus.com/notes/2017/remembering-my-personal-wiki/</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>Before I started writing this blog, I used <a href="https://moinmo.in">MoinMoin</a> as a personal wiki.
It was self-hosted on a Linux box in my parents' basement. I used it for
everything: jotting down ideas, as a calendar, storing guitar tabs, tracking
workout routines, course planning, and personal finances. I wrote on the wiki
actively from about 2002 to about 2008. Here are some blasts from the past:</p>

<ul>
<li>My Lego fandom started to shift from into robotics. To be clear,
this is just a fancy way of saying that I was still <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Bartender/">playing</a> <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/CardDealer/">with</a>
<a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/VerticalCrossBeams/">legos</a> into my early twenties.</li>
<li>Origami interests also shifted into the <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/OrigamiSoftware/">digital realm</a>.</li>
<li>I <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Network/">maintained a network</a> of about ten Linux boxes named after
<a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Aleph/">Hebrew</a> <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Zayin/">letters</a>. What a pain in the ass!</li>
<li>Wrote a few computer games, like this uninspired <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/ArcadeTank/">tank game</a>, and this
totally awesome <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Sponge/">pong variant</a> that was played inside a sphere.</li>
<li>Discovered <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Second-system_effect">second system syndrome</a> when trying to rewrite <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Alienation/">a web based
RPG</a> I originally wrote in 2000.</li>
<li>Had some interesting, still relevant <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/GpsRpg/">ideas foreshadowing</a> Augmented
Reality gaming.</li>
<li>Catalogued delicious Japanese food in <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/JapaneseRestaurants/">Vancouver</a>.</li>
<li>Smashed a Palm Tungsten <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/TungstenDestruction/">with a hammer</a> out of frustration,
attempted to use a <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/TreoBluetoothHeadsets/">Bluetooth headset with my Treo</a> and dreamed of a
<a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/DreamGadget/">better gadget</a>.</li>
<li>Hoping to <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/MatrixWorkouts/">avoid the gym</a>, I got into <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Kettlebells/">kettlebells for fitness</a>,
and even thought about starting a <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Gireviki/">kettlebell community</a>.</li>
<li>Saved <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Guitar(2f)Gravedigger/">guitar</a> <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Guitar(2f)WildMountainThyme/">tabs</a> I played with the intention of
<a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/LibTab/">doing something techy</a> with them later.</li>
</ul>

<p>Embarassing and endearing, <code>wiki.z3.ca</code> serves as a time capsule of my late
teens and early twenties. Je me souviens.</p>


        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Short posts using split Markdown</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="/notes/2017/short-posts-using-split-markdown/"/>
    
    <updated>2017-05-28T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>//smus.com/notes/2017/short-posts-using-split-markdown/</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p><a href="https://github.com/borismus/lightning">Lightning</a>, the static blog generator that powers this site, is
awesome for long form content. But it does not work well for short form content,
since creating each post requires a bunch of up-front effort:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>I navigate to the right place, recalling the current year (!) and deciding on
the slug for the post (eg. <code>content/posts/2017/how-to-fix-the-world</code>).</p></li>
<li><p>I manually create the <code>index.md</code> file and then specify the redundant
human-readable title and the posted date within it:</p>

<pre><code>How to Fix the World
===
posted: May 28, 2017

Listen to me, I have the answers.
</code></pre></li>
</ol>

<p>After writing the post, the title will inevitably have changed, so I rename the
slug to match: <code>mv how-to-fix-the-world how-to-slightly-improve-the-world</code>.
Finally I publish and tweet, and hopefully the world becomes infinitesimally
better.</p>

<p>I once tried to <a href="/easier-link-blogging/">make it easier to keep a lightning-style link blog</a>, but
ended up scrapping the solution because it was buggy and required a Mac.</p>

<h2>Split markdown pages</h2>

<p>My aim was to remove the up-front costs I described above. Appending to the top
of an existing file and having the engine automatically generate a slug based on
the title seemed like the right approach. This means that one markdown file
results in multiple HTML pages. The latest <a href="https://github.com/borismus/lightning">Lightning</a> has been
updated with split markdown files, and refactored into classes, making it easier
to add features in the future. To give a sense of what these split markdown
files look like, take a look at <a href="https://github.com/borismus/smus.com/blob/master/notes_all.md">this file</a>.</p>

<p>Split markdown files power two new sections on this site: a <a href="/books">book
reviews section</a>, and a <a href="/notes">notes section</a>. I'm hoping that this
added convenience will encourage me to write shorter, more focused posts with
increasing frequency.</p>


        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Analogies from the industrial revolution</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="/notes/2017/analogies-from-the-industrial-revolution/"/>
    
    <updated>2017-05-24T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>//smus.com/notes/2017/analogies-from-the-industrial-revolution/</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>Several centuries after the industrial revolution, machines still can't do all
physical things humans can, not even by a long shot. Drawing a masterwork,
singing an aria, playing a musical instrument, manipulating a soft object,
cutting hair, taking care of the sick are all examples of human-only tasks. The
industrial revolution gave machines the ability to do crude, physically
demanding work at scale, but it did not address all of physicality.</p>

<p>Just like the industrial revolution did not automate all aspects of physical
work, there is good reason to believe that the AI revolution will not solve
all aspects of intellectual work. Where the line will be drawn remains to be
seen, but I would bet that one aspect of human cognition that isn't really at
risk from any immediate AI-based disruption are creative pursuits. Many well
respected professions like doctor, lawyer, and engineer have both a rote
component that lends itself easily to automation, and a creative one. Some
examples:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Curing patients boils down to the application of known heuristics to
triage specific cases, but if you are a MD-PhD studying a new area of medicine
or tackling a new disease, it's a much more creative and speculative process. </p></li>
<li><p>The legal profession involves finding the right precedents relevant to the case
at hand, but articulating a convincing argument or deciding how to work out a
new situation where there are now laws yet? Creativity.</p></li>
<li><p>Designing a marketing webpage for a clothing brand is pretty formulaic. But
inventing way of solving a problem using new technology? Totally creative. </p></li>
</ul>


        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>