<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
      xml:lang="en"
      xml:base="https://smus.com">
  <title>Boris Smus (Notes)</title>
  <link href="https://smus.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://smus.com"/>
  <updated>2025-05-04T21:24:31-00:00</updated>
  <id>https://smus.com/atom.xml</id>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Invention &amp; Discovery Cards work complete</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2025/invention-discovery-cards-work-complete"/>
    
    <updated>2025-01-24T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2025/invention-discovery-cards-work-complete</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>I'm pleased to have completed transforming <a href="/books/asimovs-chronology-of-science-and-discovery/">Asimov's Chronology of Science and Discovery</a> into a deck of Magic Cards. Over five years later, all 1477 entries from
Asimov's encyclopedia are now represented as illustrated cards on <a href="https://invention.cards">https://invention.cards</a>. The
website is rendered based on <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1hDNXas7DzwglB95HV2_2u1utWAwBZR2hQHlMPz-fj5A/edit?gid=0#gid=0">this master spreadsheet</a> which I compiled with the help of AI
and manually vetted. Since AI hallucinations can safely be ignored, and I am infallible, I declare victory!</p>
<!--more-->

<h1>Just kidding...</h1>
<p>A project like this is never over, but I did make some revisions to <a href="https://invention.cards">https://invention.cards</a> to celebrate
the data milestone.</p>
<ul>
<li>The site now has a title.</li>
<li>The list of all cards is now fully scrollable.</li>
<li>Rendering is capped to 100 cards to maintain performance.</li>
<li>No limit to the depth of the ancestor or successor trees.</li>
<li>Added random card button.</li>
</ul>
<p>In 2019, when I <a href="/books/asimovs-chronology-of-science-and-discovery/">first cracked Asimov's encyclopedia</a>, I immediately wanted to turn it into a visual chronology:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>My goal is to ultimately generate a visual, Civilization-style technology tree for this whole book.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Mission accomplished, amirite? Permit me a quick walk down memory lane:</p>
<ul>
<li>2020: My <a href="/visual-chronology-science-discovery">initial visualization</a> was inspired by the then newly coined <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/science/archive/2019/07/we-need-new-science-progress/594946/">Progress Studies</a>.</li>
<li>2021 brought headwinds which stymied my progress studies. We now had two young children to raise and a pandemic to survive.</li>
<li>2022 brought tailwinds in the form of hawt new AI models. By early 2024 I posted an <a href="/visual-chronology-science-discovery-v2/">illustrated revision</a> and extended the chronology to the year 1850. Data-wise, this was just the half-way point.</li>
<li>2024: I <a href="/invention-cards-ai/">used AI to accelerate the process</a> and by the end of the year, I'd advanced up to 1945.</li>
<li>2025 brings us to today!</li>
</ul>
<h1>That's funny...</h1>
<blockquote>
<p>The most exciting phrase to hear in science, the one that heralds new discoveries, is not "Eureka!" but "That's funny..." - Isaac Asimov</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Throughout the process of reading and summarizing, I kept an "Asimov surprise log", capturing the head scratchers that made me pause and say "That's funny...":</p>
<ol>
<li>Specific surprising inventions and discoveries (e.g. Why is it that <a href="https://invention.cards/dendrochronology">Dendrochronology</a> was only conceived of in 1920?)</li>
<li>Multiple inventions and discoveries (e.g. How is it that we made space-related discoveries before inventing <a href="https://invention.cards/telescope">telescopes</a>?)</li>
<li>Groups of cards that tell a compelling story (e.g. Why did it take fifteen centuries to invent the practical steam engine after the <a href="https://invention.cards/basic-steam-engine">Greeks harnessed steam for motion</a>?)</li>
<li>Broad patterns across inventions and discoveries (e.g. Which general purpose inventions unlocked the most compelling discoveries?)</li>
<li>Meta-observations about what the source material (e.g. Asimov's background in Chemistry and golden age sci-fi explains disproportional energy spend on biology, chemistry, and astronomy. In 2025, what are our collective blinders?)</li>
</ol>
<p>Now that this project is in some sense complete, I hope to spend some energy elaborating on these and other
questions in the near future. Stay tuned!</p>

        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Unintended Consequences of False Equity</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2024/unintended-consequences-of-false-equity"/>
    
    <updated>2024-10-28T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2024/unintended-consequences-of-false-equity</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>What if our pursuit of educational equity is perpetuating inequality? Just as a rising tide lifts all boats, true educational equity must lift all students, regardless of background or ability.</p>
<p>In a school setting, equity refers not to the equality of outcomes, but to the equality of opportunities for all students to succeed. In recent years, Seattle Public Schools (SPS) has prioritized supporting students furthest from educational justice (FFEJ), a laudable goal that aims to address historical inequities. However, this narrow focus has unintended consequences. While healthy adults may not need medicine, children — even the brightest — require external stimulation to reach their full academic potential. Here are three negative secondary effects of an overemphasis on FFEJ students.</p>
<!--more-->

<p>First is <strong>reduced enrollment and funding to the district</strong>. As high-end academics stagnate, displeased parents of capable children pull their children out of public school. This exodus is prominently displayed in Seattle, where a quarter of school-age children have now withdrawn from public school (up from one-sixth in 2022). Since Washington schools are funded per capita, less enrollment means less money funneling into the school district. From this purely self-interested financial perspective, neglecting capable students is like sawing off the branch you are sitting on.
Furthermore, prioritizing FFEJ students also leads to <strong>less equity for highly capable students from poorer families</strong>. Private school is not cheap, and homeschooling is a luxury that only some families can afford, with at least one parent no longer able to work full-time. Thus, many families dissatisfied with public academics will not have the luxury of leaving the system. With the richest opting out of the public system, there are also less donations flowing to the Parent Teacher Student Associations (PTSA). With fewer capable students in the system and fewer exemplars of excellence for other students to follow, we will see a stronger correlation between socioeconomic status and academics. As a result, highly capable students forced to remain in the public system have reduced upward mobility.</p>
<p>A related side effect of this policy is an <strong>academic inversion in affluent neighborhoods</strong>, whose public schools become worse than those in poorer neighborhoods. When an upper-class neighborhood predominantly enrolls its children in private schools, the public school in the area will stagnate and cater to a smaller audience on the outer rim of the catchment area. In Seattle, this effect is on display in Laurelhurst.</p>
<p>Quoting <a href="https://mediadirectory.economist.com/people/charlotte-howard/">Charlotte Howard</a>, The Economist’s executive editor:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>There’s a real opportunity for leaders to talk not about coddling specific subgroups, but passing broad policies to help Americans writ large, regardless of their particular group to advance.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>What needs to happen is pretty simple: give each student what they need to thrive; actual equity. In SPS, this would mean bringing back programs for highly capable students. This does not need to be done in a separate school as in the recently terminated Highly Capable Cohort (HCC) program. But it should probably not be done in the same classrooms as the other students, with no additional resources for already overloaded teachers. Enriched and remedial classes within neighborhood schools are a tested and true solution to this problem. These new programs need measurable goals so that the district can begin <a href="/notes/2024/seattle-public-schools-accountability-problem/">to be accountable</a> in their pursuits of high-end excellence.</p>
<p>In conclusion, our current educational system's emphasis on minimal standards directly impacts highly capable students and ultimately has an indirect negative impact on all students. It's time for Seattle and other progressive school districts to reclaim "equity", unlock the full potential of our children, and empower them to shape a brighter future for humanity.</p>

        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Seattle Public Schools accountability problem</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2024/seattle-public-schools-accountability-problem"/>
    
    <updated>2024-10-12T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2024/seattle-public-schools-accountability-problem</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>Imagine if Microsoft's company guidance was that it would make $100 billion this quarter. The end of the quarter rolls along and as it turns out, they only made $10 billion. This surprising result would lead to a market selloff frenzy. Microsoft's stock would take such a beating that surely their board would demand their CEO's resignation for gross mismanagement.</p>
<p>In contrast, Seattle Public Schools (SPS) has missed their targets comparably. The school district has not been held accountable by the school board. In 2019, SPS declared their first <a href="https://www.seattleschools.org/about/school-board/student-outcomes-focused-governance/">top-line goal</a> was as follows:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The percentage of Black boys who achieve English Language Arts proficiency or higher on the 3rd grade Smarter Balanced Assessment will increase from 28% in June 2019, to 70% in June 2024.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>June 2024 has come and gone, and this metric has moved from 28% to 32%. This is a mere 4% difference; a far cry from the 40% required to meet their self-determined goal. For this objectively terrible performance, the school board gave Mr. Jones a raise and lauded him for being “a strong leader for racial equity and educational justice.”</p>
<p>The situation is even worse than this comparison to big tech reveals. When Microsoft misses its goals, the victims are also the most capable of having righted the ship. Also, the damage is limited: the CEO and former employees will find new jobs, and shareholders will make better investments next time. In the case of a school district, the victims are innocent children who had no hand in the matter, and the impact on their life is profound. In short, our children's education is being undermined by shortsighted, unaccountable adults.</p>
<p>It's time for the school board to do their job and hold school district executives accountable for failing to meet expectations. It's time to set better, more realistic goals, and it's time to achieve them.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"And I'm sorry, Mr. Jones... It's time" — Ben Folds</p>
</blockquote>

        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Nine Links for Fall 2023</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2024/nine-links-for-fall-2023"/>
    
    <updated>2024-01-08T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2024/nine-links-for-fall-2023</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>Here is a small selection of intriguing articles I read online over the last three months.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/international/archive/2023/10/magic-sorcery-politics/675836/">Political Analysis Needs More Witchcraft</a> (<em>The Atlantic</em>) — Beliefs, true or false, rational or irrational, shape politics, and many people self-report a belief in witchcraft (1/6 in US, 2/3 of Latvia), and 85% globally believe in God. Academics and pundits tend to dismiss these views for being outlandish and this is a major blind spot.</li>
<li><a href="https://nothinghuman.substack.com/p/metrics-cowardice-and-mistrust">Metrics, Cowardice, and Mistrust</a> (<em>Ivan Vendrov</em>) — Vendrov describes a feedback loop in which making the wrong call based on intuition, or delegating to someone who does the same can be a firing offense at a corporate job. The result of this cover-your-ass mentality is an over-reliance on metrics at the expense of velocity and good outcomes.</li>
<li><a href="https://studio.ribbonfarm.com/p/a-whole-new-cope">A Whole New Cope</a> (<em>Venkatesh Rao</em>) — Most of us have negligible power to do anything about concerning events half way across the world, yet are deeply affected by them. Rao suggests this is because we interpret these events not in isolation but as signs and portents of our entire world beginning to come apart.</li>
<li><a href="https://aeon.co/ideas/ketman-and-doublethink-what-it-costs-to-comply-with-tyranny">‘Ketman’ and Doublethink: What It Costs to Comply With Tyranny</a> (<em>Jacob Mikanowski</em>) — Contra Arendt, who believed that the subjects produced by totalitarianism no longer distinguish between fact and fiction, Miłosz argued that they practiced what he called Ketman, first mastering deception, then practicing it competitively, valuing cunning over all else, and finally losing the ability to "differentiate his true self from the self he simulates".</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/@ben_mathes/employees-risk-more-8b757f6bbf0a">Employees Risk More</a> (<em>Ben Mathes</em>) — VCs invest money into a portfolio of bets, while the startup employee invests all of their time into one risky bet. Investors can raise more money, but employees can't raise more time, so if you're looking to join a startup, do your homework!</li>
<li><a href="https://randsinrepose.com/archives/the-wolf/">The Wolf</a> (<em>Rands</em>) — Describes an engineer archetype who works outside well-defined processes and is unburdened by the "encumbering necessities of a group of people building at scale". As a result, he is incredibly effective and appears to suffer no consequences for not following the rules.</li>
<li><a href="https://interconnected.org/home/2023/09/22/wards">Old Wards and New Against Fake Humans</a> (<em>Interconnected</em>) — Practical advice for detecting a fake human on the internet: challenge him to say something obscene. On a video call? Have your interlocutor turn sideways and show you her ears, and watch for visual glitches. It's "like shaking hands from the old days, demonstrating that I’m not about to draw my sword."</li>
<li><a href="https://autotranslucence.com/2018/03/30/becoming-a-magician/">Becoming a magician</a> (<em>Autotranslucence</em>) — Have you reached a plateau? Is your well-worn strategy bringing you diminishing returns? Pause and consider who you want to be next. What are the fears that hold you back? Who are you really impressed by? Surround yourself with those people that look like magicians to you, learn from them, articulate your new goal and find a new strategy to get there.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2023/10/ai-image-generation-human-creativity-imagination/675840/">A Tool to Supercharge Your Imagination</a> (<em>Ian Bogost</em>) — In an uncharacteristically optimistic article, Bogost lauds modern image generation models for their ability to quickly "shape unfiltered thoughts" and give them "shape outside your mind", but ignores the downsides. It's a bit like reading a book and then watching the movie: all of the fuzzy but vivid mental imagery in your mind's eye collapses into the images on the screen. Gandalf will never again be an abstract wizard, only the one depicted by Ian McKellen.</li>
</ul>
<p>Happy New Year to you all!</p>

        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Five Links for Summer 2023</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2023/five-links-for-summer-2023"/>
    
    <updated>2023-09-22T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2023/five-links-for-summer-2023</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>Five links that stood out to me over the summer:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/@komorama/the-live-oak-playbook-504000d0afa2">The Live Oak Playbook</a> (<em>Alex Komoroske</em>) — Invoking a botanical analogy, Alex argues that as our environment gets more harsh, the industry needs to adopt an approach more akin to an oak than to a eucalyptus. An insightful synthesis full of great, <a href="https://read.fluxcollective.org/">FLUX-y</a> ideas.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.simoncross.com/p/the-circle-of-control">The Circle of Control</a> (<em>Simon Cross</em>) — Elaborating on the Serenity Prayer, a succinct visual metaphor to distinguish between 1) things you directly control, 2) things you can only indirectly influence, and 3) things that affect you, but you have no control or influence over.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/1886/12/the-dream-of-russia/522855/">The Dream of Russia</a> (<em>The Atlantic, 1886</em>) — In this Atlantic article written nearly 150 years ago, Cyrus Hamlin describes Russia's deeply held imperial ambitions, focusing on their desire to control Constantinople.</li>
<li><a href="https://collabfund.com/blog/everything-is-cyclical/">Everything is Cyclical</a> (<em>Morgan Housel</em>) — Mountains grow from tectonic activity and then collapse under their own weight, victory has always sown the seeds of a fresh war, revolution brings with it counter-revolution, and so on.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.invisibleoranges.com/death-metal-english/">Death Metal English</a> (<em>Invisible Oranges</em>) — A concise playbook for converting regular English into DEATH METAL ENGLISH. For example, "commuting to work" gets translated into TRANSPORTATION OF THE WAGEBOUND UNTO THE NEXUS OF PERPETUAL QUOTIDIAN ENSLAVEMENT.</li>
</ul>

        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Five Links for Spring 2023</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2023/five-links-for-spring-2023"/>
    
    <updated>2023-06-30T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2023/five-links-for-spring-2023</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>Spring has sprung, as have five more links to things I enjoyed reading over the last three months:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/belief/2009/jun/05/heidegger-philosophy">Being and Time Series</a> (<em>Simon Critchley, 2009</em>) — A relatively accessible 8-part series dedicated to Heidegger's magnum opus "Being and Time", a notoriously difficult but also insightful and influential philosophical masterwork from the mid-20th century.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpsyg.2014.00756/full">Heart Rate Variability Biofeedback: How and Why Does It Work</a> (<em>Frontiers</em>) — Turns out the pressure wave produced by the heart and breathing are deeply intertwingled. By breathing at a certain frequency (~6 breaths a minute), one can increase HRV temporarily, and also exercise the neuroplasticity in the baroreflex, increasing resting HRV.</li>
<li><a href="https://crookedtimber.org/2023/05/06/the-cult-of-the-founders/">The Cult of the Founders</a> (<em>Crooked Timber</em>) — Frames the <a href="https://avc.com/2021/04/the-vision-thing/">well known</a> distinction between visionary-founder and operator-CEO in terms of prophets who rip up the rulebooks and create an ecstatic cult, and priests who are rule following administrators skilled in the "routinization of charisma".</li>
<li><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2016/01/18/why-big-companies-keep-failing-the-stack-fallacy">Why Big Companies Keep Failing: The Stack Fallacy</a> (<em>Anshu Sharma</em>) — Explains the Stack Fallacy, in which people believe that it is trivial to build the layer above, but very difficult to improve the layer below. Examples include browser engineers who ridicule web development and pure mathematicians who deride physicists as merely applied mathematicians.</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/@kentbeck_7670/fast-slow-in-3x-explore-expand-extract-6d4c94a7539">Explore/Expand/Extract</a> (<em>Kent Beck</em>) — A well articulated exploration of corporate behavior at different parts of the S-curve.</li>
</ul>

        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Seven Links for Winter 2023</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2023/seven-links-for-winter-2023"/>
    
    <updated>2023-03-31T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2023/seven-links-for-winter-2023</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>This year, rather than posting a digest of links monthly, I'm doing the same
quarterly, aiming for five to ten of my favorite links every three months. I
read 128 articles over January, February, and March, and favorited about 30% of
them. In retrospect, here are the magnificent seven that really stuck with
me:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://blog.sbensu.com/posts/2023-01-18-high-variance-management/">High Variance Management</a> (<em>Sbensu</em>) — Stage actors need to have a great "take" every performance, but film actors have the luxury of multiple takes. Analogously, rather than insisting on perfection every time, managers can embrace en evolution-inspired approach called "creative selection", encouraging multiple teams to tackle the same problem, prototyping and demoing to one another, and then having a decision maker pick the best approach.</li>
<li><a href="https://acoup.blog/2019/11/22/collections-why-are-there-no-empires-in-age-of-empires/">Why Are There No Empires in Age of Empires</a> (<em>Unmitigated Pedantry</em>) — Strategy games like AoE and Civ put you at the reins of an empire conquering other empires by means of total annihilation. This is misleading, because the point of real empires is to access the resources and labor of a subordinate population.</li>
<li><a href="https://boomcalifornia.org/2013/06/24/thinking-through-the-tomato-harvester/">The Tomato Harvester</a> (<em>Boom California</em>) — A well written account of California's rapid tomato farming transition from small individual farms to large industrial farming in the 1960s. The tomato and the harvester co-evolved, and the domestication of both plant and machine was due to the human animal.</li>
<li><a href="https://superbowl.substack.com/p/time-is-a-wheel-time-is-an-arrow">Time Is a Wheel, Time Is an Arrow</a> (<em>Superb Owl</em>) — Attempts to synthesize linear and cyclic time into a coherent worldview to counteract the modern propensity towards a linear view of time in which our civilization is progressing in some definite direction. What if the question isn't if the road we're on leads to utopia or dystopia, but whether we are on the road in the first place?</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/@ElizAyer/annual-performance-reviews-ruin-everything-7464e07dff3a">Annual Performance Reviews Ruin Everything</a> (<em>Elizabeth Ayer</em>) — A long multifaceted post criticizing annual performance reviews for potentially diagnosing challenges correctly, but usually placing responsibility on the individual, rather on the organization itself or larger system. As Deming’s famous quote has it, "a bad system will beat a good person every time."</li>
<li><a href="https://skamille.medium.com/which-meetings-should-you-kill-7430467c005b">Which Meetings Should You Kill?</a> (<em>Camille Fournier</em>) — Fournier suggests that excessive time spent on 1:1 meetings, not including those with direct reports, should be consolidated into "well-run weekly group meetings to fill the trust and alignment gap, rather than having your broader team go through the combined number of subset 1:1 meetings."</li>
<li><a href="https://www.newyorker.com/tech/annals-of-technology/chatgpt-is-a-blurry-jpeg-of-the-web">ChatGPT Is a Blurry JPEG of the Web</a> (<em>New Yorker</em>) — Ted Chiang critiques generative AI for writing, observing that LLMs serve as a blurring and interpolation tool over large corpora of data they are trained on, employing the analogy of lossy compression. Chiang observes that "your first draft isn’t an unoriginal idea expressed clearly; it’s an original idea expressed poorly", and starting with a blurry copy of unoriginal work isn’t a good way to create original work.</li>
</ul>

        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Links for November 2022</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2022/links-for-november-2022"/>
    
    <updated>2022-11-30T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2022/links-for-november-2022</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <ul>
<li><a href="https://kvetch.substack.com/p/why-did-comedy-die">Why Did Comedy Die?</a> (<em>Kvetch</em>) — The genre of comedy movie appears to have peaked in the the 1990s; perhaps it's a regression to the mean, maybe comedy movies are hard to translate for a global audience, or perhaps it's "sequelitis" and Marvel movies sucking all of the air out of the room, or perhaps the author is getting old and curmudgeonly?</li>
<li><a href="https://baheyeldin.com/literature/arabic-and-islamic-themes-in-frank-herberts-dune.html">Arabic and Islamic Themes in Frank Herbert's "Dune"</a> (<em>The Baheyeldin Dynasty</em>) — From the transparent analogy between spice and crude oil, and the stylings of the Fremen, Herbert's masterpiece was prima facie inspired by Middle Eastern themes. Khalid digs deeper into an etymological tour of the series revealing more Arabic influences than a typical westerner could glean.</li>
<li><a href="https://lithub.com/simone-weils-radical-conception-of-attention/">Simone Weil’s Radical Conception of Attention</a> (<em>Literary Hub</em>) — Weil drew a distinction between two kinds of attention: the first involving "muscular effort", where we perform for our interlocutor, demonstrating that we are heeding them through social cues, and the second which she dubs "negative attention", where we blot out all distractions, dilate our minds, and wait selflessly for insights to come to us.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.economist.com/1843/2022/11/15/the-good-delusion-has-effective-altruism-broken-bad">The Good Delusion: Has Effective Altruism Broken Bad?</a> (<em>The Economist</em>) — As Sam Bankman-Fried's crypto empire collapses, the public eye turns critically towards the earning to give and existential risk strains of the Effective Altruism movement which inspired his activity and nudged him to use destructive means to achieve questionable ends.</li>
</ul>

        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Links for October 2022</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2022/links-for-october-2022"/>
    
    <updated>2022-10-30T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2022/links-for-october-2022</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <ul>
<li><a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/ideas/archive/2022/06/russia-ukraine-nuclear-weapon-us-response/661315/">What if Russia Uses Nuclear Weapons in Ukraine</a> (<em>The Atlantic</em>) — What to do about a Russian tactical nuclear attack on Ukraine led to two very different responses from two groups tasked with this morbid scenario; a stark reminder about the contingency of history.</li>
<li><a href="https://time.com/6219200/what-russia-wants-ukraine/">Russia Wants to Lock Ukraine Back in the Soviet Cellar</a> (<em>Time</em>) — Pomerantsev describes a flourishing civil society in Ukraine, which comes at a time of great fear, evocatively describing the primal feeling of being alive triggered in the face of existential risk, looking upward, "like some medieval villager, the sky seems full of portents, danger, hope and symbols".</li>
<li><a href="https://fortune.com/2016/06/02/lying-leadership-skills-expectations-communication/">Why Deception Is Probably the Single Most Important Leadership Skill</a> (<em>Fortune</em>) — Argues that deception, not candor is a key quality in leadership because of reinforcing feedback loops: convincingly displaying confidence can attract the support that makes the confident posture become true, and similarly, projecting high expectations of employees leads to them performing better.</li>
<li><a href="https://acoup.blog/2022/08/26/collections-why-no-roman-industrial-revolution/">Why No Roman Industrial Revolution</a> (<em>Bret Devereaux</em>) — Bret argues that the Industrial Revolution could have only happened in Britain in the late 18th century because of a very specific set of contingent events: the centuries-long arms race for the best cannon led to pressure-resistant cylinders, which enabled nascent piston steam engines; steam power found a killer app: pumping water out of coal mines, and it happened to be easy to run steam engines on coal, leading to a virtuous cycle of efficiency improvements until finally the steam engine was good enough for use in textile production, which through serendipity was also centered in Great Britain.</li>
<li><a href="https://subconscious.substack.com/p/possibility-space">Possibility Space</a> (<em>Gordon Brander</em>) — "You don’t need to <em>be</em> creative. The creative breakthrough already exists out there in the space of possibility. It’s just waiting to be discovered."</li>
<li><a href="https://kvetch.substack.com/p/why-practice-judaism">Why Practice Judaism?</a> (<em>Misha Saul</em>) — Misha writes vocatively about aspiring to connect with thousands of years of communal observance by leaning on religious rituals (na'aseh v'nishma). Like the commitment of marriage, religion is a covenant to fall back on when life becomes too complex and tumultuous.</li>
<li><a href="https://logicmag.io/play/model-metropolis/">Model Metropolis</a> (<em>Logic Magazine</em>) — Kevin describes how Jay W. Forrester's complex modeling influenced the creator of Sim City to build a game that promulgates similar biases to its players, but more generally explores the limits to modeling, and the built-in assumptions that models carry in them. While itself flawed, this article is a healthy reminder that a model is just a map, and possibly a faulty one.</li>
<li><a href="http://dangrover.com/blog/2022/09/24/sim-games.html">Simulation Games Might Be What The World Needs Now</a> (<em>Dan Grover</em>) — Simulated models of reality, argues Dan, aren't useful because they provide a perfect map of the territory, but because they can facilitate a grounded, concrete conversation without the "scaffolding of narrative". Almost always, they reinforce that the world is always more complicated than it looks.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.theguardian.com/tv-and-radio/2022/oct/12/russia-adam-curtis-extreme-capitalism-liz-truss-traumazone">They Are Stealing Russia: Hyper-Capitalism Wrecked a Nation</a> (<em>Adam Curtis</em>) — Curtis' BBC documentary takes the viewer into unique footage of late USSR and early modern Russian life, showing the chaos, rampant corruption and trauma which three decades ago sowed the seeds for Russia's current path.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/world-asia-china-63225277">Xi Jinping's Party Is Just Getting Started</a> (<em>BBC</em>) — Wingfield-Hayes chronicles Xi Jinping's contingent rise to consolidated power in China, from his fight against corruption under Hu Jintao, to a purge of the old party and its replacement with "Yes" men, to an inculcation of his ideas in everyday Chinese life. Strong echoes of Mao, Stalin, and Putin.</li>
<li><a href="https://studio.ribbonfarm.com/p/scintillation-points">Scintillation Points</a> (<em>Venkatesh Rao</em>) — Rao suggests that sceniuses (scenii?) form around preferred topics that he calls Scintillation points (after Schelling points), which serve as nebulous attractors for the group to make steady progress on clarifying, but also provide social validation for each individual that their exploration is worthwhile.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.artofmanliness.com/character/advice/john-boyds-roll-call-do-you-want-to-be-someone-or-do-something/">John Boyd’s Roll Call: Do You Want to Be Someone or Do Something</a> (<em>Art of Manliness</em>) — John Boyd's life story is an example of a man who chose to do something meaningful with the time given him instead of taking the comfortable path of being a well liked careerist, chasing accolades and ranks.</li>
</ul>

        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Links for September 2022</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2022/links-for-september-2022"/>
    
    <updated>2022-09-30T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2022/links-for-september-2022</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <ul>
<li><a href="https://www.csis.org/analysis/can-russia-execute-gas-pivot-asia">Can Russia Execute a Gas Pivot to Asia?</a> (<em>CSIS</em>) — Shines a light on some difficulties Russia will be facing as it tries to send most of its gas exports east rather than west, including the challenge of breaking into a brand new market full of much larger players, the need to build new pipelines, all while selling its product at a discounted rate.</li>
<li><a href="https://mollyg.substack.com/p/addition-vs-subtraction">Addition vs Subtraction</a> (<em>Molly Graham</em>) — Graham argues that corporations (like people) tend to add new processes, and rarely remove existing ones, which leads to a steady march towards the overly complicated. Rather than simply complain, Molly offers some interesting ideas for combating this trend, like declaring a yearly calendar jubilee, or for large companies to hire a full-time employee dedicated to looking for things to stop doing.</li>
<li><a href="http://weblog.tetradian.com/2014/05/09/not-so-wicked/">Not So Wicked</a> (<em>Tetradian</em>) — Tom Graves digs into the term "wicked problem", which in contrast to tame or kind problems do not have a definite answer, and are highly complex. He prefers the term "wild problem", which is also the term Russ Roberts uses in his eponymous book.</li>
<li><a href="https://skamille.medium.com/opp-other-peoples-problems-d7eb174724ee">Other People's Problems</a> (<em>Camille Fournier</em>) — Fournier emphasizes the importance of picking your battles in a corporate setting, and underscores just how difficult solving problems is, especially if they have a cultural element. "There’s always going to be something you can’t fix."</li>
<li><a href="https://mysticalsilicon.substack.com/p/on-extending-human-understanding">On Extending Human Understanding of Animal Sensory Worlds Through AI</a> (<em>David Gasca</em>) — Inspired by Ed Yong's latest book, Gasca observes that just like animals experience the world in a way that we cannot, AIs might do the same. An engaging summary of "An Immense World", which seems like a worthy read.</li>
<li><a href="https://stratechery.com/2022/instagram-tiktok-and-the-three-trends/">Instagram, TikTok, and the Three Trends</a> (<em>Stratechery</em>) — Ben Thompson describes the current transition from social media where you consume content from your friends (Instagram), to algorithmic media, where you consume extremely engaging content created by others (TikTok) to a speculative near future where AI generated content is the most engaging.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.gawker.com/culture/failure-to-cope-under-capitalism">Failure to Cope "Under Capitalism"</a> (<em>Gawker</em>) — Clare Coffey criticizes the quickness with which we are prone to blaming the system rather than looking inward. Then again, I am a sucker for any call to think seriously about the good life and pursue it wholeheartedly, despite the struggles and inevitable failures along the way.</li>
</ul>

        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Links for August 2022</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2022/links-for-august-2022"/>
    
    <updated>2022-08-31T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2022/links-for-august-2022</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p><img alt="Generated image of an Origami fold of Rodin's Thinker." src="/assets/generated/2022-08-31.jpg" /></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://archive.vcu.edu/english/engweb/transcendentalism/authors/emerson/essays/selfreliance.html">Self-Reliance</a> (<em>Ralph Waldo Emerson</em>) — A classic essay from the transcendentalist 19th century philosopher, reminding to think for yourself, avoid conformity, be open to changing your mind, and worry less about being misunderstood.</li>
<li><a href="https://fs.blog/jootsing">"JOOTSing": The Key to Creativity</a> (<em>Farnam Street</em>) — Jootsing, a term coined by Douglas Hofstadter, means Jumping Out Of The System (JOOTS). First you must become intimately familiar with the system and its rules, and only then can you create something new by breaking some of them.</li>
<li><a href="https://theanarchistlibrary.org/library/ursula-k-le-guin-the-carrier-bag-theory-of-fiction">The Carrier Bag Theory of Fiction</a> (<em>Ursula K. Le Guin</em>) — Referencing the Carrier Bag Theory of Evolution, in which Fisher suggest the primacy of the bag over the knife, Le Guin questions the idea that the proper shape of a narrative involves conflict. Instead, Le Guin argues that "reduction of narrative to conflict is absurd"; instead, the natural shape of a novel is one of a bag of words carrying meanings, far less prescriptive than the hero's journey.</li>
<li><a href="https://sashachapin.substack.com/p/notes-against-note-taking-systems">Notes Against Note-Taking Systems</a> (<em>Sasha Chapin</em>) —  A forceful reminder that getting lost in your knowledge management system is a fantastic way to avoid creating things. Keep it simple!</li>
<li><a href="https://oxonianreview.com/articles/death-is-a-master-from-russia">Death Is a Master From Russia</a> (<em>The Oxonian</em>) — Pomerantsev: "I am a writer and I love my mother tongue. Today my love is still valid, but it has become difficult, dramatic. Evil is polyglot. It speaks hundreds of different languages. It has its favorites, though."</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/personal-growth/sprezzatura-the-art-of-making-difficult-things-look-simple-55d0441c5cd">Sprezzatura: The Art of Making Difficult Things Look Simple</a> (<em>Louis Chew</em>) — The ability to display a certain nonchalance while performing a great feat was the hallmark of the ideal courtier. To the untrained eye, the performer is a genius, and this is magical; but the trained observer sees sprezzatura as a sign that the individual has put in the work. Fortune favors the prepared.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/june-huh-high-school-dropout-wins-the-fields-medal-20220705/">June Huh, High School Dropout, Wins the Fields Medal</a> (<em>Quanta</em>) — A portrait of a poet turned mathematician whose character is charming and in many ways the polar opposite of a prototypically successful person who moves fast and gets things done. So many ways to be.</li>
<li><a href="https://mysticalsilicon.substack.com/p/you-know-nothing-a-conversational">"You Know Nothing”: A Conversational Mindset</a> (<em>David Gasca</em>) — David suggests a stance for having better conversations: resist the urge to make assumptions about your interlocutor and start from a place of curiosity. From this place, it's easier to initiate and have a good conversation.</li>
<li><a href="https://jsomers.net/i-should-have-loved-biology/">I Should Have Loved Biology</a> (<em>James Somers</em>) — James recalls how little he enjoyed learning Biology, which despite its interestingness as a field, felt like a "lifeless recitation of names". What if instead of focusing on seemingly arbitrary facts, Bio was taught historically, by acquainting students with real biological questions, the scientific processes biologists used to answer them, to give students an opportunity to put themselves in the scientists shoes and wonder? What if it involved more <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wJyUtbn0O5Y">inspiring and beautiful illustrations</a> and explorable explanations?</li>
<li><a href="https://ourworldindata.org/much-better-awful-can-be-better">The World Is Awful. The World Is Much Better. The World Can Be Much Better</a> (<em>Our World in Data</em>) — For many issues all three statements can be true at the same time. Take child mortality where 5.2 million children, or 3.8% of their population dies every year (completely awful), this number was 43% in 1800 (so we are making progress), but if the whole world was like the EU, this number could be reduced ten-fold (room to improve).</li>
<li><a href="https://every.to/p/what-i-miss-about-working-at-stripe">What I Miss About Working at Stripe</a> (<em>Brie Wolfson</em>) — A nostalgic piece about a time when the gravitational pull of work was strong. The author does a good job of capturing the feeling that a kind and balanced working environment may be at odds with the latent desire to do the best work of one's lifetime.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/ideas/archive/2022/05/parenting-decisions-dont-trust-your-gut-book-excerpt/629734/">The One Parenting Decision That Really Matters</a> (<em>The Atlantic</em>) — In a large scale study of children's outcomes as a function of many variables, recent studies indicate that the effect of nature on a child is far stronger than nurture, but one parenting factor stands above the rest: the location of the childhood home. See <a href="https://www.opportunityatlas.org/">The Opportunity Atlas</a> for more details.</li>
</ul>

        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Links for July 2022</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2022/links-for-july-2022"/>
    
    <updated>2022-07-31T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2022/links-for-july-2022</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p><img alt="Generated image of Putin up to no good." src="/assets/generated/2022-07-31.jpg" /></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://worksthatwork.com/1/urinal-fly">Aiming to Reduce Cleaning Costs</a> (<em>Works That Work</em>) — A humorous look at the fly targets found in the Schiphol urinals. It turns out that men cannot resist peeing on things, especially if they look as though they might wash away. If it’s something that you consciously don’t like, you’re more likely to pee on it, hence the fly. The first known urinal target was a bee in Victorian England in 1880, perhaps as a high-falutin' joke (Latin for bee is apis).</li>
<li><a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/ideas/archive/2022/06/how-san-francisco-became-failed-city/661199/">How San Francisco Became a Failed City</a> (<em>The Atlantic</em>) — San Francisco's homeless budget has grown exponentially, committing $1B over 2022 and 2023 to tackle the problem, but people are still selling fentanyl on the streets, petty crime is rising quickly, and school quality is plummeting. The main battle is between leftist idealists who think a perfect world is just within reach and we're on the right track, and liberals who are fed up with psychotic addicts on the sidewalk, and disagree that a merit-based school system is inherently racist.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.ijors.net/issue5_2_2016/articles/cicek.html">The Legacy of Genghis Khan - The Mongol Impact on Russian History, Politics, Economy, and Culture notes</a> (<em>IJORS</em>) — Medieval Russia (Kyiv) tracked Medieval Europe and its Latin Christian civilization, but the Mongol invasion isolated Russia from the west for nearly three centuries, setting it on a parallel track. Two opposing historical takes on this feature the Westernizers, who were charmed with the values of enlightenment, democracy, and freedom, blamed the Mongols for Russia’s backwardness, whereas the Eurasianists embraced the Mongol legacy, claiming that it strengthened the founding pillars of the Tsarist Russian State such as Orthodoxy and autocracy and thus made a profound contribution to the security and stability of Russia.</li>
<li><a href="https://skamille.medium.com/i-hate-manager-readmes-20a0dd9a70d0">I Hate Manager READMEs</a> (<em>Camille Fournier</em>) — In her own words: "If you know you have foibles/quirks that you in fact want to change about yourself, do the work." "Keep your bad behaviors to yourself, and hold yourself accountable for their impact". How? Consider getting a coach.</li>
<li><a href="https://nautil.us/the-kekul-problem-6082/">The Kekulé Problem</a> (<em>Nautilus</em>) — Legend has it that August Kekulé discovered the ring-like structure of benzene after daydreaming about the snake seizing its own tale, the ancient ouroboros symbol. If the unconscious is so smart, muses writer Cormac McCarthy, why the cryptic messaging? Just tell poor Kekulé directly, using language! Alas, the ancient unconscious predates language, and moves in mysterious ways.</li>
<li><a href="https://newlinesmag.com/reportage/estonia-warning-the-world-about-russia/">Estonia: Warning the World About Russia</a> (<em>Newlines Magazine</em>) — Estonians don't need to be reminded of what Russia under Stalin did to their ancestors in 1941 and 1949. Unlike much of the rest of the world, Estonian PM Kaja Kallas believed that Putin would invade on Feb 24. Today Estonia unequivocally supports Ukraine, donating 40% of the country's annual military budget and more than 0.8% of its GDP.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.purposegeneration.com/buzz/article/gather-with-purpose-how-to-host-a-jeffersonian-dinner">How to Host a Jeffersonian Dinner</a> (<em>Purpose Generation</em>) — By engaging in a single conversation, with only one person speaking at a time, Jefferson and his guests were able to unlock the power of their collective wisdom. The purpose was simple: to listen, learn, and inspire one another through meaningful dialogue around a particular topic.</li>
<li><a href="https://subconscious.substack.com/p/centralization-is-inevitable">Centralization Is Inevitable</a> (<em>Subconscious</em>) — Gordon leans on network theory to graphs occurring in nature, like the one with airports as vertices and flights as edges, or the internet with nodes as webpages and links as edges. These graphs may start random but converge to be power law distributed if you plot the frequency of nodes as a function of degree, but this makes them vulnerable to attacks on a few high-degree nodes (centers), which inevitably happen.</li>
</ul>

        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Links for June 2022</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2022/links-for-june-2022"/>
    
    <updated>2022-06-30T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2022/links-for-june-2022</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p><img alt="Generated image of a nuclear icebreaker running into trouble in the north sea. Oil painting by Ivan Aivazovsky" src="/assets/generated/2022-06-30.jpg" /></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://psyche.co/guides/how-to-have-a-life-full-of-wonder-and-learning-about-the-world">How to Revive Your Sense of Wonder</a> (<em>Psyche Guides</em>) — The childhood desire to ask "how" and "why" usually fades with age, but having children around, being open to embracing their way of thinking, and encouraging their curiosity by asking them generative questions of our own, parents can learn to rediscover the joys of wide-eyed discovery.</li>
<li><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2022/01/29/please-make-a-dumb-car/">Please Make a Dumb Car</a> (<em>TechCrunch</em>) — A relatable rant criticizing modern cars for evolving into another overbearing device of which we have too many. The prototypical large touchscreen display in the middle of the console is overloaded for controlling everything from windshield wiper frequency to in-cab temperature to audio volume. Marketed as the next generation in mobility, this is largely a cost-saving measure that cuts down on part numbers.</li>
<li><a href="https://palladiummag.com/2022/04/11/collapse-wont-reset-society/">Collapse Won't Reset Society</a> (<em>Palladium</em>) — Identifies "collapse enthusiasts", people that look forward to the end of the current order, so that through a period of difficult anarchy, their ingroup can emerge victorious. Historically speaking there is surprising continuity even through anarchic periods, abrupt shifts don't normally last, and radical resets are pretty much unprecedented.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.psypost.org/2022/05/heightened-dream-recall-ability-linked-to-increased-creativity-and-functional-brain-connectivity-63139">Heightened Dream Recall Ability Linked to Increased Creativity and Functional Brain Connectivity</a> (<em>PsyPost</em>) — The Alternate Uses Task (AUT) is a famous psychological test to measure divergent thinking ability. Doing well on this test appears to be correlated with creative thinking, high dream recall, as well as increased functional connectivity within the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Default_mode_network">default mode network</a>. Which way does the arrow of causality fly? Can these abilities be cultivated?</li>
<li><a href="https://www.ribbonfarm.com/2022/05/18/crisis-mindsets/">Crisis Mindsets</a> (<em>Ribbonfarm</em>) — Rao argues that "having to face a crisis alone, besides all the obvious practical downsides, has a corresponding subtle downside — wondering why you’re bothering fighting at all". As the world turns and the default mindset shifts from flourishing to crisis, we are reminded to "retain a strong connection to the sublime".</li>
<li><a href="https://hbr.org/2007/01/becoming-the-boss">Becoming the Boss</a> (<em>HBR</em>) — New managers promoted from IC roles are often stars and haven't made significant mistakes, but learning to manage is a tacit skill, learned through trial and error. The natural question "Who am I becoming?" looms large. A broad ranging article that might resonate with a new manager.</li>
<li><a href="https://hugoclub.blogspot.com/2022/06/dethrone-stars.html">The Tsars Like Dust</a> (<em>Hugo Book Club Blog</em>) — Argues that Science Fiction falls back on monarchy as the default form of government, because from a storytelling perspective, it's difficult to make nuanced forms of government interesting, and easier to explain policy decision as a result of one person's choice. These fictional monarchies are often "based on a presumption that there is an inherent superiority to those within a specific lineage", reified even in the latest Star Wars trilogy.</li>
<li><a href="https://religionnews.com/2020/06/16/why-crossfits-founder-got-crossed-up-on-by-floyd-protests/">Why CrossFit’s founder got crossed up by Floyd protests</a> (<em>RNS</em>) — Burton suggests that the ideology of "best-selfism" embodied by CrossFit, embracing the quasi-religious pursuit of a better body through hard work and dedication, is fundamentally incompatible with the social justice movement which embraces solidarity and mutual support. There is perhaps a deeper truth about both best-selfism and social justice: Neither is out of the reach of the tendrils of capitalism.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.commentary.org/articles/jay-lefkowitz/the-rise-of-social-orthodoxy-a-personal-account/">The Rise of Social Orthodoxy (2014)</a> (<em>Commentary</em>) — A personal account of an as-yet-unnamed splinter movement in the Jewish Modern Orthodox denomination, which seeks to find a new point on the spectrum, closer towards modernity and further from orthodoxy, while still fully embracing the Jewish idea of <a href="https://www.jpost.com/jerusalem-report/understanding-naaseh-vnishma-in-a-post-modern-world-631129">na’aseh v’nishma</a>: engaging first in religious practices and letting matters of faith come later.</li>
<li><a href="https://bookmarks.reviews/george-orwells-1940-review-of-mein-kampf/">George Orwell reviews Mein Kampf (1940)</a> — Reviewed during the period of peace between Russia and Germany, reviewing an "unexpurgated" translation of Mein Kampf edited from a pro-Hitler angle from he was "still respectable", Both socialism and capitalism present positive visions that "assume tacitly that human beings desire nothing beyond ease, security and avoidance of pain", Orwell astutely observes that Hitler's ideology appealed to those seeking a valorous path, offering struggle, danger, death and an opportunity for patriotism and the military virtues.</li>
<li><a href="https://craigmod.com/ridgeline/143/">Walking the Cotswolds, Walking Japan</a> (<em>Craig Mod</em>) — Craig Mod presents an amazing multi-day meetup format involving walking and talking (a great combination, highly recommended): "A topic is chosen before bed. We chat the next day as we walk, and then we gather for a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HuAT0YHQz94">Jeffersonian-style dinner</a> in the evening. One person talks, then another. Everyone listens."</li>
<li><a href="https://beforewegoblog.com/purity-and-futures-of-hard-work-by-ada-palmer/">Hopepunk, Optimism, Purity, and Futures of Hard Work</a> (<em>Ada Palmer</em>) — punk = “fight the man” + hope = “we deserve a better world”. Ada observes that hopepunk is a distinct opposites to the grimdark fantasy genre because while it embraces positive aspects of human nature (teamwork, honesty, resilience), unlike the more bland squeecore, hopepunk rejects purity. An insightful read, including a paradoxical insight, suggesting dystopian literature as a "fundamentally optimistic genre".</li>
<li><a href="https://tedgioia.substack.com/p/where-did-the-long-tail-go">Where Did the Long Tail Go?</a> (<em>Ted Gioia</em>) — A look back at Chris Anderson's starry eyed take on the future of the internet in "The Long Tail" (2006), which predicted that the internet would flourish into a world of endless choices for every fringe interest under the sun. In retrospect, rather than "Selling Less of More", thanks to aggregators and centralization, we are losing the long tail and returning back to normal economics, selling more of less.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/newsletters/archive/2022/06/uber-ride-share-prices-high-inflation/661250/">Why Urban Life Suddenly Got Way More Expensive</a> (<em>The Atlantic</em>) — When interest rates were near zero, VC money flowed easily and subsidized many risky ventures operating at a loss that aimed to "<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=p7Lo0sZfdHE">Blitzscale</a>" their way to gaining a monopoly, effectively subsidizing the price for consumers. As the tides turn, Blitzscaling is becoming harder to execute, so prices for food delivery, ride sharing, meal kits should further increase.</li>
</ul>

        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Links for May 2022</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2022/links-for-may-2022"/>
    
    <updated>2022-05-31T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2022/links-for-may-2022</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p><img alt="Generated image of The Little Prince surfing and catching the golden snitch" src="/assets/generated/2022-05-31.jpg" /></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://nasjaq.substack.com/p/the-terrapunk-manifesto">The Terrapunk Manifesto</a> (<em>Nasjaq</em>) — A critical look at the Solarpunk movement, which the author argues is fundamentally about stagnation, promoted as harmony. Terrapunk is a more progress-centric bouquet of beliefs, with an emphasis on human ingenuity, nuclear energy, and a multi-planetary future.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/opinion/articles/2022-05-17/elon-musk-henry-ford-and-the-cost-of-stardom">Elon Musk Is Acting Like Henry Ford</a> (<em>Bloomberg</em>) — After his initial success, Henry Ford purchased a failing newspaper and promulgated his anti-semitic views, and drove a way his most capable lieutenants, replacing them with sycophants. His empire was ultimately dethroned by Alfred P. Sloan, an MIT trained engineer who eventually assumed control of GM and pioneered consumer financing. Will Musk suffer a similar fate?</li>
<li><a href="https://neddonovan.substack.com/p/the-department-store-that-was-once">The Department Store That Was Once a Country</a> (<em>Ned Donovan</em>) — Chronicles the rich history of the Hudson's Bay Company, which was given a monopoly over nearly 4 million square kilometers in modern day Canada. The corporation created a new currency: the MB (Made Beaver), fixed prices against it, outlawed private trading, and ran a psyop that their land was horrible and deadly.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/newsletters/archive/2022/05/human-progress-invention-eureka-myth/629811/">The Forgotten Stage of Human Progress</a> (<em>The Atlantic</em>) — Derek Thompson continues his clarion call to implement what we’ve already invented, such as more nuclear power plants. Human progress is not just one damn breakthrough after another. It's not a neat tech tree but a messy tangle of invention, refinement, partial implementation, and political negotiation.</li>
<li><a href="https://parpa.substack.com/p/when-should-an-idea-that-smells-like">When Should an Idea That Smells Like Research Be a Startup?</a> (<em>Ben Reinhardt</em>) — Ben argues that venture backed startups are often not a great fit for doing research, which often takes a long and unpredictable amount of time. You either need a "money factory", or a charismatic leader to convince everybody else that there is in fact a critical path long enough to find it.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.timesofisrael.com/israels-watergen-provides-water-from-air-units-in-former-is-hq-raqqa/">Israel’s Watergen Provides ‘Water-From-Air’ Units to Medical Facility in Syria</a> (<em>Times of Israel</em>) — The Watergen generator, powered by solar energy, converts droplets of moisture from the air into clean water. It's being trialed in Gaza to provide fresh water, since the overused acquifer has been degraded by saltwater intrusion and contaminated by pollutants.</li>
<li><a href="https://freddiedeboer.substack.com/p/just-stop-apologizing?s=r">Just Stop Apologizing</a> (<em>Freddie deBoer</em>) — deBoer points out a core hypocrisy in many progressive communities: restorative justice is embraced as a core value, yet people that transgress the norms of that community and then apologize profusely are not themselves afforded any restorative justice.</li>
<li><a href="https://mysticalsilicon.substack.com/p/my-summary-of-tyler-cowens-approach?s=r">Tyler Cowen's Approach to Leading an Intellectually Fulfilling Life</a> (<em>David Gasca</em>) — Cowen is a prolific writer, podcaster, and infovore. His style of being a fox involves an insatiable curiosity, extensive travel, and in general sampling the best offerings from a variety of obscure fields.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.smithsonianmag.com/history/the-rise-and-fall-of-worlds-fairs-180979946/">The Rise and Fall of World's Fairs</a> <em>(Smithsonian Magazine)</em> — Tracks the evolution of world fairs from "the world's universities" in the 19th century to "sites of entertainment". In many ways, mega theme parks like Disney World EPCOT (Experimental Prototype Community of Tomorrow) are spiritual descendants of world fairs.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.rand.org/pubs/perspectives/PE198.html">Russia's “Firehose of Falsehood” Propaganda Model</a> <em>(RAND Corporation)</em> — Modern Russian propaganda relies on a continuous barrage of invented and inconsistent information. It takes less time to make up facts than it does to verify them, and first impressions are very resilient. This is a wicked problem, argue the authors. Don't expect to "counter the firehose of falsehood with the squirt gun of truth".</li>
<li><a href="https://kk.org/thetechnium/103-bits-of-advice-i-wish-i-had-known/">103 Bits of Advice I Wish I Had Known</a> <em>(Kevin Kelly)</em> — We don't usually fall for listicles, but Kevin Kelly recently turned 70 and dropped some unique 💎's.</li>
<li><a href="https://noahpinion.substack.com/p/interview-ramez-naam-futurist-author">Interview: Ramez Naam, futurist, author, and investor</a> (<em>Noah Smith</em>) — A broad ranging interview with Mez, a treasure trove of information about energy and climate and their ramifications on politics, as well as feedback loops involved. Mez also teases emerging technology, like synthetic "electrofuels" and floating wind farms.</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/@ericmigi/why-pebble-failed-d7be937c6232">Why Pebble Failed</a> <em>(Eric Migicovsky)</em> — Almost a decade after it failed, the CEO of a promising smartwatch company wrote a postmortem highlighting the importance of product-market fit, of having a well communicated long-term vision, and the value of a good marketing team.</li>
</ul>

        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Links for April 2022</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2022/links-for-april-2022"/>
    
    <updated>2022-04-30T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2022/links-for-april-2022</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p><img alt="Generated image of a codex with helicopters." src="/assets/generated/2022-04-30.jpg" /></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/03/25/opinion/oscars-movies-end.html">We Aren’t Just Watching the Decline of the Oscars. We’re Watching the End of the Movies</a> <em>(NYTimes)</em> — Sensationally titled, Douthat gestures at the declining cultural importance of movies, and speculates convincingly about their likely relegation to a stable but niche role like that of theatre, opera, or ballet.</li>
<li><a href="https://aestheticsforbirds.com/2017/09/21/against-rotten-tomatoes/">Against Rotten Tomatoes</a> (<em>Aesthetics for Birds</em>) — Matt Strohl argues that crowdsourced movie rankings the Tomatometer are "mostly a bad thing". Designed to punish bad movies, they also punishes bold and distinct ones, reducing creative risk taking.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.spectator.co.uk/article/i-can-feel-my-heart-hardening-as-the-war-goes-on">I Can Feel My Heart Hardening as the War Goes on</a> (<em>The Spectator</em>) — Pomerantsev considers the parallels the biblical story of Exodus to Russia's genocidal war on Ukraine as he travels home to celebrate Passover in his hometown Kiev. In particular, he wrestles with the puzzle of how to keep your humanity while killing a genocidal enemy.</li>
<li><a href="https://linotype.substack.com/p/the-insidious-cultural-relativism?s=r">The insidious cultural relativism of failure</a> (<em>Linotype</em>) — Stefano argues that it's much easier to climb down a hill if you are confident that the world is full of many hills. However if you think it’s not so full of hills it’s insane to climb down from your comfortable perch!</li>
<li><a href="https://www.newyorker.com/news/q-and-a/why-elon-musk-bought-twitter">Why Elon Musk Bought Twitter</a> (<em>New Yorker</em>) — Twitter is just one of many games Elon Musk is addicted to (we're living in a simulation, right?). Historically, he has created value for his companies by being unhinged on Twitter, but this is a dangerous game since many high-profile people have gotten in trouble for their tweets. Time to fix it!</li>
<li><a href="https://newsletters.theatlantic.com/galaxy-brain/626c8c4e12500c0020ca5f5b/twitter-elon-musk-meme-tweet-debates/">Elon Musk Is Already Grinding Us Down</a> (<em>The Atlantic</em>) — Warzel highlights two dark patterns on twitter, which are likely to be amplified by Musk's changes: 1) The dominance of pithy, short, reductive utterances (memes) over chains of informative tweets (tweetstorms), and 2) The tendency to race to quickly reply to high profile tweets, in order for the reply to be placed in the valuable real estate below.</li>
</ul>

        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Links for March 2022</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2022/links-for-march-2022"/>
    
    <updated>2022-03-31T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2022/links-for-march-2022</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p><img alt="Generated image of nuclear ice breaker as depicted by leonardo davinci in his sketchbook" src="/assets/generated/2022-03-31.jpg" /></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.science.org/content/article/pacific-northwest-s-forest-gardens-were-deliberately-planted-indigenous-people">Pacific Northwest's ‘forest gardens' were deliberately planted by Indigenous people</a> <em>(Science)</em> — It took a long time for researchers to recognize these forest gardens as a human-created landscape at all. A hopeful peek at how "humans have the ability to not just allow biodiversity to flourish, but to be a part of it". Perhaps the dichotomy of hunter-gatherers vs. farmers is overstated?</li>
<li><a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/science/archive/2022/02/biosphere-planetary-intelligence-evolution/622867/">Is Earth Smart</a> <em>(The Atlantic)</em> — Building on the notion of a biosphere (life), the noosphere (intelligent life) and technosphere (technological systems created by intelligent life) present major challenges to survival. Just like the immature biosphere did not really hit its stride until the Great Oxygenation Event, our immature technosphere is actively destructive until an equivalent transition, argue the authors.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.tabletmag.com/sections/news/articles/anti-anti-semitism">Anti-Anti-Semitism (2010)</a> <em>(Tablet Magazine)</em> — A bizarre foray into World Without Nazism, a Kremlin-flavored Anti-Defamation League for the post-Soviet realm. This is especially sinister given the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=J3ugaKoAuNs">denazification propaganda</a> used to justify Russia's invasion of Ukraine.</li>
<li><a href="https://blog.emojipedia.org/vaccine-emoji-comes-to-life/">Vaccine Emoji Comes to Life</a> <em>(Emojipedia)</em> — In response to increased discourse about vaccinations and COVID, the blood-filled syringe emoji (💉) was updated to remove the blood to make it more universal. This raises a bunch of different questions: why is there only a white wine glass emoji, only a red one (🍷)? Famously, Apple changed its pistol emoji into a toy water gun (🔫) in 2016, causing widespread upset. When is it OK to repurpose existing emoji, and when is it not?</li>
<li><a href="https://s2.q4cdn.com/299287126/files/doc_financials/annual/shareholderletter2005.pdf">Amazon Shareholder's Letter (2005)</a> (<em>Jeff Bezos</em>) — Bezos explores the limits of math and data, conceding that many important decisions cannot be made in a math-based way, lamenting "math-based decisions command wide agreement, whereas judgment-based decisions are rightly debated and often controversial, at least until put into practice and demonstrated". Alas, Complexity!</li>
<li><a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/international/archive/2022/02/zelensky-ukraine-president-jewish-hero/622945/">How Zelensky Gave the World a Jewish Hero</a> (<em>The Atlantic</em>) — In addition to a quick recap of Zelenskyy's unlikely path from Russian comedian to Ukranian president, and an aside into the sorry state of <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2018/03/28/most-poles-accept-jews-as-fellow-citizens-and-neighbors-but-a-minority-do-not/ft_18-03-26_polandholocaustlaws_map">Jewish intolerance in Europe</a>, I was heartened to learn that the Jewish community in Ukraine is recovering, for example the newly built <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Menorah_center,_Dnipro">Menorah center in Dnipro</a> reportedly serving 40,000 people a day.</li>
<li><a href="https://detaly.co.il/evrejstvo-prezidenta-zelenskogo-kak-simvol/">Еврейство президента Зеленского как символ</a> (<em>Detali Israel</em>) — A look into the outsized impact of Ukraine on Jewry, including atrocities like Bogdan Khmelnytsky's attempt to eradicate Ukranian Jews, and the Holocaust massacre at Babyn Yar. At the same time, Ukraine has a long history of relative tolerance to Jews, and was the birthplace of many greats: politicians like David Ben-Gurion, Ze'ev Jabotinsky, writers like Isaac Babel, Sholom Alechem, Chaim Bialik. Many American greats descend directly from Ukranian Jews: Leonard Bernstein, Bob Dylan, Noam Chomsky, Steven Spielberg, Mel Brooks, Jon Stewart.</li>
</ul>

        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Links for February 2022</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2022/links-for-february-2022"/>
    
    <updated>2022-02-28T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2022/links-for-february-2022</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p><img alt="Generated image of Georg Cantor contemplating infinity" src="/assets/generated/2022-02-28.jpg" /></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://aeon.co/essays/why-longtermism-is-the-worlds-most-dangerous-secular-credo">Against longtermism</a> (<em>Aeon</em>) — Torres argues that an over-focus on the long term is dangerous because it ignores shorter term existential threats, and encourages endless growth, which itself might be the cause of our problems. As a fan of long term thinking, I found this very provocative. What is the synthesis between pollyannaish beliefs in technology and degrowth?</li>
<li><a href="https://jaygraber.medium.com/web3-is-self-certifying-9dad77fd8d81">Web3 is Self-Certifying</a> (<em>Jay Graber</em>) — Graber describes the concept of self-certifying data, which "enables trust to reside in the data itself, not in where you found it, allowing apps to move away from client-server architectures." Examples of protocols that enable this include git, BitTorrent, IPFS, and SSB.</li>
<li><a href="https://thebaffler.com/salvos/whats-the-point-if-we-cant-have-fun">What’s the Point If We Can’t Have Fun?</a> (<em>David Graeber</em>) – In a rambling article, Graeber highlights Kropotkin's argument that species that cooperate most effectively tend to be the most competitive in the long run. Kropotkin argues that animal cooperation often has nothing to do with survival or reproduction, but is a form of pleasure in itself.</li>
<li><a href="https://longnow.org/essays/richard-feynman-connection-machine/">Feynman and The Connection Machine</a> (<em>Long Now</em>) — A sometimes touching vignette of Richard Feynman, as seen by Danny Hillis, who founded Thinking Machines to build the world's fastest parallel supercomputers in the 1980s. Nobody really knew how to build computers back then, so the problem was left to amateurs like Hillis and Feynman.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2022/02/future-internet-blockchain-investment-banking/621480/">The Internet Is Just Investment Banking Now</a> (<em>The Atlantic</em>) — Argues that Web3 is “the most honest turn of the internet epoch”: many things in our everyday life have become financialized, and while Web2 entrepreneurs have tried to hide that behind a facade of idealism, the new world of crypto at last makes the financialization explicit.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.ft.com/content/a81c934c-cb31-11e9-af46-b09e8bfe60c0">Why Cisco’s ‘spin-ins’ never caught on</a> (<em>Financial Times</em>) — In the 90's, Cisco pioneered the model of 'spin-ins': a group of employees would leave Cisco and form a new company with well defined short-term goals, which if achieved, required Cisco to acquire the venture and possibly breed resentment from less entrepreneurial peers. On the other hand, the downside for the entrepreneurs was also quite high, since they would end up with nothing if no acquisition took place.</li>
<li><a href="/notes/2022/links-for-february-2022/#">Is Old Music Killing New Music?</a> (<em>Ted Gioia</em>) — Top 40 charts, Grammy Awards, and other incarnations of mainstream pop culture seem to be losing their cultural cache. Instead, songs most in demand are by musicians in their 70s and 80s, if not already dead.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.newyorker.com/science/elements/can-you-warm-yourself-with-your-mind">Can You Warm Yourself with Your Mind?</a> (<em>New Yorker</em>) — Studies in Nature show that advanced practitioners of g-tummo meditation can raise their core temperature by 1-2°C, or their extremities by around 10°C. This is done by contracting abdominal and pelvic muscles and visualizing a flame rising from below the navel to the top of the head.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.newsweek.com/clifford-stoll-why-web-wont-be-nirvana-185306">Why the Web Won't Be Nirvana (1995)</a> (<em>Newsweek</em>) — A cantankerous skeptic dumps on the future of the web, producing a litany of predictions which are wrong to various degrees. Revisiting pundits from the past is a useful exercise that reminds us just how difficult the future is to predict.</li>
<li><a href="https://noahpinion.substack.com/p/a-moment-of-clarity">A Moment of Clarity</a> (<em>Noah Smith</em>) — In addition to astute observations on the eve of Russia's war on Ukraine, Smith describes a clear headedness on shared American values that surely must have been felt internally, even by adherents of "warmed-over Chomsky".</li>
</ul>

        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Links for January 2022</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2022/links-for-january-2022"/>
    
    <updated>2022-01-31T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2022/links-for-january-2022</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p><img alt="Generated image of a space shuttle in Leonardo Da Vinci's sketchbook" src="/assets/generated/2022-01-31.jpg" /></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="/notes/2022/links-for-january-2022/">Buy Things, Not Experiences</a> (<em>Harold Lee</em>) – Common wisdom suggests that having a lot of stuff will not bring happiness, but advocates of this "new minimalism" often live in modern houses in expensive neighborhoods. In general, Lee argues that there is no real boundary between things and experiences, and in fact we may have erred too far and are now over-consuming experiences.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.michellelim.org/writing/speaking-in-tales/">Speaking in Tales: conversing in Chinese means constantly alluding to folklore</a> (<em>Michelle Lim</em>) — Lim describes chéng yǔ, commonly used 4-character phrases in Chinese, which are allusions to classical Chinese folk tales. This introduces unique challenges to translations, which lose their evocative impact when you don’t know the story.</li>
</ul>

        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Article highlights of 2021</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2021/article-highlights-of-2021"/>
    
    <updated>2021-12-21T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2021/article-highlights-of-2021</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>Following my yearly tradition (<a href="/notes/2020/article-highlights-of-2020/">2020</a>,
<a href="/notes/2019/article-highlights-of-2019/">2019</a>, and
<a href="/notes/2021/article-highlights-of-2021/notes/2019/reading-in-2018/">2018</a>), here were my favorite articles from 2021.
It's hard to come up with coherent groupings, but overall I definitely read more
about emergence, evolution, equilibrium and complexity-related stuff. I tried to
make sense of Russia, China and where the US sits in the new world order.
Notably, I read a lot of <a href="https://constructionphysics.substack.com">Construction
Physics</a>, as if preparing for an
ambitious but unspecified building project.</p>
<p>I may have overindexed on articles and non-fiction books this year, at the
expense of reading novels. This is at odds with my stated belief in the <a class="wiki" href="https://z3.ca/Power_of_Fiction">Power of Fiction</a>. Looking back at my <a href="/books">book list</a>, I only read two fiction
books the whole year — possibly an all-time low. My aim for 2022 is to double
down on reading for pleasure, relieving pressure to capture every insight.</p>
<p>Happy New Year!</p>
<!--more-->

<h1>Lenses and mental models</h1>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.edge.org/response-detail/11783">Important Concept: Kayfabe</a> (Edge) - Eric Weinstein describes Kayfabe, a term from professional wrestling about a situation where there appears to be a real contest but the outcomes are predetermined. Unsportsmanlike conduct happens from the appearance of actual competition (called "shooting", as opposed to scripted deception, which is called "working"). This phenomenon organically emerged, because real wrestling is pretty monotonous for the audience, and for the participants, features occasional but extreme peril. Weinstein speculates that Kayfabe occurs in other domains too.</li>
<li><a href="https://vitalik.ca/general/2020/11/08/concave.html">Convex and Concave Dispositions</a> (Vitalik Buterin) - Vitalik explores situations where the polarity model (two desirable attributes in conflict with one another) are resolved better by picking one of the poles than trying to find something in-between. His main example is lockdowns: a 100% effective travel ban is far more useful than a half-hearted lockdown. Given the choice of war with country A and war with country B, a little bit of A and B is not generally a great choice. Interesting lens nonetheless.</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/@samo.burja/live-versus-dead-players-2b24f6e9eae2">Live versus Dead Players</a> (Samo Burja) - In Samo's definition, Live Players are able to do new things. Dead players are repeating stereotyped behaviors, often cargo-culting what Live Players have pioneered.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/our-brain-typically-overlooks-this-brilliant-problem-solving-strategy/">Our Brain Typically Overlooks This Brilliant Problem-Solving Strategy</a> (Scientific American) - People often limit their creativity by continually adding new features to a design rather than removing existing ones.</li>
<li><a href="https://taylorpearson.me/ergodicity/">A Big Little Idea Called Ergodicity</a> (Tyler Pearson) - An accessible explanation of ergodicity using startups and Russian Roulette as analogy. In an ensemble probability, the ruin of one individual does not affect the others (eg. you are a VC, "some of your startups may fail", but one of them IPOs, so you still make out like a bandit). In a time probability, the ruin at one point in time affects all future points in time (eg. you are a founder, and years of effort are completely wasted).</li>
<li><a href="https://simonsarris.com/play/">Deliberate Practice for Knowledge Work</a> (Simon Sarris) - Simon answers Andy's question provocatively: "Deliberate practice of knowledge work requires testing knowledge, and that is achieved by doing. Note taking is not the under-studied force of knowledge, play is."</li>
<li><a href="https://jamesclear.com/great-speeches/creativity-in-management-by-john-cleese">Creativity in Management</a> (John Cleese) - Cleese gave a great speech to Video Arts in 1991. Humor is a natural concomitant in the open mode, but it’s a luxury in the closed. I add Cleese to the stable of believers in open, divergent, wandering, exploratory, beer drinking hill finders.</li>
<li><a href="https://marginalrevolution.com/marginalrevolution/2011/03/the-fallacy-of-mood-affiliation.html">The fallacy of mood affiliation</a> (Marginal Revolution) - A form of motivated reasoning where you first choose a mood or attitude, then find confirming evidence that matches the mood.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.edge.org/response-detail/27080">Concept: Bisociation</a> (Edge) - Arthur Koestler, who has transformed into a kind of totem for me over the last few years, coined this word bisociation, which integrates two (or more) apparently incompatible frames of thought. In humor, the canonical example is a pun. For Koestler, the ability to simultaneously view a situation through multiple frames of reference is the source of all creative breakthroughs.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.systemsinnovation.io/post/edge-of-chaos-1">Edge of Chaos</a> (Systems Innovation) - Right between the two extremes, order and chaos, at a kind of abstract phase transition called the edge of chaos, you also find complexity: a class of behaviors in which the components of the system never quite lock into place, yet never dissolve into turbulence.</li>
<li><a href="https://sandwalk.blogspot.com/2008/02/evolution-as-tinkering.html">Evolution as Tinkering</a> (Larry Moran) — Argues that natural selection has no analogy with any aspect of human behavior, but the closest thing might be tinkering. Often without even knowing what she’s going to create, the tinkerer uses whatever she can find to make a workable object.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.lewissociety.org/innerring/">The Inner Ring</a> (C. S. Lewis) - Every organization has a legible hierarchy. A general is superior to a colonel, and a colonel to a captain. But the way things really work is via a series of concentric rings, a shadow organization that is illegible to the uninitiated. To a young person, just entering on adult life, the world seems full of “insides,” full of delightful intimacies and confidentialities, and he desires to enter them. But if he follows that desire he will reach no “inside” that is worth reaching. The true road lies in quite another direction: mastering a craft.</li>
<li><a href="https://apenwarr.ca/log/20211201">100 years of whatever this will be</a> (apenwarr) - Decentralized, distributed systems aren't a panacea, and often need to be regulated. Furthermore, if no regulation is present, some other shadow hierarchy will emerge, and it may not be one that we like.</li>
<li><a href="https://astralcodexten.substack.com/p/secrets-of-the-great-families">Secrets Of The Great Families</a> (Scott Alexander) - A fun overview of a few impressive families and their multitalented members. I learned about the Tagores and their amazing names, all of which end with "dranath". Seriously though, how do great families remain great without reversion to the mean? Three ways, at least: 1. having a lot of children, and 2. marrying people from other great families, 3. children of great people feel pressure to do something great.</li>
</ul>
<h1>American Culture Wars</h1>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.cato.org/blog/global-leader-obsolete-technology">A Global Leader in Obsolete Technology</a> (Cato Institute) - Punchy article mocks high-speed rail for being functionally obsolete technology. Slower than flying, less convenient than driving, and more expensive than either one. Most of the argument against has to do with cost, and even China's rail efforts have put it into great debt. The author suggests building more highway instead. It's a pretty weak argument, but could be buttressed if self-driving cars and trucks become a norm. I highlight this because I'm a rail fan and think this was a valuable perspective.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/02/11/opinion/california-san-francisco-schools.html">California Is Making Liberals Squirm</a> (NYTimes) - Ezra Klein criticizes progressives for being symbolically liberal, but operationally conservative. Signs professing love for Immigrants and how much BLM are placed in communities that organize against efforts that would bring those values closer to reality.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/ideas/archive/2021/01/how-big-tech-impeached-donald-trump/617643/">The Meaning of Trump’s Mass Cancellation</a> (The Atlantic) - A critique of swashbuckling CEOs pretending to do a great deed by banning Trump from their platforms. In fact they punished a lame-duck president at the nadir of his power.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/opinion/articles/2021-09-19/woke-movement-is-global-and-america-should-be-mostly-proud">Why Wokeism Will Rule the World</a> (Bloomberg) - Tyler Cowen of all people calls for a bit more nuance when criticizing wokeness. Indeed, we are a little bit too woke here in the US private sector. It's also unclear whether wokeness will ultimately help Black Americans. But globally, it's pretty clear that more wokeness might not be such a bad thing. It would be nice if Afghans let women work again, and if Saudi Arabia would stop executing gay people.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.interfluidity.com/v2/8392.html">Liberalism and class</a> (Interfluidity) - The obligation to be tolerant in a liberal society has shifted from “try not to be a dick” to understanding the sensitivities of diverse communities and taking care to respect them. But this has the paradoxical effect of further isolating the "professional" class from the bulk of the public, for whom the burden of staying current with everchanging mores is simply too much. The requirement of diplomacy has become a kind of regressive tax. The same high standards are expected of everyone, but only a certain class of people can easily afford to meet them.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/09/19/opinion/supply-side-progressivism.html">The Economic Mistake the Left Is Finally Confronting</a> (New York Times)† — Ezra Klein argues that the world we should build toward requires more than redistribution: it requires progress, inventions, and advances that will boost productivity and ultimately grow the supply of goods and services.</li>
<li><a href="https://daily.jstor.org/how-america-tried-and-failed-to-solve-its-servant-problem/">How America Tried (and Failed) to Solve Its "Servant Problem"</a> (JSTOR Daily) - In the early part of the twentieth century, most middle-class American homes had at least one servant. The “servant problem” boiled down to the fact that wealthier women wanted reliable, cheap, willing labor, but poorer women (many of them black) did not want to be their servants. Somewhat unsatisfying since the article presents no real explanation, but an interesting snapshot of a long forgotten era.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2004/12/12/magazine/strategic-extremism.html">Strategic Extremism, published 2004</a> (New York Times) - In the mid-20th century, a majority Americans that voted were moderates, their views shaped by the Big Three TV networks. But over time the Big Three's hold grew weaker, and the shifting media landscape made it easier to appeal to smaller and smaller groups of people. Televangelists began to appeal to Evangelicals. Fox News appealed to the right. Direct mail allowed politicians to narrowcast to more specific demographics. Modern social media lets you do this easily, and at scale, and we have seen the results.</li>
</ul>
<h1>Russia</h1>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.economist.com/graphic-detail/2021/10/11/russian-elections-once-again-had-a-suspiciously-neat-result">Russian elections once again had a suspiciously neat result</a> (The Economist) - unusually high number of turnout and vote-share results were multiples of five in this most recent Russian election (eg, 50%, 55%, 60%), a tell-tale sign of manipulation. Two thoughts: first, hire some smarter election frausters next time. Second, I was tickled by this since it's so directly related to <a href="https://smus.com/diffusion-of-literacy-canada/">age heaping</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.jewishbookcouncil.org/pb-daily/papa-stalin-and-the-happy-family">Papa Stalin and the Happy Family</a> (Jewish Book Council) - Underscores the role of propaganda in Soviet Jewish children's literature, which tended to sketch portraits of children with absent or incompetent parents, mostly focusing on Kvitko.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.atlasobscura.com/articles/soviet-childrens-books-in-india">How Soviet Children's Books Became Collectors' Items in India</a> (Atlas Obscura) - A look into the obscure world of Soviet children's literature like Денискины рассказы translated into Marathi, as part of an Comintern play of the early Soviets. But there was feedback too, eg. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rinI7d3mSyA">Бродяга (1951)</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.lrb.co.uk/blog/2021/july/information-sovereignty">Information Sovereignty</a> (London Review of Books) - A system based on cynicism and paranoia means people end up distrusting everything. The Kremlin has, by most accounts, produced a decent vaccine for the coronavirus. But the government can’t persuade the Russian people that they need to take it. Only 13 per cent are vaccinated, despite Putin’s claim that the Sputnik V is ‘just as reliable as Kalashnikov assault rifles’</li>
</ul>
<h1>China</h1>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2012/02/16/opinion/why-chinas-political-model-is-superior.html">Why China’s Political Model Is Superior</a> (New York Times) - Written in 2012, I found this to be a surprising article for the gray lady to publish.</li>
<li><a href="https://noahpinion.substack.com/p/why-is-china-smashing-its-tech-industry">Why is China smashing its tech industry?</a> (Noah Smith)† - Smith argues that, after the Cold War, the West’s priorities shifted from survival to enjoyment, but China has doubled down on survival, moving toward the view that “hard tech is more valuable than products that take us more deeply into the digital world.” That, in turn, explains the crackdown on sectors that don’t help China stockpile national power.</li>
<li><a href="https://lillianli.substack.com/p/the-short-notes-the-mechanism-of">The Mechanism of the Five-Year Plan</a> (Chinese Characteristics)† — Tech analyst Lillian Li explains how the Chinese government’s famous Five-Year Plans work, drawing a parallel to big tech companies’ “OKR” processes.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.sixthtone.com/news/1007589/https%3A%2F%2Fwww.sixthtone.com%2Fnews%2F1007589%2Ftired-of-running-in-place%252C-young-chinese-lie-down">Tired of Running in Place, Young Chinese ‘Lie Down’</a> (Sixth Tone) - Some young Chinese are resolving to just scrape by, exerting the bare minimum effort at an unfulfilling job, as opposed to the futility of raging against the capitalist machine. When you can’t catch up with society’s development — say, skyrocketing home prices — tang ping (lying Down) is actually the most rational choice,” he said.</li>
</ul>
<h1>Religion, broadly construed</h1>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://theconversation.com/how-limiting-latin-mass-may-become-the-defining-moment-for-pope-francis-164826">How limiting Latin Mass may become the defining moment for Pope Francis</a> (The Conversation) - Vatican II (1965) decreed that the mass be translated into the local vernacular. Hardcore Catholics really wanted their mass conducted in Latin, some were excommunicated over it. In 2007, Pope Benedict XVI expanded the use of the traditional Latin Mass. Then in 2021, Pope Francis reverted back to the Vatican II rules, banning the Latin Mass once more. See also <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/08/12/opinion/pope-francis-latin-mass.html">this enraged response from a Rad Trad</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://aeon.co/ideas/we-need-highly-formal-rituals-in-order-to-make-life-more-democratic">We need highly formal rituals in order to make life more democratic</a> (Aeon) - A somewhat naive take on the need for collective rituals, and an implementation of this as a pseudo religion in College residence. Borders on cosplay, but I do agree in spirit: "I hope we all come out of quarantine wearing our Sunday best, ringing bells, lighting candles and burning incense."</li>
<li><a href="https://charleseisenstein.org/essays/girard-series-part-1-the-death-of-the-festival/">The Death of the Festival</a> (Charles Eisenstein) - My encounter with some of the ideas of Rene Girard. "Without respite from the conventions of the social order and without respite from our roles within it, we go crazy as well ... A real festival is essentially a repeated, ritualized riot that has evolved its own pattern language."</li>
<li><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2018/03/30/arts/music/bach-religion-music.html">Johann Sebastian Bach Was More Religious Than You Might Think</a> (NYTimes) - I already thought Bach was pretty religious, but this article makes his religiosity more specific and extreme, and grounded in his own annotations of the Calov bible, a biblical tome compiled by Abraham Clov with Martin Luther's sermons and writings. The article paints Bach at odds with progressivist currents even of his own day. Bach favored biblical revelation over human reason, disparaged notions of human autonomy, held non-Luteran faiths in contempt, exalted German goodness, and the divine right of kings.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/10/03/opinion/last-jew-afghanistan-zebulon-simentov.html">What Happens When the Last Jew Leaves Afghanistan</a> (NYTimes) - It costs little to wax nostalgic about departed Jews when one lives in a place where diversity, rather than being a living human challenge, is a fairy tale from the past.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-020-01811-w">Hundreds of Israel’s Archaeological Sites Are Vanishing Under Concrete</a> (Nature)† — Explores the tension between “salvage digs,” done to document archaeological remains in danger of destruction due to Israel’s extensive development projects, and the commercial sources of archaeological funding in Israel.</li>
</ul>
<h1>Geopolitics and War</h1>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://peterturchin.com/cliodynamica/state-collapse-and-nation-building-in-afghanistan/">State Collapse and Nation Building in Afghanistan</a> (Peter Turchin) — The now ex-president of Afghanistan, Ashraf Ghani, started his career as an academic and wrote a book called Fixing Failed States. Turchin reviews the book and argues that deliberate state-building is hard, but perhaps accidental state-building has been happening in the background in Afghanistan.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/international/archive/2018/04/terrorism-governance-religion/556817/">When Terrorists and Criminals Govern Better Than Governments</a> (The Atlantic)† — Argues that hierarchies imposed from outside are not part of the local feedback system and thus may be ineffective: “if people can’t get the leadership they crave from the state, they’ll find somebody else to do the job.”</li>
<li><a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2021/sep/24/mismatch-of-mindsets-why-the-taliban-won-in-afghanistan">Mismatch of Mindsets: Why the Taliban Won in Afghanistan</a> (The Guardian)† — An anthropologist argues that many recent military blunders can be attributed to Westerners’ confusion around their own values and the values of others, and an assumption that all parties are willing to negotiate and compromise more than they really are, especially when it comes to group belonging and sacred values.</li>
</ul>
<h1>Long-term thinking</h1>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://longnow.org/ideas/02021/10/22/dune-foundation-and-the-allure-of-science-fiction-that-thinks-long-term/">“Dune,” “Foundation,” and the Allure of Science Fiction that Thinks Long-Term</a> (Long Now) - Asimov and Herbert took diametrically opposed stances — the trust-the-plan humanistic optimism of Foundation in one corner, the esoteric pessimism of Dune in the other. The author speculates that Dune fits the current "moment of broader cultural gloominess" better than Foundation does.</li>
<li><a href="https://applieddivinitystudies.com/stagnation/index.html">Isolated Demands for Rigour in New Optimism</a> (Applied Divinity Studies) - A battery of optimism is upon us. You should be ashamed of yourself, says the author. "The recent trend of rhetoric against stagnation is not founded in evidence or driven by data. It is pure mood affiliation."</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/the-long-now-foundation/scenario-planning-for-the-long-term-c68a75df169b">Scenario Planning for the Long-term</a> (Long Now) - Scenario planning is not about prediction; it’s about making better decisions. That is, if you really do your homework well in multiple scenarios, you’re probably going to see this future.</li>
<li><a href="https://constancecrozier.com/2020/04/16/forecasting-s-curves-is-hard/">Forecasting s-curves is hard</a> (Constance Crozier) - Many social and biological systems follow the S-curve. What first looks like exponential growth, slows and increases linearly, and finally levels off (therefore end up looking like a wonky s). Constance shows how difficult it is to mathematically extrapolate S-curves in <a href="https://vimeo.com/408599958">a compelling video</a>.</li>
</ul>
<h1>Construction techniques</h1>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://austinvernon.eth.link/blog/construction.html">So, You Want to Build a House More Efficiently</a> (Austin Vernon) - There's a naive high modern take that is tempting to apply to house construction: "Let's build buildings like cars". Unfortunately this doesn't work: materials are too heavy and no cost dominates the cost of new home construction.</li>
<li><a href="https://constructionphysics.substack.com/p/mass-effects">Mass Effects</a> (Construction Physics) - Advancing construction technology over the last 200 years has seen the weight and volume of construction materials plummet. The Eiffel Tower is twice as tall as the Pyramid of Giza, but uses 1/300 of the volume. Less material means easier transportation, simpler assembly, smaller foundation. But thick and heavy building elements confer advantages like being less prone to vibration, more thermal and sound proofing, and feeling nicer.</li>
<li><a href="https://constructionphysics.substack.com/p/balloon-framing-is-worse-is-better">Balloon Framing is Worse is Better</a> (Construction Physics) - Impressed by Austin Vernon's post, I decided to follow up and read the source. This article digs into pre-fabrication and transport vs. on-site construction, and explains why the balloon frame has persisted for as long as it has.</li>
<li><a href="https://constructionphysics.substack.com/p/where-are-the-robotic-bricklayers">Where Are The Robotic Bricklayers?</a> (Construction Physics) - Masonry seemed like the perfect candidate for mechanization, but a hundred years of limited success suggests there’s some aspect to it that prevents a machine from easily doing it. At least a couple of reasons: 1. Mortar has sort of complex physical properties, eg. viscosity increases when it’s moved or shaken, 2. Heavy bricks require larger, more expensive machinery, and 3. In the US, masonry walls are constructed with a large amount of reinforcement.</li>
<li><a href="https://constructionphysics.substack.com/p/logistics-production-volume-and-industrialized">Logistics, Production Volume, and Industrialized Building</a> (Construction Physics) Why have prefab homes not completely replaced bespoke, on-site construction? Economies of scale naturally push us towards this end of the spectrum. The answer lies in product value density. Buildings have low product-value density, and the logistics costs for transporting a fully assembled building are enormous. Even if transport was easy, there are still be significant site costs. Permitting, grading, setting foundations, etc. can be up to 20% of overall construction costs, and aren't easily addressed by any sort of mass-production method.</li>
<li><a href="https://ifstudies.org/blog/the-diy-family">The DIY Family</a> (Institute for Family Studies) - Like a modern lower end version of a Gilded Age baron, many Americans are now catered to by an army of part-time servants (grocery &amp; restaurant delivery, nannies, uber drivers, house cleaning). This article points to a pandemic spurred reversal. Closing childcare centers meant more parents choosing to stay at home and watch the kids. More people were doing DIY projects than calling the handyman. More people cooking for themselves. Will this trend persist over the long term? I don't think so.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.bbc.com/future/article/20210810-the-ancient-persian-way-to-keep-cool">The ancient Persian way to keep cool</a> (BBC) - Wind catchers were ancient Persian buildings designed with natural cooling systems. They were tall so they could catch wind, funnel it down to the dwelling below, while depositing any sand or debris at the foot of the tower. Yazd, UNESCO world heritage site is home to many.</li>
</ul>
<h1>Economics</h1>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/FcRt3xAF4ynojfj6G/what-do-gdp-growth-curves-really-mean">What Do GDP Growth Curves Really Mean?</a> (Less Wrong) - Even granting that GDP doesn’t measure happiness, or leisure time, or household work, GDP calculations are misleading because they ignore the effects of technological revolutions. GDP is calculated at recent prices, dominated by the things which are expensive today (eg. real estate). Things which are cheap today are ignored in hindsight. So goods whose prices drop dramatically because of some technological revolution are downweighted to near-zero.</li>
<li><a href="https://tunnelingonline.com/why-tunnels-in-the-us-cost-much-more-than-anywhere-else-in-the-world">Why Tunnels in The US Cost Much More Than Anywhere Else in The World</a> (Tunnel Business Magazine) - It costs $2.5B/mi in New York, $900M/mi in other parts of the US and Australia, $500M/mi in Europe and the Middle East, and $200M/mi in India &amp; China to build tunnels. Many complex cost drivers, including labor costs, labor laws, regulations, bureaucracy.</li>
<li><a href="https://patrickwyman.substack.com/p/american-gentry">American Gentry</a> (Patrick Wyman) - Patrick points at a certain kind of usually invisible wealthy family, whose wealth is not flashy, but stays in the family for generations. The sort of family that owns seventeen McDonald’s franchises in eastern Tennessee, or owners of the third-biggest construction company in Bakersfield.</li>
<li><a href="https://commoncog.com/blog/cash-flow-games/">The Games People Play With Cash Flow</a> (Common Cog) - Deep dive into trade-offs of raising capital early. Succinctly answers why so many profitable SaaS companies still want to take on venture funding. "in many businesses, you must spend money now to make money later. This implies that you’ll need a source of capital at the start of many business ventures".</li>
<li><a href="https://evonomics.com/why-behavioral-economics-is-itself-biased/">Why Behavioral Economics is Itself Biased</a> (Evonomics) - Turns out that the study showing that there is no "Hot Hand" in basketball was biased, and in fact the phenomenon is real. The winds of change are blowing, and behavioral economics is not immune to its own critiques.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/ideas/archive/2021/04/the-autopilot-economy/618497/">Could Index Funds Be ‘Worse Than Marxism’?</a> (The Atlantic) - Some $11 trillion is now invested in index funds, up from $2 trillion a decade ago. And as of 2019, more money is invested in passive funds than in active funds in the United States. Index funds increase inertia, and they get too dominant, capital will get allocated only to the big companies and not necessarily to good, promising, or efficient companies. Also, index fund managers like Vanguard get outsized control of votes in companies in the index. Perhaps we could all use a little more of that manic stock-picking energy, not less.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.profgalloway.com/the-martian/">The Martian</a> (No Mercy/No Malice) - A look at Elon Musk's financial machinations and outsized influence on markets.</li>
<li><a href="https://theprepared.com/blog/why-ykk-zippers-are-the-brown-mms-of-product-design-look-at-the-little-details-to-judge-overall-gear-quality/">Why YKK zippers are the brown M&amp;Ms of product design</a> (The Prepared) - A surprising look at YKK, a Japanese manufacturer of high quality zippers. The authors suggest using this and other signs to look for quality in products.</li>
<li><a href="https://cointelegraph.com/magazine/2020/09/24/wtf-happened-in-1971">WTF happened in 1971</a> (Coin Telegraph) - Still very confused on this one. But alarmingly,  hours to buy a single unit of the S&amp;P 500 has increased to an all time high of 126 hours today, up from an average of 30.9 hours since 1860.</li>
</ul>
<h1>Tech: AI to XR</h1>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.folklore.org/StoryView.py?project=Macintosh&amp;story=The_Macintosh_Spirit.txt">The Macintosh Spirit</a> (Folklore) - One of many great anecdotes about early Apple culture which shaped the Macintosh. The original team was driven more by artistic values, oblivious to competition, where the goal was to be transcendently brilliant and insanely great. And there was a Pirate mentality: "it's better to be a pirate than join the navy".</li>
<li><a href="https://sandimetz.com/blog/2016/1/20/the-wrong-abstraction">The Wrong Abstraction</a> (Sandi Metz) - Abstraction is an important part of computer programming. It helps reduce duplication, and reason about things as systems interacting with one another. But we often over do it, anticipating a complicated future that never comes, or end up with the wrong abstraction. If you find yourself in a situation like this, go backward! It's better to unroll the abstraction, duplicate code, and find new, more meaningful abstractions.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.swyx.io/part-time-creator-manifesto/">The Part Time Creator Manifesto</a> (Shawn Wang) - Not the greatest article, but a nice existence proof that some people are able to combine a full-time job with profitable part-time work, and live to tell the tale.</li>
<li><a href="https://cdixon.org/2009/12/30/whats-strategic-for-google">What's strategic for Google?</a> (Craig Dixon) - Hardboiled look at Google strategy circa 2009.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.incompleteideas.net/IncIdeas/BitterLesson.html">The Bitter Lesson</a> (Rich Sutton) - Rich names a trend that has been happening in ML research for a long time now. Throwing large amounts of compute at pretty generic neural networks yields better results than hand-crafted, specialized non-neural model architectures.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.theverge.com/2021/4/27/22403741/deepfake-geography-satellite-imagery-ai-generated-fakes-threat">Deepfake satellite imagery poses a not-so-distant threat, warn geographers</a> (The Verge) - Far from presenting deepfakes cartography as a novel challenge, "humans have been lying with maps for pretty much as long as maps have existed, they say, from mythological geographies devised by ancient civilizations like the Babylonians, to modern propaganda maps distributed during wartime". No mention of Potemkin villages, but same genre.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2021/10/facebook-metaverse-was-always-terrible/620546/">Hey, Facebook, I Made a Metaverse 27 Years Ago</a> (The Atlantic) Zuck isn't building the metaverse because he has a remarkable new vision of how things could be. The futures it imagines have been imagined a thousand times before, and usually better.</li>
<li><a href="https://dlc.dlib.indiana.edu/dlc/bitstream/handle/10535/5962/Silence%2520is%2520a%2520Commons.html?isAllowed=y&amp;sequence=1">Ivan Illich: Silence is a Commons</a> (indiana.edu) - Ivan Illich is doing to computers what he did to education (De-Schooling Society, 1971), to energy (Energy and Equity, 1974), to medicine (Medical Nemesis, 1975), etc.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.interaction-design.org/literature/article/design-for-the-future-but-balance-it-with-your-users-present">The MAYA Principle: Design for the Future, but Balance it with Your Users’ Present</a> (Interaction Design Foundation)† - Google Glass has not become the success it was anticipated to become. How do we learn to strike the right balance between the most advanced design and our users’ ability to accept our product?</li>
<li><a href="https://thefrailestthing.com/2014/08/21/preserving-the-person-in-the-emerging-kingdom-of-technological-force/">Preserving the Person in the Emerging Kingdom of Technological Force</a> (The Frailest Thing) - L. M. Sacasas presents a coherent critical theory take on why it is that Google Glass has so far been rejected by society.</li>
<li><a href="https://glazkov.com/2021/08/20/the-miracle-count/">The miracle count</a> (Dimitri Glazkov)† - Put simply, the miracle count is the number of unlikely events that we need to happen for a project to succeed. If your startup needs zero miracles to work, it probably isn't a defensible startup. If your startup needs multiple miracles, it probably isn't going to work.</li>
<li><a href="https://alexdanco.com/2020/02/28/vcs-should-play-bridge/">VCs should play bridge</a> (Alex Danco) - In bridge, your bids have to serve two purposes: they are both literal commitments (if your bid wins, you must follow through with it) and also coded signals which you use to try and telegraph information to your partner about where you see opportunity. This seems like a useful analogy to understand insanely high startup valuations.</li>
<li><a href="https://alexdanco.com/2021/01/11/why-the-canadian-tech-scene-doesnt-work/">Why the Canadian Tech Scene Doesn’t Work</a> (Alex Danco) - Canada has too many Bad Angel Investors. They focus too much on guaranteed winnings. They want to see structure: milestones, accelerators, incubators, mentorship programs, and other process-heavy things. Canada needs more Good Angels playing an infinite game. They need to contribute to a community; not in order to win something definite, but to earn the right to keep participating in the scene. I found this explanation a useful application of an otherwise annoying book.</li>
</ul>
<h1>Innovation systems</h1>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2013/07/29/slow-ideas">Spreading Slow Ideas</a> (New Yorker) - Considers the speed of technological diffusion by comparing the fast spread of anesthesia to the slow spread of antiseptics. It comes down to fast feedback loops of seeing effects and technical complexity of applying the tech. Very insightful deep dive into more modern examples of slow diffusion of medical ideas and how to catalyze the process with human connection.</li>
<li><a href="https://guzey.com/ideas-not-mattering-is-a-psyop/">Ideas not mattering is a psyop</a> (Alexey Guzey) - Against the "ideas are cheap" trope, which I often invoke. I think this changed my view from "all that matters is execution" to some more balanced version of ideas mattering, execution mattering, and a million other things mattering.</li>
<li><a href="https://reactionwheel.net/2015/10/the-deployment-age.html">The Deployment Age</a> (Jerry Neumann) - A somewhat long overview of Carlotta Perez's theory of technological change. Roughly speaking, Progress advances in surges, and each surge has two major stages. The first is "Installation", where a new technology irrupts and results in a speculative frenzy. The bubble pops, leads to a lot of broken hearts and empty wallets, but the frenzy leaves behind useful infrastructure. The second stage is "Deployment", during which the new technologies really revolutionize the world and reach maturity.</li>
<li><a href="https://mattsclancy.substack.com/p/combinatorial-innovation-and-technological">Combinatorial Innovation and Technological Progress in the Very Long Run</a> (What’s New Under the Sun)† — Introduces the concept of “combinatorial innovation,” where new inventions are composed of two or more older inventions; shows how this should, in theory, lead to explosive growth in technological progress; and explores some limiting factors that, in practice, limit us to slowing or constant progress.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.collaborativefund.com/blog/experts/">Experts From A World That No Longer Exists</a> (Collaborative Fund) - The biggest risk to an evolving system is that you become bogged down by experts from a world that no longer exists.  Clarke's First Law: "When a distinguished but elderly scientist states that something is possible, he is almost certainly right. When he states that something is impossible, he is probably wrong." Henry Ford has a remedy for this problem: don't keep a record of failures: "If you keep on recording all of your failures you will shortly have a list showing that there is nothing left for you to try – whereas it by no means follows because one man has failed in a certain method that another man will not succeed". Definitely thought provoking, and interesting example of note taking as an info hazard.</li>
<li><a href="https://avc.com/2021/04/the-vision-thing/">The Vision Thing</a> (Fred Wilson) - Leadership comes in two flavors, visionary leadership and operational leadership. Founders are almost always visionaries and hired CEOs are almost always operators.</li>
<li><a href="https://rootsofprogress.org/a-career-path-for-invention">We need a career path for invention</a> (Roots of Progress) - “Inventor” is not a role one can be hired for. The aspiring inventor finds themselves straddling science and business. They could join a research lab, or become an engineer at a technology-based company. In either case, they will be misaligned with their environment.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.technologyreview.com/2021/07/13/1028295/proud-solutionist-history-technology-industry/">Why I’m a proud solutionist</a> (Jason Crawford) - Jason highlights that there is a middle way between starry-eyed optimism and nihilistic pessimism. Nothing new here, but a good reminder of a stance that I am sympathetic to.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/business/archive/2014/10/why-germany-is-so-much-better-at-training-its-workers/381550/">Why Germany Is So Much Better at Training Its Workers</a> (The Atlantic) - Laments how hard it is to imagine many American firms, generally focused on short-term financial gain, building the kind of in-house training centers we saw at every German plant. They focus on "Dual training", which captures the idea at the heart of every apprenticeship: Trainees split their days between classroom instruction at a vocational school and on-the-job time at a company.</li>
</ul>
<h1>Urban design</h1>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://urbankchoze.blogspot.com/2014/04/japanese-zoning.html">Japanese Zoning</a> (Urban kchoze) - US zoning laws impose one or two exclusive uses for every zone. Japanese laws tend to view things more as the maximum nuisance level to tolerate in each zone, but every use that is considered to be less of a nuisance is still allowed. So low-nuisance uses are allowed essentially everywhere. How did American zoning get so prescriptive and over-regulated? In general I am enjoying articles that point to a better system, or suggest concrete improvements to the existing one.</li>
<li><a href="https://devonzuegel.com/post/urban-density-is-a-tragedy-of-the-commons">Urban sprawl is a tragedy of the commons</a> (Devon Zuegel) - Space and access form a polarity. You want to have a big house, but you also want it to be close to places you like and need. Acknowledges that the underlying coordination problem is wicked, but also that there are many low-hanging fruit to increase access to amazing things without sacrificing space.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.ben-evans.com/benedictevans/2017/3/20/cars-and-second-order-consequences">Cars and second order consequences</a> (Benedict Evans) - Evans follows two major trends in cars through some speculative scenarios: moving to electric means much more than replacing the gas tank with a battery, and moving to autonomy means much more than ending accidents. What happens to public transport? To parking garages? To long commutes? To surveillance due to multiple video cameras in every car?</li>
<li><a href="http://www.theguardian.com/cities/2016/aug/12/lost-cities-merv-worlds-biggest-city-razed-turkmenistan">Lost cities #5: how the magnificent city of Merv was razed – and never recovered</a> (The Guardian) - I only learned about Merv recently from <a class="wiki" href="https://z3.ca/Lost_Enlightenment_by_Frederick_Starr">Lost Enlightenment by Frederick Starr</a>. A shocking story of collapse — from the largest city in the world in the 13th century to dusty, windswept remains. Even the name is lost.</li>
<li><a href="https://noahpinion.substack.com/p/drawing-pictures-of-cities">Drawing pictures of cities</a> (Noah Smith) - Smith breaks down what makes the famous Solar Punk image !<a class="wiki" href="https://z3.ca/Imperial_Boy_Solar_Punk_Art.png">Imperial Boy Solar Punk Art.png</a> so appealing. I loved the systematic breakdown of solarpunk aesthetics, which is still nascent and thus impervious to analysis.</li>
</ul>
<h1>Movable type</h1>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://tricycle.org/magazine/buddhist-history-moveable-type/">The Buddhist History of Moveable Type</a> (Tricycle) - A deep look into early Buddhist Zen prints using metal typesetting. This predated Gutenberg’s press, but was not practical. It did not included mechanisms modified from wine or oil presses that allowed for lowering a metal frame over the top of the paper. The improved method was even, reliable, and fast.</li>
<li><a href="https://blog.gatunka.com/2009/09/30/japanese-typewriters/">Japanese Typewriters</a> (Gatunka) - A mechanical kanji typewriter is obviously complex for the sheer number of characters involved. But further difficulties arose from complicated glyphs such as 曇 or 驚, required striking with additional force to compensate for the large surface area of the typeface. Some echoes back to the printing press and challenges with movable type.</li>
</ul>
<h1>Climate change and resilience</h1>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://blogs.ubc.ca/michaelpidwirny/2017/11/02/climate-change-challenges-for-alpine-ski-resorts-in-western-canada/">Climate Change Challenges for Alpine Ski Resorts in Western Canada</a> - A deep look at how climate change will affect ski resorts over the next half-century. I really liked this analysis because it was scientific and specific, not hand-wringing, but also extremely sobering in terms of implications: "Under the worst-case scenario (by 2085) all of the coastal resorts will become much too warm to support winter recreation".</li>
<li><a href="https://alexsteffen.substack.com/p/ruggedize-your-life">Ruggedize Your Life</a> (The Snap Forward) - No place on Earth will escape climate and ecological upheaval, but some are better than others. Mostly this is a process of elimination: discard from consideration the places with severe risks, or multiple overlapping risks, and take a closer look at what’s left. The old advice that it’s smart to buy the smallest house in the best neighborhood you can afford is especially true from a "shit hitting the fan" perspective.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.wired.com/story/is-it-better-to-plant-trees-or-let-forests-regrow-naturally/">Is It Better to Plant Trees or Let Forests Regrow Naturally?</a> (Wired) - Planting a trillion trees over the next three decades would be a huge logistical challenge. A trillion is a big number. If natural forest growth is cheaper and better, does that make sense?</li>
<li><a href="https://rootsofprogress.org/devanney-on-the-nuclear-flop">Why has nuclear power been a flop?</a> (Roots of Progress) - A multi-faceted look at Nuclear energy failure in the US. Super interesting angle is regulation around radiation levels. Specifically, <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/nceh/radiation/alara.html">ALARA: As Low As Reasonably Achievable</a> "might seem like a sensible approach, until you realize that it eliminates, by definition, any chance for nuclear power to be cheaper than its competition."</li>
<li><a href="https://www.lowtechmagazine.com/2021/05/how-to-design-a-sailing-ship-for-the-21st-century.html">How to design a sailing ship for the 21st century?</a> (Low Tech Magazine) - Seriously considers what it would take to rebuild global shipping on sailboats. Docking a 500 ton sailboat under sail? No thanks — we'll need tugboats! How practical it would be given today's population and appetites? (Not very)</li>
</ul>
<h1>Internet culture</h1>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://society.robinsloan.com/archive/checkpoints/">Checkpoints</a> (Robin Sloan) - Made me aware of an internet subculture Robin calls checkpointing, after checkpoints in JRPG games which typically come between dangerous sections. Barely surviving, you come by surprise, to peaceful oasis where you can save your game before the boss fight. People have been leaving heartfelt comments to this effect. You have to <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Q9XTqQbuavI">see it</a> to believe it.</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/@samo.burja/the-youtube-revolution-in-knowledge-transfer-cb701f82096a">The YouTube Revolution in Knowledge Transfer</a> (Samo Burja)† — Samo observes that an overlooked benefit of YouTube is that it allows novices to observe experts at work, reminiscent of the master-apprentice model. This has unlocked a form of mass-scale tacit knowledge transmission that is historically unprecedented.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.theverge.com/2014/8/20/6046003/a-history-of-metaphors-for-the-internet">A history of metaphors for the internet</a> (The Verge) - If the internet is a highway, the government should regulate what people do on it. The cloud is weightless and intentionally vague, in sharp contrast with the industrial reality of remote datacenters. Skimps on a few interesting ones, like filesystems, which are an analogy from filing cabinets. And also the modern obsession with the Metaverse, a science fiction analogy.</li>
</ul>
<h1>Books</h1>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://adactio.com/extras/notesontheculture/">A Few Notes On The Culture</a> (Iain M. Banks) - In which the author goes deep on his book series on The Culture. A fascinating tidbit which echoes in the books: "A planned economy can be more productive — and more morally desirable — than one left to market forces."</li>
<li><a href="https://lareviewofbooks.org/article/heresies-of-dune/">Heresies of “Dune”</a> (Los Angeles Review of Books) - Frank Herbert's grandparents helped found a socialist commune in Washington State, north of Tacoma. His father was raised there, and Herbert spent many of his young years there. Growing up, he rebelled and become a republican.</li>
<li><a href="https://commoncog.com/blog/the-3-kinds-of-non-fiction-book/">The three kinds of non-fiction books</a> (Commonplace)† - There are three kinds of non-fiction book: 💁‍♀️ narrative, 🌳 tree, and 🌿 branch. Tree books are books that lay out a framework of ideas (eg. Thinking Fast &amp; Slow). Branch books consist of a single idea. IMHO, these shouldn't be read.</li>
</ul>
<h1>Medicine and health</h1>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://reallifemag.com/doctors-orders/">Doctor’s Orders</a> (Real Life)† — A deep dive into vaccine hesitancy through the lens of a broader trend of the medicalization of society: when previously non-medical issues become medical and thus fixable, medical knowledge is elevated to the status of society’s ground truth, and medical advertising targets the individual consumer.</li>
<li><a href="https://qz.com/1010684/all-the-wellness-products-american-love-to-buy-are-sold-on-both-infowars-and-goop/">All the "wellness" products Americans love to buy are sold on both Infowars and Goop</a> (Quartz) - Many of the alternative-medicine ingredients in Amanda Bacon's wellness Moon Juice brand are sold—with very different branding—on the Infowars store, run by Alex Jones, a conspiracy theorist. The horseshoe theory of craziness.</li>
<li><a href="https://time.com/5752114/nazi-military-drugs/">How Methamphetamine Became a Key Part of Nazi Military Strategy</a> (TIME) - Pervitin, a methamphetamine (aka speed) helped German soldiers go on working for 36 to 50 hours without feeling any noticeable fatigue. Part of the speed of the Blitzkrieg literally came from speed. The drug was even dispensed to pilots and tank crews in the form of chocolate bars known as Fliegerschokolade and Panzerschokolade.</li>
<li><a href="https://aeon.co/essays/why-theres-no-such-thing-as-the-mind-and-nothing-is-mental">The mind does not exist</a> (Aeon) - Somewhat incoherent argument against the terms 'mind' and 'mental'. Mainly linked because of a pointer to a field called Psychoneuroimmunology. A fascinating study by Ader &amp; Cohen showed that the nervous system can affect the immune system. In the same way that Pavlov's dogs can be conditioned to drool on hearing a bell ring, rats given sugar water became immunosuppressed.</li>
</ul>
<p>†: Previously recommended in <a href="https://read.fluxcollective.org/">The FLUX Review</a>.</p>

        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Article highlights of 2020</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2020/article-highlights-of-2020"/>
    
    <updated>2020-12-26T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2020/article-highlights-of-2020</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>It's the most wonderful time of the year again! Following <a href="/notes/2019/article-highlights-of-2019/">last year's
summary</a>, here were my top reads for
2020. Last year I vowed to read fewer articles because they felt way more junky
than books do. I haven't changed my mind on this matter, but I was compelled to
try to understand this especially unusual year.</p>
<!--more-->

<h1>Education</h1>
<ul>
<li>An elite private school in Sydney, Australia, the alma mater of three prime ministers, banned laptops in 2016 and required students to handwrite essays through the tenth grade: the headmaster said the school found money spent on interactive white boards, laptops, and the associated software was a total waste. <a href="https://americanaffairsjournal.org/2019/08/rotten-stem-how-technology-corrupts-education/">Rotten STEM: How Technology Corrupts Education</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.vox.com/2020/1/8/21051869/indoor-air-pollution-student-achievement">Installing Air Filters in Classrooms Has Surprisingly Large Educational Benefits</a></li>
<li>The best methods are therefore those that supply comprehensible input in low anxiety situations, containing messages that students really want to hear. These methods do not force early production in the second language. <a href="https://www.sk.com.br/sk-krash-english.html">Stephen Krashen's Theory of Second Language Acquisition</a></li>
</ul>
<h1>Invention</h1>
<ul>
<li>Consolidation. Today’s cloud and mobile companies — Amazon, Microsoft, Apple, and Google — may very well be the GM, Ford, and Chrysler of the 21st century. <a href="https://stratechery.com/2020/the-end-of-the-beginning/">The End of the Beginning</a></li>
<li>Saul Griffith remains impressive. <a href="https://www.inc.com/magazine/20100201/saul-griffiths-house-of-cool-ideas.html">Saul Griffith's House of Cool Ideas</a></li>
<li>What if the government bought the most valuable patents from its inventors, thus unlocking whole industries for more innovation? Main problem is how to price them. <a href="https://www.tenentrepreneurs.org/blog/innovation-eyes-on-the-prize">Innovation: Eyes on the Prize</a></li>
<li>More and more online activity is sinking into the cozyweb (away from public internet). <a href="https://breakingsmart.substack.com/p/the-extended-internet-universe">The Extended Internet Universe</a></li>
<li>We overestimate the impact of technological progress but underestimate the impact of cultural and social shifts. <a href="http://nautil.us/issue/65/in-plain-sight/why-futurism-has-a-cultural-blindspot-rp">Why Futurism Has a Cultural Blindspot</a></li>
<li>Unimportant problems are often more fun to work on, and ultimately you never know how important they really are. <a href="http://yosefk.com/blog/work-on-unimportant-problems.html">Work on unimportant problems</a></li>
</ul>
<h1>Self help</h1>
<ul>
<li>A worthy goal for a year is to learn enough about a subject so that you can’t believe how ignorant you were a year earlier. <a href="https://kk.org/thetechnium/68-bits-of-unsolicited-advice/">68 Bits of Unsolicited Advice</a></li>
<li>When a difficulty comes your way, you should feel proud and excited, like “a wrestler whom God, like a trainer, has paired with a tough young buck.” <a href="https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2016/12/19/how-to-be-a-stoic">How to Be a Stoic</a></li>
<li>Look for smart people and hard problems. Smart people tend to clump together, and if you can find such a clump, it's probably worthwhile to join it. <a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/hs.html">What You'll Wish You'd Known</a></li>
<li>Rationality used to be this capacious concept that included reasonableness, but no longer. <a href="https://www.vox.com/future-perfect/2020/1/20/21068423/rationality-behavioral-economics-psychology-reasonable-decisions">Is rationality overrated?</a></li>
<li>It now feels okay to have an ordinary life, to not make big contributions, to be an ordinary person. I never felt like that before. <a href="https://edelwax.medium.com/narcissism-4c314beb39eb">Narcissism</a></li>
<li>Leonardo da Vinci wrote: …the more minutely you describe, the more you will confuse the mind of the reader and the more you will remove him from knowledge of the thing described. Therefore it is necessary to make a drawing. <a href="https://www.bbc.com/worklife/article/20200910-the-benefits-of-note-taking-by-hand">The Benefits of Note-Taking by Hand</a></li>
<li>They offer conceptual scaffolding for answering what I consider to be the most important question of our time: <em>How can we be good ancestors?</em>. By 01700 most clocks had minute hands and by 01800 second hands were standard. <a href="https://medium.com/the-long-now-foundation/six-ways-to-think-long-term-da373b3377a4">Six Ways to Think Long-term</a></li>
</ul>
<h1>Software</h1>
<ul>
<li>Google's new triumvirate: Mr. Pichai, Mr. Kent Walker, and Ms. Porat. <a href="https://www.economist.com/briefing/2020/07/30/googles-problems-are-bigger-than-just-the-antitrust-case">Google’s problems are bigger than just the antitrust case</a></li>
<li>Maybe something has changed about the nature of innovation, at least in software. <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2020/01/why-silicon-valley-and-big-tech-dont-innovate-anymore/604969/">Silicon Valley Abandons the Culture That Made It the Envy of the World</a></li>
<li>People are switching from Go to Rust. I haven't switched to Go yet! <a href="https://blog.discord.com/why-discord-is-switching-from-go-to-rust-a190bbca2b1f">Why Discord is switching from Go to Rust</a></li>
<li>There certainly will be $10 billion dollar companies started within segments slow to adopt technology: legal tech, construction, agriculture, and mining are all prime candidates for massive new technology entrants. <a href="https://luttig.substack.com/p/when-tailwinds-vanish">When Tailwinds Vanish</a></li>
<li>A deep look into Clubhouse, with lots of interesting hot takes. <a href="https://divinations.substack.com/p/inside-the-clubhouse">Inside the Clubhouse</a></li>
<li>Proximity Chat: you have an avatar or icon that can move around a virtual space. There are two broad metaphors behind proximity chat platforms: table-based and map-based. <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/zoom-parties-proximity-chat/">A Mission to Make Virtual Parties Actually Fun</a></li>
<li>Because information is formless, the metaphors we use to describe it are particularly powerful: a highway, cyber-space, surfing. <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2014/8/20/6046003/a-history-of-metaphors-for-the-internet">A History of Metaphors for the Internet</a></li>
<li>We were spoiled by the old, weird Google that did things like Books because they could, throwing it in the teeth of the publishers, or Wave, an experiment in interactivity that in many ways is still ahead of its time. They did things because they hadn’t been done. <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2020/11/11/rip-google-music-one-of-the-companys-last-examples-of-generosity/">RIP Google Music</a></li>
<li>Should you join a big company or start a startup? This frequently debated question paints a picture of a world where the only choice is between being a cog at a giant semi-monopoly, or taking investment money in the hopes of one day growing to be head cog at a giant semi-monopoly. <a href="https://scattered-thoughts.net/writing/small-tech/">Small tech</a></li>
</ul>
<h1>Culture</h1>
<ul>
<li>Half of single adults – and a majority of single women – are not on the dating market <a href="https://www.pewsocialtrends.org/2020/08/20/nearly-half-of-u-s-adults-say-dating-has-gotten-harder-for-most-people-in-the-last-10-years/">Nearly Half of U.S. Adults Say Dating Has Gotten Harder for Most People in the Last 10 Years</a></li>
<li>Why don't science fiction and fantasy take root in Israeli soil? Maybe it's because tying SF to the Torah would lead to becoming a mini Salman Rushdie. Maybe it's because Israel first appeared in a work of fantasy - The Jewish State by Herzl. <a href="https://www.haaretz.com/1.5472801">Never-never land</a></li>
<li>The personal lives of science fiction writers. Isaac Asimov died of AIDS, and Arthur C. Clarke was gay. Three rules and you're out. <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/culture/archive/2020/01/isaac-asimovs-throwback-literary-legacy/605815/">Isaac Asimov’s Throwback Vision of the Future</a></li>
<li>From most quarters of Japan there emanates a vaguely-defined, yet distinct fear and loathing of the internet (c. 2009, likely obsolete) <a href="http://neojaponisme.com/2009/05/19/the-fear-of-the-internet/">The Fear... of the Internet</a></li>
<li>Kvitko, on the other hand — like many of his compatriots — sketches portraits of children with absent or incompetent parents. They must overcome this deficiency by falling back on their own internal resources as well as those of the Soviet state, the ultimate dispenser of care and guidance. <a href="https://www.jewishbookcouncil.org/pb-daily/papa-stalin-and-the-happy-family">Papa Stalin and the Happy Family</a></li>
<li>I, like Gibson, have absolutely no idea what the physical world will be like in sixty years. <a href="https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2019/12/16/how-william-gibson-keeps-his-science-fiction-real">How William Gibson Keeps His Science Fiction Real</a></li>
<li>I learned a lot about bears. <a href="https://www.grizzlytimes.org/single-post/2018/12/18/Bear-Dreaming-Of-Wonder-in-Winter">Bear Dreaming: Of Wonder in Winter</a></li>
<li>I am trying to be a good novelist, and hoping that people will forgive me for being a bad correspondent. <a href="https://www.nealstephenson.com/why-i-am-a-bad-correspondent.html">Neal Stephenson - Why I Am a Bad Correspondent</a></li>
<li>Some $40 bottles of Okanagan cabernet sauvignon have sold for nearly $1,000 in China. <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/09/19/world/canada/british-columbia-wine-Okanagan-Valley.html">Canada’s Napa Valley Seeks Elusive Audience: Canadian Wine Drinkers</a></li>
<li>This value is known as 公德心: in Mandarin, gongdexin; in Japanese, kootokushin; in Korean, kongdkshim; and in English, public-spiritedness. <a href="https://news.mit.edu/2020/meanings-face-masks-emma-teng-0819">Historian Emma Teng on Face Masks</a></li>
</ul>
<h1>Medicine</h1>
<ul>
<li>It was thought to be caused by noxious air — “malaria”, for example, literally means “bad air". <a href="https://antonhowes.substack.com/p/age-of-invention-a-breath-of-fresh">Age of Invention: A Breath of Fresh Air</a></li>
<li>The typical development time for a vaccine against a new disease is over five years. We've done really well this time around. <a href="https://www.gatesnotes.com/Health/Pandemic-Innovation">The first modern pandemic</a></li>
<li>We must immediately begin random sampling of the population using both PCR testing that tells up about active infections and antibody tests that informs about who has been infected in the past. <a href="https://cliffmass.blogspot.com/2020/04/flying-blind-on-coronavirus-why-random.html">Flying Blind on Coronavirus: Why Random Testing is so Important</a></li>
<li>Rick bought his own qPCR machine and thinks that this is the future of biotech. He may well be right! <a href="https://medium.com/@RickByers/the-dawn-of-personal-biotech-cb0af0d52e4c">The dawn of personal biotech</a></li>
<li>Countries have two options: either they fight it hard now or they will suffer a massive epidemic. (May 28) <a href="https://tomaspueyo.medium.com/coronavirus-the-hammer-and-the-dance-be9337092b56">Coronavirus: The Hammer and the Dance</a></li>
<li>Many health experts, including the surgeon general of the United States, told the public simultaneously that masks weren’t necessary for protecting the general public and that health care workers needed the dwindling supply. <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/03/17/opinion/coronavirus-face-masks.html">Why Telling People They Don’t Need Masks Backfired</a></li>
<li>You can apparently saturate an entire city with Tamiflu if the entire city had the bird flu. <a href="https://www.economist.com/open-future/2020/04/04/how-society-can-overcome-covid-19">How society can overcome covid-19</a></li>
<li>The plague resurfaced roughly every 20 years from 1348 to 1665. 40 outbreaks in 300 years! And many more crazy pandemic stories. <a href="https://www.history.com/news/pandemics-end-plague-cholera-black-death-smallpox">How 5 of History's Worst Pandemics Finally Ended</a></li>
<li>But the warnings of thoughtful shutdown skeptics warrant careful study, not stigma rooted in the false pretense that they don’t have any plausible concerns or value human life. <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/ideas/archive/2020/05/take-shutdown-skeptics-seriously/611419/">Take the Shutdown Skeptics Seriously</a></li>
<li>The obliteration of all microbes as often and aggressively as possible is not always appropriate. As with any medicine, more does not mean better. Not enough time to shower? Washing underarms, groin, and feet may actually be healthier. <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2020/07/hygiene-is-overrated/612235/">You’re Showering Too Much</a></li>
</ul>
<h1>Environment</h1>
<ul>
<li>Fire professionals should be considering ecology and picking their fights: letting fires that pose little risk burn through the stockpiles of fuels. Yet that’s not the mission. <a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/they-know-how-to-prevent-megafires-why-wont-anybody-listen">They Know How to Prevent Megafires. Why Won’t Anybody Listen?</a></li>
<li>Someone built a wall out of many different types of stone to see how well each material stands the test of time. <a href="https://www.nist.gov/blogs/taking-measure/test-time-nists-wall-many-stones">The Test of Time: NIST’s Wall of Many Stones</a></li>
<li>Fixating on a future long beyond the lives of our great-great-great-grandchildren might be as defeatist as worrying about apocalypse with every little advance made by human societies. <a href="https://slate.com/technology/2020/01/doomsday-clock-10000-year-long-now.html">A Tale of Two Clocks: Doomsday vs. the Long Now</a></li>
<li>On building an app for friends and family, with no greater ambitions. <a href="https://www.robinsloan.com/notes/home-cooked-app/">An app can be a home-cooked meal</a></li>
<li>An inspiring position paper from Ink &amp; Switch about owning your own data and storing it locally rather than on someone's cloud. <a href="https://www.inkandswitch.com/local-first.html">Local-first software</a></li>
<li>Back in 2008, a Bank of Korea report found that of 5,586 companies older than 200 years in 41 countries, 56% of them were in Japan. <a href="https://www.bbc.com/worklife/article/20200211-why-are-so-many-old-companies-in-japan">Why so many of the world’s oldest companies are in Japan</a></li>
<li>A man chronicled his transatlantic journey as a passenger on a cargo ship, something I've dreamed of doing for years. <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/travel/2020/jan/07/cargo-ship-train-rail-to-vancouver-canada-low-carbon-travel-europe">I didn't want to fly – so I took a cargo ship from Germany to Canada</a></li>
<li>If Zincton is approved it will take eight years to build all phases. It would become the first brand new major ski resort in BC in almost half a century. <a href="https://dailyhive.com/vancouver/zincton-mountain-village">New major ski resort proposed for BC interior</a></li>
<li>Tree planting drones, tree planting robots, drones to map forests, and other surprising uses of advanced technology. <a href="https://www.fastcompany.com/90504789/these-drones-can-plant-40000-trees-in-a-month-by-2028-theyll-have-planted-1-billion">These Drones Will Plant 40,000 Trees in a Month. By 2028, They’ll Have Planted 1 Billion</a></li>
<li>Only really huge declines in CO2 emissions, far greater that what is occurring during this lockdown period, will be necessary to really move the needle on global warming. <a href="https://cliffmass.blogspot.com/2020/04/is-atmospheric-co2-declining-from-covid.html">Is Atmospheric CO2 Declining From the Covid Economic Collapse?</a></li>
<li>Tree planting can often worsen outcomes for everything from the number of bird, insect, and plant species to measures of canopy cover, tree density, and forest structure. Still haven't learned from SLAS? Nature knows best. <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/is-it-better-to-plant-trees-or-let-forests-regrow-naturally/">Is It Better to Plant Trees or Let Forests Regrow Naturally?</a></li>
<li>Unlike all other forms of marine aquaculture, commercially grown bivalve shellfish have been identified as the only sustainable form of aquaculture that has no negative impact on the environment. <a href="https://www.eco-business.com/opinion/sustainable-shellfish-aquaculture/">Sustainable Shellfish Aquaculture</a></li>
</ul>
<h1>Economics</h1>
<ul>
<li>Seattle got rid of parking quotas and the requirement for property owners to live on site, and now allows two ADUs. <a href="https://www.sightline.org/2019/07/01/seattle-approves-best-backyard-cottages-rules-united-states/">Seattle Says Yes to the Best Rules in America for Backyard Cottages</a></li>
<li>Keynes once proposed that we could jump-start an economy by paying half the unemployed people to dig holes and the other half to fill them in. <a href="https://locusmag.com/2020/07/cory-doctorow-full-employment/">Cory Doctorow: Full Employment</a></li>
<li>Open borders and mass immigration are a victory for the bosses. Andrew Carnegie in 1886 compared immigration to “a golden stream which flows into the country each year”. Interesting ITT-worthy material. <a href="http://peterturchin.com/cliodynamica/the-left-case-against-open-borders/">The Left Case against Open Borders</a></li>
<li>Airlines got a bailout. Parents are on their own. <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/06/29/opinion/coronavirus-school-reopening.html">Remote School Is a Nightmare. Few in Power Care</a></li>
<li>Really old money. <a href="https://qz.com/694340/the-richest-families-in-florence-in-1427-are-still-the-richest-families-in-florence/">The richest families in Florence in 1427 are still the richest families in Florence</a></li>
<li>Supply chain resilience is underrated. TSMC is still dependent on a single Dutch supplier for its advanced lithography systems. That supplier, ASML, is in turn dependent on a single factory in Germany for its optical engine. <a href="https://sloanreview.mit.edu/article/is-it-time-to-rethink-globalized-supply-chains/">Is It Time to Rethink Globalized Supply Chains?</a></li>
<li>What the U.S. really needs to do is reconstitute its communities of engineering practice. That will require treating manufacturing work, even in low-margin goods, as fundamentally valuable <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/opinion/articles/2020-05-07/why-american-manufacturing-can-t-handle-the-coronavirus">Why America Can Make Semiconductors but Not Swabs</a></li>
<li>People with limited understanding of business think that business is all about making profits. But those who actually run businesses know that running a business is all about managing cash flows. <a href="https://commoncog.com/blog/cash-flow-games/">The Games People Play With Cash Flow</a></li>
<li>I know the real San Francisco, and I know that its underlying issues do not differ dramatically from the problems facing the other rest of America or any other corner in our hyper-capitalistic planet. <a href="https://om.co/2020/11/24/on-not-leaving-san-francisco/">On Not Leaving San Francisco</a></li>
<li>Relative cost per mile of tunnel around the world. NYC: $2B, Other US &amp; Australia: $750M, Europe &amp; Mid-east: $350M, Asia: $150M. <a href="https://tunnelingonline.com/why-tunnels-in-the-us-cost-much-more-than-anywhere-else-in-the-world/">Why Tunnels in the US Cost Much More Than Anywhere Else in the World</a></li>
<li>Why do companies so often cling to having general managers in charge of business units? At Apple, vice presidents are in charge of functions, not products. <a href="https://hbr.org/2020/11/how-apple-is-organized-for-innovation">How Apple Is Organized for Innovation</a></li>
<li>Understanding where our modern standard of living comes from, at a basic level, is a responsibility of every citizen in an industrial civilization. <a href="https://rootsofprogress.org/industrial-literacy">Industrial Literacy</a></li>
<li>The real unemployment rate (U-6) is a broader definition of unemployment than the official unemployment rate (U-3). In June 2020, it was 18%. It's down from the 22.8% rate in April. That's almost as bad as the 25% rate during the Great Depression. <a href="https://www.thebalance.com/what-is-the-real-unemployment-rate-3306198">What Is the Real Unemployment Rate?</a></li>
</ul>
<h1>Politics</h1>
<ul>
<li>Behind the bluster and rhetoric of populist discourse there lies a deeper emotion: resentment. <a href="https://foreignpolicy.com/2019/09/18/the-west-has-a-resentment-epidemic-populism/">The West Has a Resentment Epidemic</a></li>
<li>For Warren, the problem with modern American capitalism is that it is not nearly capitalist enough. It has been captured by special interests, which are strangling competition. <a href="https://foreignpolicy.com/2019/12/12/elizabeth-socialist-understand-capitalism-pro-market-leftist/">Socialists Will Never Understand Elizabeth Warren</a></li>
<li>Unfortunately, the problem of nuclear arms is still very serious today. <a href="https://www.japantimes.co.jp/opinion/2006/04/21/commentary/world-commentary/turning-point-at-chernobyl/">Turning point at Chernobyl by Gorbachev</a></li>
<li>One in five Millennials thinks the Communist Manifesto better “guarantees freedom and equality” than the Declaration of Independence and thinks society would be better off if the government abolished private property; one in six thinks the world would be better off if the Soviet Union were still around. <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/ideas/archive/2020/03/youngs-dont-care-about-ussr/607249/">Young People Don’t Care About the U.S.S.R.</a></li>
<li>Richard Rorty cautioned the left to not accidentally the whole system, and for the "reformist left" to remain within the framework of constitutional democracy. <a href="https://www.vox.com/policy-and-politics/2017/2/9/14543938/donald-trump-richard-rorty-election-liberalism-conservatives">Richard Rorty’s prescient warnings for the American left</a></li>
<li>The goal of disinformation is not to dominate the informational space but to dilute it. “Flood the zone with shit,” was Steve Bannon’s infamous advice for dealing with the media. <a href="https://foreignpolicy.com/2020/04/21/democracies-disinformation-russia-china-homegrown/">Democracies Can’t Blame Putin for Their Disinformation Problem</a></li>
<li>The roles of warrior cop, traffic patroller, tax collector, and counselor are hopelessly intertwined. <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/ideas/archive/2020/06/unbundle-police/612913/">Unbundle the Police</a></li>
<li>If you are not doing “antiracist work” you are ipso facto a racist. A terrifying sentiment. <a href="https://nymag.com/intelligencer/2020/06/andrew-sullivan-is-there-still-room-for-debate.html">Is There Still Room for Debate?</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.technologyreview.com/2020/07/15/1004950/how-to-talk-to-conspiracy-theorists-and-still-be-kind/">How to talk to conspiracy theorists—and still be kind</a></li>
<li>Gentry classes are generally hereditary, and the Americans are no exception. Example: a single family owning seventeen McDonald’s franchises in eastern Tennessee, or enrich themselves from ownership of the third-biggest construction company in Bakersfield. <a href="https://patrickwyman.substack.com/p/american-gentry">American Gentry</a></li>
<li>Trump improved over his 2016 performance among Black women (+4 percentage points), Black men (+5), Latinas (+3) and Latinos (+4).” A third of Latino men, and a quarter of Latino women, picked Trump. Trump’s support was up among Asians and Muslims, and apparently doubled among self-identified LGBT voters. <a href="https://quillette.com/2020/11/09/america-has-serious-problems-its-time-to-stop-blaming-them-on-trumpism/">America Has Serious Problems. It’s Time to Stop Blaming Them on ‘Trumpism’</a></li>
<li>The composition of Trump’s followers, with a large minority of Latino voters and a nontrivial number of Black voters, makes their motivations more various and complicated than just racism. <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/ideas/archive/2020/11/theres-no-escaping-who-we-have-become/616992/">Face the Bitter Truth</a></li>
<li>The problem is that neither side has shown any willingness or understanding to solve the structural problems that have brought about the current revolutionary situation. <a href="http://peterturchin.com/cliodynamica/america-in-november-2020-a-structural-demographic-view-from-alpha-centauri/">Structural-Demographic View from Alpha Centauri</a></li>
<li>The Gray Lady promulgates dumb ideas, for example, the worst caste systems in human history includes the United States alongside Nazi Germany. <a href="https://www.bariweiss.com/resignation-letter">Resignation Letter</a></li>
</ul>

        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Books highlights of 2019</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2019/books-highlights-of-2019"/>
    
    <updated>2019-12-31T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2019/books-highlights-of-2019</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>I’ve been reading and summarizing for five years now (cue Ratatat). I’m not sure that it’s helped much with retention, but at the very least, having an easily searchable corpus of my book-related notes is worthwhile.</p>
<p>A decent year for fiction, I finally read <a href="/books/invisible-cities-by-italo-calvino/">Invisible Cities</a>, which I enjoyed not viscerally, but more as an art piece. I liked <a href="/books/the-fiddler-is-a-good-woman/">The Fiddler is a Good Woman</a> for the author’s ability to retell the same sordid tale from multiple perspectives. <a href="http://localhost:5500/books/diamond-age-by-stephenson-audio/">Diamond Age</a> was a collection of incredible ideas and surprisingly relevant for my job. I also enjoyed <a href="/books/hyperion-by-dan-simmons-audio/">Hyperion</a>, especially Sol Weintraub’s tale, which touched me deeply. <a href="/books/the-fifth-season-by-n-k-jemisin/">The Fifth Season</a> was interesting, but I have some identitarian reservations. I think my overall fiction highlight was <a href="/books/the-odyssey-translated-by-emily-wilson-audio/">Homer’s Odyssey translated by Emily Wilson</a>.</p>
<p>I read two non-fiction books which were a little too extreme for my tastes: <a href="/books/deschooling-society-by-ivan-illich">Deschooling Society</a>, which just read like an angry and ill considered screed and <a href="/books/radical-markets-by-posner-and-weyl/">Radical Markets</a>, which had some really interesting ideas, but presented as a whole seemed ridiculous. I really enjoyed <a href="/books/timefulness-by-marcia-bjornerud-audio/">Timefulness</a>, a whirlwind overview of geology, and <a href="/books/range-by-david-epstein-audio/">Range</a>, an ode to generalists. The standout non-fiction for me was <a href="/books/seeing-like-a-state-by-james-scott/">Seeing Like a State</a>, which will continue to turn over in my mind for years to come. I listened to fewer history lectures than usual, but can wholeheartedly recommend <a href="/books/the-story-of-medieval-england-audio/">The Story of Medieval England</a>. Instead, I focused on parenting books, which are pretty bad as a genre. That said, <a href="/books/the-new-father/">The New Father</a> served as a worthwhile companion to skim during the first year of Eliana’s life, and <a href="/books/yes-brain-by-siegel-and-bryson/">Yes Brain</a> had practical suggestions for digesting mindfulness into something that small children might be able to understand.</p>
<p>I also begun a new long-term book summarization project, which is to digest <a href="">Asimov's Chronology of Science and Discovery</a>, and visualize it as a Civ-style tech tree. Hopefully I’ll have something to report on that front in 2020!</p>

        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Article highlights of 2019</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2019/article-highlights-of-2019"/>
    
    <updated>2019-12-31T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2019/article-highlights-of-2019</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>I’m still using Instapaper for reading online things, although in 2020, my aim is to read articles (even) less, in favor of books.</p>
<ul>
<li>Try to install a radar system with one job: Searching for chances to give a compliment. <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/everybody-is-stupid-except-you/201812/compliments-how-get-happy-and-make-better-world">Compliments: How to Get Happy and Make a Better World</a></li>
<li>Warren Buffett’s metric of success is “Do the people you care about love you back?” <a href="https://www.gatesnotes.com/About-Bill-Gates/Year-in-Review-2018">What I learned at work this year</a></li>
<li>As Edelman points out, if YouTube really cared about our intentions and values, when we logged on to learn ukulele it would try to serve that need — and then send us off to practice! <a href="https://time.com/5505431/internet-feel-awful-dignity/">The Internet Can Make Us Feel Awful. It Doesn't Have to Be That Way</a></li>
<li>Wisdom as the ultimate virtue. Really solid framing in favor of centrism. <a href="https://www.shanesnow.com/articles/values/">How to be good: A theory about Virtues &amp; Values</a></li>
</ul>
<!--more-->

<ul>
<li>From 1200 to 1745, 21-year-olds would reach an average age of anywhere between 62 and 70 years. <a href="https://www.bbc.com/future/article/20181002-how-long-did-ancient-people-live-life-span-versus-longevity">Do we really live longer than our ancestors?</a></li>
<li>Nick Cave isn’t just an awesome musician, but is also quite eloquent. “What we are actually listening to is human limitation and the audacity to transcend it.” <a href="https://www.brainpickings.org/2019/01/24/nick-cave-music-ai/">Music, Feeling, and Transcendence: Nick Cave on AI, Awe, and the Splendor of Our Human Limitations</a></li>
<li>Seismic air guns are widely used to map the sea floor. They are incredibly loud and disruptive to ocean fauna. <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/01/22/science/oceans-whales-noise-offshore-drilling.html">Oceans Are Getting Louder, Posing Potential Threats to Marine Life</a></li>
<li>Unlike traditional two-by-four lumber, cross-laminated timber (CLT) consists of layers of wood glued together to form solid, thick panels that can be made in custom dimensions for anything from walls and floors to beams and roofs. CLT is being used to build mid-rise buildings, including big swaths of Google Sidewalk in Toronto. <a href="https://www.financialexpress.com/industry/skyscrapers-made-of-wood-make-a-return-nudged-by-google/1482316/">Skyscrapers made of wood make a return, nudged by google</a></li>
<li>Peter Turchin: “the way forward to sustaining and increasing the well-being of large segments of population is not to abolish government, but to evolve institutions that keep bureaucrats working for the benefit of the population, rather than themselves.” <a href="http://peterturchin.com/cliodynamica/an-anarchist-view-of-human-social-evolution/">An Anarchist View of Human Social Evolution</a></li>
<li>The scary thing about GPT-2-generated text is that it flows very naturally if you’re just skimming. <a href="https://srconstantin.wordpress.com/2019/02/25/humans-who-are-not-concentrating-are-not-general-intelligences/">Humans Who Are Not Concentrating Are Not General Intelligences</a></li>
<li>I disagree with Stratechery that the web is better today than it was when we were punching monkeys, but he writes terrifyingly about Spotify’s role in today’s podcast marketplace. <a href="https://stratechery.com/2019/spotifys-podcast-aggregation-play/">Spotify’s Podcast Aggregation Play</a></li>
<li>A stark look at the rising costs of digital goods and their implications for working poor. <a href="https://reallifemag.com/well-played-store-credit/">Video games are teaching users how to enjoy perpetually renting consumer goods rather than owning them</a></li>
<li>I thought the Albedo effect only applied to melting ice caps, but as it turns out, it also applies to clouds! <a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/cloud-loss-could-add-8-degrees-to-global-warming-20190225/">A World Without Clouds</a></li>
<li>What came first, the moralizing God or the complex society? Evidence points to the latter, followed by Gods-as-divine-policemen. <a href="https://gizmodo.com/humans-built-complex-societies-before-they-invented-mor-1833436320">Humans Built Complex Societies Before They Invented Moral Gods</a></li>
<li>The American public is broadly pessimistic about its country’s future, and this pessimism correlates with education level. <a href="https://www.pewsocialtrends.org/2019/03/21/public-sees-an-america-in-decline-on-many-fronts/">Looking to the Future, Public Sees an America in Decline on Many Fronts</a></li>
<li>As wealthy kids are growing up with less screen time, poor kids are growing up with more. <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/03/23/sunday-review/human-contact-luxury-screens.html">Human Contact Is Now a Luxury Good</a></li>
<li>Stop building to ship until you’ve first built to learn. <a href="https://uxdesign.cc/building-to-learn-977a8cd88ced?">https://uxdesign.cc/building-to-learn-977a8cd88ced?</a></li>
<li>A charitable look at Post-modernism holds that there is no privileged lens with which to view the world; that even empiricism is suspect, because it too has a tendency to reproduce and reify the power structures in which in exists. <a href="https://socratic-form-microscopy.com/2019/04/03/post-modernism-and-political-diversity/">https://socratic-form-microscopy.com/2019/04/03/post-modernism-and-political-diversity/</a></li>
<li>Texas produces more wind power than every other state in the country, four times as much as the runner-up, California. <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2019/04/11/magazine/climate-change-exxon-renewable-energy.html?mtrref=www.instapaper.com&amp;gwh=A83B2941A03E83BDCAE36DF6FD0D3189&amp;gwt=pay&amp;assetType=REGIWALL">https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2019/04/11/magazine/climate-change-exxon-renewable-energy.html?mtrref=www.instapaper.com&amp;gwh=A83B2941A03E83BDCAE36DF6FD0D3189&amp;gwt=pay&amp;assetType=REGIWALL</a></li>
<li>While I disagree that there may be a difference between personal and professional values, I found this brief article to be a useful exercise. <a href="https://blog.alexmaccaw.com/a-value-driven-life">https://blog.alexmaccaw.com/a-value-driven-life</a></li>
<li>Formidable pays employees $20/hr for contributions (outside of normal work time) to OSS and tech communities or even a personal hack project purely for fun and learning, as long as it’s released under an OSI license. <a href="https://formidable.com/blog/2019/sauce-program/">https://formidable.com/blog/2019/sauce-program/</a></li>
<li>Look at how everyone else is doing it (the likely local maxima) and then find a better way. <a href="https://www.nateliason.com/blog/local-maxima">https://www.nateliason.com/blog/local-maxima</a></li>
<li>A look into some of Duolingo’s limitations. Learning a language with an app should be a starting point, not the end.<a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/05/04/smarter-living/500-days-of-duolingo-what-you-can-and-cant-learn-from-a-language-app.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2019/05/04/smarter-living/500-days-of-duolingo-what-you-can-and-cant-learn-from-a-language-app.html</a></li>
<li>A Facebook co-founder wants the US government to fix Facebook. <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/05/09/opinion/sunday/chris-hughes-facebook-zuckerberg.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2019/05/09/opinion/sunday/chris-hughes-facebook-zuckerberg.html</a></li>
<li>How might we design mediums in which “reading” is the same as “understanding”? <a href="https://andymatuschak.org/books/">https://andymatuschak.org/books/</a></li>
<li>Safe playgrounds lead to boredom, which tends toward rash stunts like turning somersaults on top of climbing frames and standing on the shoulders of others on the swings. So let’s make playgrounds a little more dangerous! <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/05/10/well/family/adventure-playgrounds-junk-playgrounds.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2019/05/10/well/family/adventure-playgrounds-junk-playgrounds.html</a></li>
<li>What Republicans want to do with I.C.E. and border walls, wealthy progressive Democrats are doing with zoning and NIMBYism. Ouch. <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/05/22/opinion/california-housing-nimby.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2019/05/22/opinion/california-housing-nimby.html</a></li>
<li>We were certain that more communication would make everything better. Arrogantly, we ignored history and learned a lesson that has been in the curriculum since the Tower of Babel. <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/why-we-love-tech-defense-difficult-industry/">https://www.wired.com/story/why-we-love-tech-defense-difficult-industry/</a></li>
<li>What are signs that a player is alive? One strong sign is a player doing things outside of their domain. For example, Putin is a live player. The Russian state is doing things they haven’t done in a long time, like annexing Crimea… <a href="https://medium.com/@samo.burja/live-versus-dead-players-2b24f6e9eae2">https://medium.com/@samo.burja/live-versus-dead-players-2b24f6e9eae2</a></li>
<li>San Francisco is a stunningly beautiful and continuously innovative city, cursed to always be considered one or two generations past its peak, like a rowboat chasing the horizon. <a href="https://www.sfchronicle.com/oursf/article/San-Francisco-isn-t-what-it-used-to-be-13901994.php">https://www.sfchronicle.com/oursf/article/San-Francisco-isn-t-what-it-used-to-be-13901994.php</a></li>
<li>The hallmark of sociological storytelling is if it can encourage us to put ourselves in the place of any character. GoT used to be like that, but then turned into a story about heroes. <a href="https://blogs.scientificamerican.com/observations/the-real-reason-fans-hate-the-last-season-of-game-of-thrones/">https://blogs.scientificamerican.com/observations/the-real-reason-fans-hate-the-last-season-of-game-of-thrones/</a></li>
<li>An attempt to integrate cybernetics, counterculture, computing, and design. <a href="http://www.dubberly.com/articles/cybernetics-and-counterculture.html">http://www.dubberly.com/articles/cybernetics-and-counterculture.html</a></li>
<li>If AI were a great storyteller, it would be an alien bard who has studied our planet from orbit and still doesn’t get it; but the tales it tells embarrass us with their insights all the same. <a href="https://emshort.blog/2019/04/04/can-ai-tell-a-good-story/">https://emshort.blog/2019/04/04/can-ai-tell-a-good-story/</a></li>
<li>Quadratic Voting is too complicated for the average person, but the idea of having a finite number of tokens to distribute amongst a set of important issues is a good one. <a href="https://lawreview.uchicago.edu/publication/qv-or-not-qv-question-some-skepticism-about-radical-egalitarian-voting-markets">https://lawreview.uchicago.edu/publication/qv-or-not-qv-question-some-skepticism-about-radical-egalitarian-voting-markets</a></li>
<li>A whole, unmilled tree can support 50 percent more weight than the largest piece of lumber milled from the same tree. <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2009/11/05/garden/05tree.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2009/11/05/garden/05tree.html</a></li>
<li>Where do ideas come from? <a href="https://nadiaeghbal.com/ideas">https://nadiaeghbal.com/ideas</a></li>
<li>Cliff Mass correctly predicted that we’d have fewer wildfires in the PNW, great example of regression towards the mean. <a href="https://cliffmass.blogspot.com/2019/05/will-puget-sound-experience-another.html">https://cliffmass.blogspot.com/2019/05/will-puget-sound-experience-another.html</a></li>
<li>Bungalows in places like Wallingford and Ballard that many now find charming were widely criticized as cheap when they began popping up in the early part of the 20th century. Who knows how Seattle’s modern builds will age? <a href="https://www.seattletimes.com/business/real-estate/a-teardown-a-day-bulldozing-the-way-for-bigger-homes-in-seattle-suburbs/">https://www.seattletimes.com/business/real-estate/a-teardown-a-day-bulldozing-the-way-for-bigger-homes-in-seattle-suburbs/</a></li>
<li>That skyscraper in Vancouver prominently seen from Granville bridge (northbound) is also designed by big.dk. <a href="https://www.dezeen.com/2018/11/30/movie-big-heatherwick-google-hq-progress/">https://www.dezeen.com/2018/11/30/movie-big-heatherwick-google-hq-progress/</a></li>
<li>Half of parents are fathers, yet 99% of the research on parenting focuses on mothers. <a href="https://www.bbc.com/future/article/20190606-how-to-be-a-good-father-to-a-newborn-son-or-daughter">https://www.bbc.com/future/article/20190606-how-to-be-a-good-father-to-a-newborn-son-or-daughter</a></li>
<li>Massive migration of G+ accounts from Google accounts gave people the impression G+ was a “ghost town.” <a href="https://onezero.medium.com/why-google-failed-4b9db05b973b">https://onezero.medium.com/why-google-failed-4b9db05b973b</a></li>
<li>Identify and avoid cargo cults in design thinking. <a href="https://medium.com/designing-atlassian/when-design-becomes-a-cargo-cult-2bb9a50aad53">https://medium.com/designing-atlassian/when-design-becomes-a-cargo-cult-2bb9a50aad53</a></li>
<li>80% of the aviation industry's emissions come from passenger flights longer than 1,500km - a distance no electric airliner could yet fly. <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/business-48630656">https://www.bbc.com/news/business-48630656</a></li>
<li>‘Sleeping beauties’ are papers which didn’t have much influence early but come to be appreciated and important later. <a href="https://news.uchicago.edu/story/new-model-reveals-forgotten-influencers-and-sleeping-beauties-science">https://news.uchicago.edu/story/new-model-reveals-forgotten-influencers-and-sleeping-beauties-science</a></li>
<li>Our superpower is not raw intelligence but our ability to learn through imitation. Aggregated over generations, this becomes culture.<a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2019/06/04/book-review-the-secret-of-our-success/">https://slatestarcodex.com/2019/06/04/book-review-the-secret-of-our-success/</a></li>
<li>Banned about 70 years ago in Seattle, parent-in-law apartments were again allowed across the city starting in 1994 and backyard cottages since 2010. <a href="https://www.seattletimes.com/seattle-news/politics/seattle-city-council-oks-more-and-larger-backyard-cottages-restricts-mcmansions/">https://www.seattletimes.com/seattle-news/politics/seattle-city-council-oks-more-and-larger-backyard-cottages-restricts-mcmansions/</a></li>
<li>The Baumol effect: “A violinist can always choose to stop playing violin, retrain for a while, and work in a factory instead. Maybe in 1826, when factory owners were earning $1.14/hour and violinists were earning $5/hour, so no violinists would quit and retrain. But by 2010, factory workers were earning $26.44/hour, so if violinists were still only earning $5 they might all quit and retrain.” <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2019/06/10/book-review-the-prices-are-too-dmn-high/">https://slatestarcodex.com/2019/06/10/book-review-the-prices-are-too-dmn-high/</a></li>
<li>Mistake theorists treat politics as science, engineering, or medicine. The State is diseased. Conflict theorists treat politics as war. Different blocs with different interests. <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2018/01/24/conflict-vs-mistake/">https://slatestarcodex.com/2018/01/24/conflict-vs-mistake/</a></li>
<li>It’s hard to separate the threat that technology poses from the threat that capitalism poses. <a href="https://www.gq.com/story/ted-chiang-exhalation-interview">https://www.gq.com/story/ted-chiang-exhalation-interview</a></li>
<li>Convenience is a value, and one we hold personally. Maybe it’s worth reconsidering this. <a href="https://onezero.medium.com/the-tyranny-of-convenience-2e7fa145ab4">https://onezero.medium.com/the-tyranny-of-convenience-2e7fa145ab4</a></li>
<li>We don’t want hectoring morality tales, as evidenced by The Odyssey’s exceeding popularity compared to Plato’s Republic. We want stories that let us be other characters: strong and cunning, defiant or afraid, good or bad or somewhere in between. <a href="https://putanumonit.com/2019/06/25/playstation-odysseys/">https://putanumonit.com/2019/06/25/playstation-odysseys/</a></li>
<li>A scene with active technological evolution has what musician Brian Eno called scenius. <a href="https://breakingsmart.substack.com/p/following-the-scenius">https://breakingsmart.substack.com/p/following-the-scenius</a></li>
<li>The Antidisciplinarathon is a compelling format to quickly broaden one’s purview, ramp up on new fields, and meet new interesting people. <a href="http://hypotext.co/antidisciplinarathon">http://hypotext.co/antidisciplinarathon</a></li>
<li>The vast resources of Silicon Valley have too often been applied to the problem of “what is my mother no longer doing for me?” <a href="https://slate.com/culture/2019/06/life-hacking-productivity-tech-silicon-valley-hacking-life-book-review.html">https://slate.com/culture/2019/06/life-hacking-productivity-tech-silicon-valley-hacking-life-book-review.html</a></li>
<li>AFAICT, Deinstitutionalisation =&gt; Homelessness. <a href="https://www.npr.org/2019/07/12/736612514/seattle-faces-backlash-after-easing-up-on-punishing-crimes-involving-mental-illn">https://www.npr.org/2019/07/12/736612514/seattle-faces-backlash-after-easing-up-on-punishing-crimes-involving-mental-illn</a></li>
<li>We would like to think there is some quick hack, or that we can learn something with it feeling like a simple game, but the true is that real learning is hard work and frustrating. <a href="https://medium.com/@gjdickens/distraction-disguised-as-learning-duolingo-codeacademy-and-why-you-should-get-back-to-basics-99a22a9e2c33">https://medium.com/@gjdickens/distraction-disguised-as-learning-duolingo-codeacademy-and-why-you-should-get-back-to-basics-99a22a9e2c33</a></li>
<li>China seems unlikely to do personalized learning well, but appear to be far ahead in many aspects of optimizing education. <a href="https://www.technologyreview.com/s/614057/china-squirrel-has-started-a-grand-experiment-in-ai-education-it-could-reshape-how-the/">https://www.technologyreview.com/s/614057/china-squirrel-has-started-a-grand-experiment-in-ai-education-it-could-reshape-how-the/</a></li>
<li>Some studies seem to indicate that not only do students retain less when reading digitally, they’re more likely to overestimate how well they comprehended the material. <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/digital-textbooks-radical-transformation/">https://www.wired.com/story/digital-textbooks-radical-transformation/</a></li>
<li>Because the 737 has kept the same name for 50 years, the FAA certification of the fourth-generation 737 in 2017 involved only light-touch approval. The only really rigorous test-result underpinnings were those of the 1967 machine. <a href="https://www.edge.org/conversation/timothy_taylor-polythetics-and-the-boeing-737-max">https://www.edge.org/conversation/timothy_taylor-polythetics-and-the-boeing-737-max</a></li>
<li>Criticize the existence of billionaires in general, their spending on yachts or mansions. But if you only criticize billionaires when they’re trying to save lives, you risk collateral damage to everything we care about. <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2019/07/29/against-against-billionaire-philanthropy/">https://slatestarcodex.com/2019/07/29/against-against-billionaire-philanthropy/</a></li>
<li>A resurrected Franklin wouldn’t have a news job inside The Washington Post; he’d have an anonymous Twitter account with a huge following that he’d use to routinely troll political opponents. <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/journalism-isnt-dying-its-returning-its-roots/">https://www.wired.com/story/journalism-isnt-dying-its-returning-its-roots/</a></li>
<li>Tech workers might not realize that their opposition to the work their companies do on military technology does not change the decision-making of the American leaders who choose to go to war. <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/08/28/opinion/military-war-tech-us.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2019/08/28/opinion/military-war-tech-us.html</a></li>
<li>AI-writer centaurs are super interesting. <a href="https://www.vox.com/future-perfect/2019/8/30/20840194/ai-art-fiction-writing-language-gpt-2">https://www.vox.com/future-perfect/2019/8/30/20840194/ai-art-fiction-writing-language-gpt-2</a></li>
<li>“Isn’t school for learning math and science and reading,” he asked us one day, “not for teachers to tell us what to think about society?” <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2019/10/when-the-culture-war-comes-for-the-kids/596668/">https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2019/10/when-the-culture-war-comes-for-the-kids/596668/</a></li>
<li>Study after study has shown open offices to foster seclusion more than innovation. People in an open office put on headphones, talk less, and feel terrible. <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/09/25/opinion/wework-adam-neumann.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2019/09/25/opinion/wework-adam-neumann.html</a></li>
<li>Great summary of arguments in favor of and also against Sortition - the system whereby members of representative bodies are picked at random, like jurors.<a href="http://edmundgriffiths.com/sortition.html">http://edmundgriffiths.com/sortition.html</a></li>
<li>Rather than maintaining my own lawn, much better to have a smaller garden and live right beside a great park? <a href="https://earther.gizmodo.com/lawns-are-an-ecological-disaster-1826070720">https://earther.gizmodo.com/lawns-are-an-ecological-disaster-1826070720</a></li>
<li>We’re not merely lighting a match to the Amazon and imperiling everything that lives in it with extinction, but also summoning creatures long dead to return to Earth’s surface and give up the ancient energy they took to the grave. <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/science/archive/2019/08/amazon-fire-earth-has-plenty-oxygen/596923/">https://www.theatlantic.com/science/archive/2019/08/amazon-fire-earth-has-plenty-oxygen/596923/</a></li>
<li>In the last 20 years, some Inuit communities who had never seen robins before have had to invent a name for them: “Koyapigaktoruk.” <a href="https://earthsky.org/earth/decoding-climate-change-signals-arctic-treeline-tundra-alaska">https://earthsky.org/earth/decoding-climate-change-signals-arctic-treeline-tundra-alaska</a></li>
<li>Yedoma consists of thick layers of soil packed around gigantic lodes of embedded ice. Because Yedoma contains so much ice, it can melt quickly — reshaping the landscape as sudden lakes form and hillsides collapse. <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/graphics/2019/national/climate-environment/climate-change-siberia/">https://www.washingtonpost.com/graphics/2019/national/climate-environment/climate-change-siberia/</a></li>
<li>Wikis are just editable web pages; Twitter is just a way of sharing very short form writing; and Facebook is just a way of sharing writing and pictures with friends. Indeed, writing itself is just a clever way of ordering a small number of symbols on a page. While a medium may be simple, that doesn’t mean it’s not profound. <a href="https://numinous.productions/ttft/">https://numinous.productions/ttft/</a></li>
<li>For middle-class and poor families, the picture is different. Federal income taxes have also declined modestly for these families, but they haven’t benefited much if at all from the decline in the corporate tax or estate tax. <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2019/10/06/opinion/income-tax-rate-wealthy.html">https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2019/10/06/opinion/income-tax-rate-wealthy.html</a></li>
<li>The idea of the Anthropocene inflates our own importance by promising eternal geological life to our creations. It is of a thread with our species’ peculiar, self-styled exceptionalism. <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/science/archive/2019/08/arrogance-anthropocene/595795/">https://www.theatlantic.com/science/archive/2019/08/arrogance-anthropocene/595795/</a></li>
<li>To Western ears, the combination of C and F# is grating, but Tsimane listeners rated this chord just as likeable as other chords that Westerners would interpret as more pleasant, such as C and G. <a href="https://cosmosmagazine.com/biology/perception-of-musical-pitch-varies-across-cultures">https://cosmosmagazine.com/biology/perception-of-musical-pitch-varies-across-cultures</a></li>
<li>It doesn’t seem too soon to ask: Is the vision of the VR or AR headset as a widespread consumer device just a dead branch hanging off technology’s evolutionary tree? <a href="https://www.fastcompany.com/90418190/the-one-thing-google-didnt-talk-about-at-its-keynote">https://www.fastcompany.com/90418190/the-one-thing-google-didnt-talk-about-at-its-keynote</a></li>
<li>Some examples of people quickly accomplishing ambitious things together. <a href="https://patrickcollison.com/fast">https://patrickcollison.com/fast</a></li>
<li>On-device AI could be clutch for detecting illegal logging. <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/10/15/climate/indonesia-logging-deforestation.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2019/10/15/climate/indonesia-logging-deforestation.html</a></li>
<li>Technology that’s Actually Yours could be the next great counter-trend. <a href="https://alexdanco.com/2019/10/26/everything-is-amazing-but-nothing-is-ours/">https://alexdanco.com/2019/10/26/everything-is-amazing-but-nothing-is-ours/</a></li>
<li>Utrecht has a bike garage with sensors on the racks, making finding a free spot during rush hour much easier. <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2017/09/06/world/europe/bicycling-utrecht-dutch-love-bikes-worlds-largest-bike-parking-garages.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2017/09/06/world/europe/bicycling-utrecht-dutch-love-bikes-worlds-largest-bike-parking-garages.html</a></li>
<li>By pushing a highly political agenda the Anxious, Social-Justice, Partisan (ASP) movement is undermining bipartisan efforts--and nothing important will be done unless both sides of the aisle are involved. <a href="https://cliffmass.blogspot.com/2019/10/the-real-climate-debate.html">https://cliffmass.blogspot.com/2019/10/the-real-climate-debate.html</a></li>
<li>The party launched the app, called Study the Great Nation, containing articles and videos about Xi’s activities or his ideology, “Xi Jinping Thought.” There is even a sense of competition, with users earning points for reading articles and commenting on them, and a leader board showing how users are faring in quizzes. <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/world/asia_pacific/chinese-app-on-xis-ideology-allows-data-access-to-100-million-users-phones-report-says/2019/10/11/2d53bbae-eb4d-11e9-bafb-da248f8d5734_story.html">https://www.washingtonpost.com/world/asia_pacific/chinese-app-on-xis-ideology-allows-data-access-to-100-million-users-phones-report-says/2019/10/11/2d53bbae-eb4d-11e9-bafb-da248f8d5734_story.html</a></li>
<li>Younger Palestinians were interested (in improving relations with Israel), but that there were none well-established enough in their careers yet to withstand the blowback. <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/11/20/us/israel-arab-dialog.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2019/11/20/us/israel-arab-dialog.html</a></li>
<li>Clustering meetings and scheduling them near breaks is ideal. One of the best times is near the end of the day, or right before lunch. <a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/makersschedule.html">http://www.paulgraham.com/makersschedule.html</a></li>
<li>Terrifying: ISPs would recognize the obsolescence of the internet and support the Trinet only, driven by market demand for optimal user experience from GOOG-FB-AMZN. <a href="https://staltz.com/the-web-began-dying-in-2014-heres-how.html">https://staltz.com/the-web-began-dying-in-2014-heres-how.html</a></li>
<li>Saildrones are autonomous sailboats that act as mobile weather stations. Could we take advantage of this capability to improve observations of important storms? <a href="https://cliffmass.blogspot.com/2019/11/can-autonomous-weather-observation.html">https://cliffmass.blogspot.com/2019/11/can-autonomous-weather-observation.html</a></li>
<li>Prediction is overrated. What we really should be striving for, with our social science, is ability to bring about desirable outcomes and to avoid unwanted outcomes. <a href="http://peterturchin.com/cliodynamica/psychohistory-and-cliodynamics/">http://peterturchin.com/cliodynamica/psychohistory-and-cliodynamics/</a></li>
<li>If until now you were used to moving along roads and sidewalks, forget it! From now on we all walk through walls! <a href="http://www.bldgblog.com/2010/01/nakatomi-space/">http://www.bldgblog.com/2010/01/nakatomi-space/</a></li>
<li>What would it take to create an effective developmental learning environment for humanity? <a href="https://glazkov.com/2019/08/11/a-classroom-for-humanity/">https://glazkov.com/2019/08/11/a-classroom-for-humanity/</a></li>
<li>Great mathematicians each had their own strategies for generating ideas. Erdős sought hyper-focussed vigilance, Poincaré described lying in bed in a half-dream state as the ideal condition, Descartes famously loved to lounge in bed in the morning and think. <a href="https://www.newyorker.com/culture/annals-of-inquiry/the-myth-and-magic-of-generating-new-ideas?verso=true">https://www.newyorker.com/culture/annals-of-inquiry/the-myth-and-magic-of-generating-new-ideas?verso=true</a></li>
<li>On the Estonian border, another anekdot goes, a border guard is filling out Putin’s entry form. “Occupation?” the officer asks. “Not today,” Putin replies. “Just tourism.” <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/ideas/archive/2019/11/russian-jokes-tell-deeper-truths-about-putin-and-trump/602713/">https://www.theatlantic.com/ideas/archive/2019/11/russian-jokes-tell-deeper-truths-about-putin-and-trump/602713/</a></li>
<li>The Reigns mechanic requires making pragmatic choices to stay alive, not always being ideologically consistent, and working to find a way out over course of generations, slowly discovering one’s true nature and power. <a href="https://emshort.blog/2018/01/24/reigns-her-majesty/">https://emshort.blog/2018/01/24/reigns-her-majesty/</a></li>
<li><a href="http://mkremins.github.io/blog/gardening-games/">In exploration games, to spend time in a place is to deplete it, to make it less and less interesting until there’s no longer any reason to stay. In gardening games, to spend time in a place is to enrich it.</a></li>
<li>The intersection of Science Fiction and Religion often yields greatness. <a href="https://urbigenous.net/library/nine_billion_names_of_god.html">https://urbigenous.net/library/nine_billion_names_of_god.html</a></li>
</ul>

        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Avoiding local maximums</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2019/avoiding-local-maximums"/>
    
    <updated>2019-05-22T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2019/avoiding-local-maximums</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>Easier said than done.</p>
<p><img alt="Don't focus on local maxima: easier said than done." src="/assets/local-maxima.png" /></p>

        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Reading in 2018</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2019/reading-in-2018"/>
    
    <updated>2019-01-10T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2019/reading-in-2018</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>I read and listened to a few <a href="/books">books</a> in 2018. My highlights include
speculative fiction stories from Chinese authors: <a href="/books/the-truth-of-fact-the-truth-of-feeling-by-ted-chiang/">Ted
Chiang</a>, <a href="/books/three-body-problem-by-liu-cixin-audio/">Liu
Cixin</a>, <a href="/books/infinite-planets/">Ken Liu's translations
of</a>, Chen Qiufan, Xia Jia, Hao Jingfang. Also really
enjoyed <a href="/books/player-of-games-by-iain-m-banks/">Player of Games</a> and <a href="/books/darkness-at-noon-by-arthur-koestler-audio/">Darkness
at Noon</a>. On the non-fiction
front, I listened to two excellent history lectures: one on <a href="/books/the-fall-and-rise-of-china-audio/">modern
China</a>, another on the <a href="/books/living-the-french-revolution-audio/">French
Revolution</a>. I also read a pair of
books describing cyclical views of history: <a href="/books/the-fourth-turning-by-howe-and-strauss/">The Fourth
Turning</a> and a more scientific
take, <a href="/books/war-and-peace-and-war-by-peter-turchin/">War and Peace and War</a>.
A standout non-fiction favorite was <a href="/books/impro-by-keith-johnstone/">Impro</a>,
which I will definitely be returning to.</p>
<p>Most of my internet reading happens through Instapaper, which affords me a 
handy chronicle of articles that I enjoyed. Here are a few of them (excerpts are
not endorsements):</p>
<!--more-->

<ul>
<li>Between 1900 and 1910, Seattle’s population tripled, from just over 80,000 to
  more than 230,000 people. <a href="http://archive.kuow.org/post/story-behind-seattles-obsession-craftsman-homes">The Story Behind Seattle's Obsession With Craftsman
  Homes</a></li>
<li>The demo drew rave reviews from the technology press. <a href="https://www.1843magazine.com/technology/the-daily/no-googles-pixel-buds-wont-change-the-world">No, Google’s Pixel Buds
  won’t change the
  world</a></li>
<li>That’s home. That’s us. On it everyone you love, everyone you know, everyone
  you ever heard of, every human being who ever was, lived out their lives.
  <a href="https://www.brainpickings.org/2012/12/10/pale-blue-dot-motion-graphics/">Carl Sagan’s Pale Blue Dot, Animated in Motion
  Graphics</a></li>
<li>Our choice is not between "regulation" and "no regulation." The code
  regulates. It implements values, or not. It enables freedoms, or disables
  them. It protects privacy, or promotes monitoring. <a href="https://harvardmagazine.com/2000/01/code-is-law-html">Code Is
  Law</a></li>
<li>In other words: AIs are best at choosing answers. Humans are best at choosing
  questions. <a href="https://jods.mitpress.mit.edu/pub/issue3-case">How To Become A
  Centaur</a></li>
<li>Today’s belief in ineluctable certainty is the true innovation-killer of our
  age. In this environment, the best an audacious manager can do is to develop
  small improvements to existing systems — climbing the hill, as it were, toward
  a local maximum, trimming fat, eking out the occasional tiny innovation — like
  city planners painting bicycle lanes on the streets as a gesture toward
  solving our energy problems. <a href="https://www.wired.com/2011/10/stephenson-innovation-starvation/">Innovation
  Starvation</a></li>
<li>There is no reason to let a company make so much money while potentially
  helping to radicalize billions of people <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2018/03/10/opinion/sunday/youtube-politics-radical.html">YouTube, the Great
  Radicalizer</a></li>
<li>Favoring the “soft” aspects of a college application is straightforwardly
  beneficial to the more privileged at the expense of the less. <a href="https://jacobinmag.com/2018/03/sat-class-race-inequality-college-admission">The Progressive
  Case for the
  SAT</a></li>
<li>Science fiction allows us the distance to circumvent issue fatigue in our very
  troubled times. <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-017-08674-8">Science fiction when the future is
  now</a></li>
<li>Isaiah Berlin, sobered by the 20th century’s failed utopias, has argued for a
  more modest liberal pluralism that makes room for multiple, genuinely
  conflicting goods. Family and work, solidarity and autonomy, tradition and
  innovation are really valuable, and really in tension <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2018/04/steven-pinker-enlightenment-now/554054/">When Truth and Reason
  Are No Longer
  Enough</a></li>
<li>I am not a relativist; I do not say "I like my coffee with milk and you like
  it without; I am in favor of kindness and you prefer concentration camps"
  <a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/users/vl/notes/berlin.html">Isaiah Berlin on
  Pluralism</a></li>
<li>Unstructured, unsupervised time for play is one of the most important things
  we have to give back to kids if we want them to be strong and happy and
  resilient. <a href="https://reason.com/archives/2017/10/26/the-fragile-generation">The Fragile
  Generation</a></li>
<li>The average net worth among adults in the 95th to 99th percentile is about
  $1.7 million. Among the 0.1 percent, it’s about $60 million. Who, exactly, are
  the aristocrats again? <a href="https://slate.com/business/2018/05/forget-the-atlantics-9-9-percent-the-1-percent-are-still-the-problem.html">Forget What the Atlantic Is Telling You. The 1 Percent
  Are Still the
  Problem</a></li>
<li>We are a species that strives not just for survival, but also for
  significance. We want lives that matter. <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2018/06/23/opinion/sunday/suicide-rate-existential-crisis.html">Is This an Existential
  Crisis?</a></li>
<li>To support triangulation, we recommend a shift to a contributorship model,
  similar to the credits that roll at the end of a film — a long list of
  individuals with their contributions described fully and specifically <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-018-01023-3">Robust
  research needs many lines of
  evidence</a></li>
<li>Do whatever you can’t stop thinking about. Documenting your findings in public
  (regardless of outcomes!) is a worthy contribution to society, full stop. <a href="https://nadiaeghbal.com/independent-research">The
  independent researcher</a></li>
<li>Various studies have identified cooperation as a core theme in popular
  narratives across the world. ... nearly 80% of their tales concerned moral
  decision making and social dilemmas <a href="http://www.bbc.com/culture/story/20180503-our-fiction-addiction-why-humans-need-stories">Our fiction addiction: Why humans need
  stories</a></li>
<li>The transhumanist vision too easily reduces all of reality to data,
  concluding that “humans are nothing but information-processing objects.”
  <a href="https://medium.com/s/futurehuman/survival-of-the-richest-9ef6cddd0cc1">Survival of the
  Richest</a></li>
<li>This means that the mistake must be at the root, at the very basis of human
  thinking in the past centuries. ... It could also be called
  anthropocentricity, with man seen as the center of everything that exists. <a href="https://www.americanrhetoric.com/speeches/alexandersolzhenitsynharvard.htm">A
  World Split
  Apart</a></li>
<li>Concoct one story where things get better, one where they get worse, and one
  where they get weird. <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2018/09/01/opinion/sunday/how-make-big-decision.html">How to Make a Big
  Decision</a></li>
<li>Particularly sad is the belief that the majority of the homeless were drunks,
  drug addicts, criminals or thieves. It is true that the category “homeless”
  has come to include all of those people, but there are so many, many more who
  are none of those things. <a href="https://crosscut.com/2018/09/why-i-started-giving-homeless">Why I started giving to the homeless</a></li>
<li>Perhaps unsurprisingly, Magic Leap is almost entirely built on the visions of
  grown men wanting to immerse themselves in fantasy worlds. <a href="https://gizmodo.com/the-magic-leap-con-1829716266">The Magic Leap
  Con</a></li>
<li>The really important kind of freedom involves attention, and awareness, and
  discipline, and effort, and being able truly to care about other people and to
  sacrifice for them, over and over, in myriad petty little unsexy ways, every
  day. That is real freedom. The alternative is unconsciousness, the
  default-setting, the "rat race"-the constant gnawing sense of having had and
  lost some infinite thing. <a href="https://fs.blog/2012/04/david-foster-wallace-this-is-water/">This is Water</a></li>
<li>The big mistake in this pattern of failure is projecting your subjective lack
  of comprehension onto the object you are looking at, as “irrationality.” We
  make this mistake because we are tempted by a desire for legibility. <a href="https://www.ribbonfarm.com/2010/07/26/a-big-little-idea-called-legibility/">A Big Little Idea Called Legibility</a></li>
<li>There is something sinister and corrupt—Maoist—in the habit of assigning
  people to categories. <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/america-is-addicted-to-outrage-is-there-a-cure-1543620811">America Is Addicted to Outrage. Is There a
  Cure?</a></li>
<li>Like the open office, the loud restaurant seems to have overstayed its
  welcome. That’s because loud restaurants are more profitable. <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2018/11/how-restaurants-got-so-loud/576715/">How Restaurants
  Got So
  Loud</a></li>
</ul>

        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Against retweets</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2018/against-retweets"/>
    
    <updated>2018-09-09T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2018/against-retweets</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p><img alt="Create and consume time for content of various lengths." src="/assets/against-retweets.png" /></p>
<p>One of these data points is not like the other. Also, isn't it neat that common
units of time duration fall nicely onto a logarithmic scale?</p>

        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Make twitter great again?</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2018/make-twitter-great-again"/>
    
    <updated>2018-09-06T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2018/make-twitter-great-again</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>I used twitter the most while working in developer relations, mainly sharing
articles about web development that I thought deserved more attention. My feed
consisted of engineers, developer advocates, and web standards folks I
respected, all of whom had something interesting to say. Twitter was my interest
graph, in contrast with Facebook, which was just a poor facsimile of real life
relationships.</p>
<p>As my career and interests shifted, so did the people I followed on twitter.
I started following VR engineers, machine learning researchers, philosophers
and psychologists. But more tweeps meant more tweets. Soon I had a <a href="https://twitter.com/borismus/lists/smartpeople">twitter
list</a> for people that I had reluctantly unfollowed. They had
interesting things to say, but said them too often.</p>
<p>Following someone on twitter is like having a direct line into their brain. If
they write about a subject you are passionate about, fantastic. If they have
broadly aligning interests, chances are they will turn you on to something neat,
or if you're lucky, life changing. Unfortunately, most of the time, twitter
brains are distracted, anxious, angry, or unhappy. Spastic tweet storms and
political ramblings deserve only one thing, a hearty unfollow.</p>
<p>Twitter's bad design decisions only compound the problem. In "Retweets Are
Trash", Alexis Madrigal <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2018/04/the-case-against-retweets/554078/">writes</a>, "When Twitter introduced a retweet
button, in 2009, suddenly one click could send a post careening through the
network. The automatic retweet took Twitter’s natural tendency for amplification
and cranked it up." Apparently it's not hard to globally disable retweets using
a <a href="https://medium.com/@Luca/how-to-turn-off-retweets-for-everyone-99dd835c10f8">crude hack</a>. Anecdotally, it seems to have made my feed a bit calmer.</p>
<p>A quick update on my <a href="http://smus.com/notes/2018/lynched-on-twitter/">white supremacist spam problem</a>. Time seems to
have sorted it out, and the remaining squawks have been muffled by twitter's
<a href="https://support.twitter.com/articles/20169398">quality filter</a>. I also tried using Mastodon. It was a calming
experience at first, but when I followed a few people and dug around a little
bit, I was dismayed to see most design choices mirroring twitter's. I caught up
on RSS feeds, which I really like. But the RSS ecosystem continues to die. Of
nearly five hundred RSS feeds in my OPML file, more than half are broken links.
Occasionally the links are fixed, causing my reader to choke on a year's worth
of articles from a blog whose existence I've long forgotten about.</p>
<p>I can't quite decide whether or not to use twitter again. I keep thinking that I
once got a lot out of my original use of the platform. If I do return, I'll be
making use of the @reply quality filter, fully disable retweets, and unfollow
more aggressively. Whether this makes twitter great again remains to be seen.</p>

        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Lynched on Twitter</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2018/lynched-on-twitter"/>
    
    <updated>2018-08-26T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2018/lynched-on-twitter</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>Last week, a <a href="https://twitter.com/borismus/status/798350680951910400">sarcastic twitter
reply</a> I posted two
years ago was picked up by an account called Blue Check Watch, looking for
verified twitter accounts disparaging white people. As a result, my account has
become inundated by a hybrid human-bot army of white supremacist trolls. Most
responses accused me of anti-white racism, completely missing what I thought was
obviously a sarcastic tone. Sadly, many of the attacks are really nasty and
ad-hominem. One user
<a href="https://twitter.com/CascadianDennis/status/1033190496456269824">posted</a> "Why do
people who say this always look like this?", alongside my twitter profile photo.
Others are
<a href="https://twitter.com/1CE1CEB4BY/status/1033197950703464448">explicitly</a>
<a href="https://twitter.com/NationDixie/status/1033395244014944256">anti-semitic</a>
messages that do not bear repeating here. Ominously, I received an email from
Twitter informing me that they have investigated <strong>my tweet</strong>, flagged for violating
their TOS and "have not taken any action at this time."</p>
<p>Writing my snarky tweet two years ago, I was a bit uncertain whether it was
within the bounds of social acceptability. A white guy telling another
white guy that white guys are "the worst", was intended to poke a bit of fun at
the self-flaggelation associated with progressive politics. There is only so
much self-censorship one can do while still remaining authentic. In a surprising
twist, my tweet was offensive to a group I hadn't even thought about in a way I
could not have predicted, two years after the fact.</p>
<p>Twitter lynchings are not new, but it's different when it happens to you. It has
not had any serious consequences (yet?), and until it does, I will continue to
view this as a funny story, and not something truly traumatic, as it is often
framed in the press. Still, this experience serves as a good reminder of a few
points:</p>
<ol>
<li>Twitter's UI for threaded conversations is terrible, and hardly anyone of my
   virtual lynch mob even bothered to look to the tweet I was responding to.</li>
<li>My tweet was five words, twenty four characters. It was meant to be pithy,
   because that is how twitter works. But brief posts beget brief responses,
   which is fine between friends, but not fine when the whole world is watching.</li>
<li>Relatedly, sarcasm is hard to convey in this situation. Only two responses
   suggested that maybe I was being sarcastic, imploring my attackers, "Don't be
   lazy."</li>
<li>The fact that tweets have no expiry date means anything you have ever posted
   can be used against you in surprising ways. It took two years for my tweet to
   be picked up. James Gunn's incriminating posts were ten years old. Social
   norms change quickly, and this is one argument in favor of ephemerality.</li>
<li>On that same note, it seems that the white supremacy movement has really
   embraced the internet over the last couple of years in some sick symbiosis
   with the POTUS. At the same time, it's striking that the result of someone's
   pathetic search for anti-white sentiment yielded such a lackluster example.</li>
<li>Despite a general willingness for my views to be challenged, I don't have
   energy or desire to engage with this mob. I made no attempts to respond to
   any of my attackers. They appear to be victims of confirmation bias, stupid
   and/or malicious, and I have little faith that they will listen.</li>
<li>There are some really nasty people on the internet. If triggered, they will
   sherlock your religion, your employer, your family, and try to hit you where
   it hurts the most.</li>
</ol>
<p>Lynchings aside, I've been trying to use twitter less in favor of consuming and
producing longer form content, like books, blogs, and conversations. Given that
my account is currently being inundated with anti-semitic spam, I have very
little incentive to continue using the service. One thing that has been keeping
me on the platform is the potential reach I can get through 6K followers. I
should remember that in the grand scheme of things, this is a small number, 5
orders of magnitude less than the lovely POTUS. I shouldn't grow attached.</p>
<p>And so, just in time for my tenth twitter anniversary, it's time for me to make
some changes. At the very least, I'll be taking a long break.</p>

        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The difficult middle</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2018/the-difficult-middle"/>
    
    <updated>2018-07-21T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2018/the-difficult-middle</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>Monism gives life meaning through a single all-encompassing doctrine. Examples
include some political ideologies, religions, and <a href="https://meaningness.com/non-theistic-eternalism">variants of
rationality</a>. History has not been kind to those that have
fervently followed such doctrines. But once you see flaws in Monism, it can be
tempting to decide that life has <a href="https://meaningness.com/extreme-examples-eternalism-and-nihilism">no meaning at all</a>, falling
into the trap of Nihilism.</p>
<p><img alt="Stuck" src="https://i.imgur.com/WXdU3ef.gif" /></p>
<p>The choice between these two extremes is a false one. <a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/erGipespbbzdG5zYb/the-third-alternative">Rationalists know
this</a>. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Middle_Way">Buddhists know this</a>. Philosophers know
this too. David Chapman writes a <a href="https://meaningness.com/">whole blog</a> devoted to exploring
the space in between. But I have found <a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/users/vl/notes/berlin.html">Isaiah Berlin</a>'s synthesis to
be the most compelling:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Sobered by the 20th century’s failed utopias, <a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/users/vl/notes/berlin.html">Berlin</a>
argued for a more modest liberal pluralism that makes room for multiple,
genuinely conflicting goods. Family and work, solidarity and autonomy, tradition
and innovation are really valuable, and really in tension.  – <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2018/04/steven-pinker-enlightenment-now/554054/">Alison
Gopnik</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>In this view, we are condemned to an eternal balancing act, sometimes peering
too far into the meaningless abyss, and other times relaxing too deeply into
meaningful certainty. On balance, I hope to end up in this difficult middle.</p>

        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Required reading for VR enthusiasts</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2018/required-reading-for-vr-enthusiasts"/>
    
    <updated>2018-06-03T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2018/required-reading-for-vr-enthusiasts</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>Several books, movies, and articles have helped to shape my opinions on Virtual
Reality. I've was initially surprised by some former colleagues that it is
possible to view these works as aspirational rather than cautionary. I generally
prefer the dystopian interpretation. </p>
<ul>
<li>📚 Ray Bradbury - <a href="http://www.veddma.com/veddma/Veldt.htm">The Veldt</a></li>
<li>📚 Neil Stephenson - Snow Crash</li>
<li>📚 Stanislav Lem - The Futurological Congress</li>
<li>📚 Vernor Vinge - Rainbow's End</li>
<li>📚 Ernst Kline - Ready Player One</li>
<li>🎥 Black Mirror S3 E2: <a href="http://www.theverge.com/2016/10/25/13401020/black-mirror-season-3-episode-2-playtest-recap">Playtest</a></li>
<li>🎥 The Matrix</li>
<li>🎵 Father John Misty - <a href="https://genius.com/Father-john-misty-total-entertainment-forever-lyrics">Total Entertainment Forever</a></li>
<li>📜 <a href="http://slatestarcodex.com/2014/06/03/asches-to-asches/">Asches to Asches</a></li>
<li>📜 Robert Nozick's <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Experience_machine">experience machine</a></li>
</ul>

        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Balancing technological pessimism</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2018/balancing-technological-pessimism"/>
    
    <updated>2018-05-16T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2018/balancing-technological-pessimism</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p><a href="https://pessimists.co/">Pessimists archive</a> is a podcast that chronicles
pessimistic reactions to emerging technology as it was becoming mainstream.
Technology here is defined broadly, covering a broad range of topics: bikes,
coffee, pinball machines, vaccines, recorded music. The podcast is very
accessible, focused more on social and psychological issues and less on the tech
itself. </p>
<!--more-->

<p>In response to unreasonable technological enthusiasm ever present in my
industry, I have myself tended towards pessimism. After we launched Cardboard,
my small HCI team in Google Research became the de facto home of VR at Google.
Once word got out, engineers and designers flocked to our ranks, self selecting
for interest in VR. Suddenly I was surrounded by hundreds of VR enthusiasts,
while I was skeptical about the vision of VR as <a href="https://youtu.be/dxbh-TM5yNc?t=3m">"the last
platform"</a> and concerned about the social
implications of broad VR adoption.</p>
<p>I began to see myself as <a href="https://www.quora.com/World-War-Z-2013-movie/World-War-Z-2013-movie-Do-the-Israelis-really-have-a-10th-man-doctrine">the tenth
man</a>,
posing the question: what if VR isn't really a thing? I ended up much more
excited about <a href="https://atap.google.com/spotlight-stories/">Spotlight Stories</a>
without a headset, thought a bunch about augmented reality through audio, and
became increasingly alienated from my colleagues gushing with optimism, rushing
home to play Vive games in their carefully instrumented basements. This podcast
would sure have helped me put my VR pessimism into perspective. </p>
<p>One critique I had of the podcast concept is hindsight bias. All of the
technologies covered by Pessimists Archive ended up being successful, and time
has proven the doubters wrong. But how many emerging technologies were
successfully booed out of existence, or simply rejected by the market? And how
many market successes come at a significant cost that prescient pessimists
warned us about?  TV and smartphones come to mind.</p>
<p>That said, I highly recommend the podcast series. The episodes are short,
entertaining, and informative. I feel better equipped to recognize and overcome
the traps that ensnared previous generations of techno pessimists.</p>

        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>How rationalists can win</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2018/how-rationalists-can-win"/>
    
    <updated>2018-04-12T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2018/how-rationalists-can-win</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>The belief that <a href="https://wiki.lesswrong.com/wiki/Rationality_is_systematized_winning">"rationalists should win"</a> is widely held in the
rationalist community. So: does being a good rationalist actually help you win?
Certainly in some domains, like engineering and science, which focus on
quantification, systematization, and prediction. There, having a hyper-rational
mindset is clearly an advantage. As for winning at life, which I will take that
to mean leading to greater success in survival, evolution, and human
flourishing, I don't think rationality helps very much.</p>
<!--more-->

<p>The rationalist doctrine always favors quantification and optimization over
intuition. From a rationalist perspective, humans are buggy <a href="https://www.wired.com/2016/01/marvin-minskys-marvelous-meat-machine/">computers made of meat</a>. We are full of cognitive biases that cloud our judgement, and
cause us to do reliably poorly on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Newcomb%27s_paradox">simple tasks</a> related to
probability. So even if you don't really know what probability to assign, it's
better to <a href="https://putanumonit.com/">"put a number on it"</a> and then <a href="https://wiki.lesswrong.com/wiki/Shut_up_and_multiply">”shut up and multiply”</a>.</p>
<p>The problem with the above approach lies with the words "systematic" and
"predictable". Herb Simon's idea of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bounded_rationality">Bounded Rationality</a>, suggests that
our human ability to be rational, to systematize and predict is inherently
limited. These limitations may come from our limited brains, but may also be
fundamental in nature. Chaos theory makes it really difficult for even the most
advanced computers to predict even simple systems, such as the position of the
<a href="http://awesci.com/double-pendulum-and-why-we-can-never-predict-weather/">double pendulum</a> after a small amount of time.</p>
<p>The world is far more complicated than one pendulum attached to another.
Insisting on making every decision in life based on a <a href="/making-better-decisions/">series of sound logical steps</a>, one quickly becomes paralyzed by the
complexity of myriad tiny choices. Gerd Gigerenzer's <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ecological_rationality">ecological rationality</a> suggests that many things that appear illogical are actually
done for good reasons, ultimately leading to good outcomes. This idea is
directly at odds with the rational propensity for first knowing what is true
(epistemic rationality), and then making decisions in a series of logical steps.</p>
<p>Instead of being dogmatic about rationality, we should be better
consequentialists. Consider outcomes. Are rationalists more satisfied with their
lives than non-rationalists? Are they more productive?  Do they have fewer
regrets later in life? Do they have better relationships? Make more money?  Have
happier children? Impact their domains of knowledge more effectively?</p>
<p>It <a href="http://slatestarcodex.com/2018/04/02/are-the-amish-unhappy-super-happy-just-meh/">is hard to answer</a> the above questions definitively, but suppose we
had solid data, and it was clear that, Buddhists were more relaxed, Protestants
more productive, Amish happier, and Singularitarians more innovative than other
groups. Imagine we had a sense of expected consequences of being an adherent to
each type of lifestyle. Imagine further that you could take a personality test
and see how likely you would be to benefit from each. Then the rational thing to
do would be to choose one of the irrational doctrines to follow based on
expected outcomes if you were an adherent.</p>
<p>Of course, you want to remain open to changing your mind, so allow yourself to
indulge fully your chosen beliefs for a while. At the top of every year, wake up
as late as your doctrine allows and nurse your hangover, unless your beliefs
prevented you from drinking the night before. If your beliefs favors ice baths,
partake in the polar bear plunge. Then take a moment to re-evaluate your
beliefs.</p>

        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>A respectful truce?</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2017/a-respectful-truce"/>
    
    <updated>2017-08-24T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2017/a-respectful-truce</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>It's a fact that men greatly outnumber women in software engineering. As for
why, there is a fundamental disagreement between social constructivists and
evolutionary psychologists. </p>
<!--more-->

<p>Constructivists say that it’s because of systematic oppression against women.
Boys in the 80s grew up with computers, learned programming and made life a
living hell for their female classmates in CS101. <a href="http://www.npr.org/sections/money/2014/10/21/357629765/when-women-stopped-coding">Planet Money</a> has the
scoop. Evolutionary psychologists say that it’s because men and women have
evolutionarily caused <a href="https://heterodoxacademy.org/2017/08/10/the-google-memo-what-does-the-research-say-about-gender-differences/">differences in interests</a> and point to studies
indicating that progressive countries have larger gender representation gaps
because women are free to choose <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2017/08/07/contra-grant-on-exaggerated-differences/">careers based on interest</a>. I find
it likely that both positions contribute in part to the gender representation
disparity. Compelling arguments can be made for and against both, and both are
rooted in academic disciplines <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Replication_crisis">that are dangerously squishy</a>. As a
result, I don’t think we currently have a good scientific way of determining
this.</p>
<p>So what; science, schmience! Followers of the evo psych and constructivism are
at war. One continuously pisses the other off with their inflamatory rhetoric.
It is true that white males are historically privileged, but hammering “white
male privelege” into their heads predictably puts white males into a defensive
stance. Similarly, discussing how evo psych means that women are less interested
and therefore less capable of software engineering will predictably annoy
females, especially those rightfully proud of their software engineering
prowess, and tired of dealing with similar allegations for their whole career.</p>
<p>I've spent way too much time reading and thinking about this lately, and it
saddens me to conclude that the wisest course of action is to avoid discussing
this topic entirely (oops, too late). Scott Aaronson, Sarah Constantin and
Stacey Jeffery propose a <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=3389">respectful truce</a> between the two camps.
Advocates of evolutionary psychology should:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>do everything they can to foster diversity, including by creating environments
that are welcoming for women, and by supporting affirmative action, women-only
scholarships and conferences, and other diversity policies and also agree
never to talk in public about possible cognitive-science explanations for
gender disparities in which careers people choose, or overlapping bell curves,
or anything else potentially inflammatory."</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Meanwhile, social constructivists should:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>avoid libelling [white men] as misogynist monsters, who must be scaring all
the women away with their inherently gross, icky, creepy, discriminatory
brogrammer maleness.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Truce?</p>

        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The end of endings</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2017/the-end-of-endings"/>
    
    <updated>2017-07-31T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2017/the-end-of-endings</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>Despite the obnoxious title, <a href="https://a16z.com/2017/07/15/popularity-addiction-thompson-alter/">this a16z podcast</a> was unusually insightful.</p>
<p>One big theme in the podcast can be summarized as an end of endings: a trend
away from one story with a coherent, finite arc, towards something neverending.
Amorphous TV shows like Lost, as well as Hollywood's discovery that a coherent
franchise like Star Wars can be milked for many more dollars are examples of
this. The stats backs it up: Hollywood moved from 10% of the hits of the 90s
being sequels to 50% today, as can be seen in the <a href="http://www.boxofficemojo.com/yearly/">box office data</a>.
Looking at TV shows through the same lens, each show is a one hour long movie,
followed by tens of sequels. And successful franchises aim to immerse their fans
(especially kids) into their universe with figurines, games, lunch boxes, bed
sheets.</p>
<p>The end of endings also shows up in user interfaces, and is epitomized by the
infinite scroller. Millions of souls fixate on the next pretty picture, the next
baby picture, the next outrage. Entertainment that never ends!</p>
<p>This is interesting in the context of attention. In the realm of meditation, the
challenge is to focus on something mundane, like your breath. In the realm of
entertainment, the challenge is to snap out of an immersive world carefully
constructed to consume your attention for as long as possible.</p>

        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Intelligence, aliens, and self-improvement</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2017/intelligence-aliens-and-self-improvement"/>
    
    <updated>2017-07-10T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2017/intelligence-aliens-and-self-improvement</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>I recently enjoyed a podcast about intelligence, aliens and learning where Kevin
Kelly was interviewed by Sam Harris. Here are some things I liked about it:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Kelly makes a great argument that with text we already have no way of knowing
  what is true. We have to rely on the source. My fears of audio and video fake
  news are reduced.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>It's obvious that the world is changing quickly, which means lifelong learning
  is necessary. One thing I haven't systematically understood is how I learn
  best. How would you even figure that out?</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Chimpanzees are amazing at <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zsXP8qeFF6A">short term spatial
  memory</a>, and do better than
  humans in these cognitive tasks on average.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Currently, the best Chess players are human-computer hybrids. Harris claims
  that computers alone will eventually be better than these hybrids, but 
  his claim that "the ape will just be adding noise" is unsubstantiated.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>About mid-way, the two discuss the analogy between AI and aliens. I haven't
  thought of this either. But I wondered how salient that analogy was given that we
  have a largely shared environment with whatever AIs we create. To the extent
  that the AIs truly are alien, I wonder how much of a unifying force these
  alien AIs could be for humanity. </p>
</li>
<li>
<p>I strongly agreed with Kelly when he says that building machine systems
  enhances our self-understanding. Building VR rendering and head tracking
  systems, you benefit from some human visual perception basics. Human
  psychology is critical for building user interfaces. You need an understanding
  of how human hearing works to build good lossy audio compression.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>An interesting thought experiment that superscedes Asimov's laws of robotics:
  what if we built AGIs that were terribly worried about what people think. Then
  we reduce the machine menace problem to merely the evils of humanity. </p>
</li>
</ul>

        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Convincing the inconvincible</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2017/convincing-the-inconvincible"/>
    
    <updated>2017-06-20T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2017/convincing-the-inconvincible</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>I highly recommend two <a href="http://loveandradio.org/2014/02/the-silver-dollar/">podcast</a> <a href="http://loveandradio.org/2017/02/how-to-argue/">episodes</a> on the theme "how to argue",
featuring Daryl Davis, <em>the</em> black friend of white supremacists. Mr. Davis is
remarkably lucid in dealing with very difficult issues, and presents great tips
for convincing the inconvincible. </p>
<ol>
<li>
<p>Gather your information. Understand their position as well as you do your
   own. Expect to hear things you will disagree with and keep your cool. </p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Invite them. Have a conversation not a debate. Debates get people's guards
   up. Instead seek to understand them. People want to be heard and speak their
   mind freely without retaliation. </p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Look for commonality. You can find something in 5 minutes and then build on
   it. Look to other issues. Politics? As you find more commonality the
   differences matter less. </p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Talking is not fighting. When the talking stops the ground becomes fertile
   for violence (cf. Sam Harris). The longer you talk the more commonalities you
   can find. </p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Patience.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Make a good first impression. Be respectful.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Don't be condescending or insulting even when you hear things you don't like.
   Expect opinions that are ridiculous and facts that are wrong. Keep cool. </p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Don't explain somebody else's movement. Let them explain it and address the
   points that they themselves define. Let them finish and don't cut them off
   even though you probably know a lot about their ideas already. </p>
</li>
</ol>
<blockquote>
<p>"While you are actively learning about someone else you are passively teaching
them about yourself." – Daryl Davis</p>
</blockquote>

        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Remembering my personal wiki</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2017/remembering-my-personal-wiki"/>
    
    <updated>2017-06-01T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2017/remembering-my-personal-wiki</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>Before I started writing this blog, I used <a href="https://moinmo.in">MoinMoin</a> as a personal wiki.
It was self-hosted on a Linux box in my parents' basement. I used it for
everything: jotting down ideas, as a calendar, storing guitar tabs, tracking
workout routines, course planning, and personal finances. I wrote on the wiki
actively from about 2002 to about 2008. Here are some blasts from the past:</p>
<ul>
<li>My Lego fandom started to shift from into robotics. To be clear,
  this is just a fancy way of saying that I was still <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Bartender/">playing</a> <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/CardDealer/">with</a>
  <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/VerticalCrossBeams/">legos</a> into my early twenties.</li>
<li>Origami interests also shifted into the <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/OrigamiSoftware/">digital realm</a>.</li>
<li>I <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Network/">maintained a network</a> of about ten Linux boxes named after
  <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Aleph/">Hebrew</a> <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Zayin/">letters</a>. What a pain in the ass!</li>
<li>Wrote a few computer games, like this uninspired <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/ArcadeTank/">tank game</a>, and this
  totally awesome <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Sponge/">pong variant</a> that was played inside a sphere.</li>
<li>Discovered <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Second-system_effect">second system syndrome</a> when trying to rewrite <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Alienation/">a web based
  RPG</a> I originally wrote in 2000.</li>
<li>Had some interesting, still relevant <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/GpsRpg/">ideas foreshadowing</a> Augmented
  Reality gaming.</li>
<li>Catalogued delicious Japanese food in <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/JapaneseRestaurants/">Vancouver</a>.</li>
<li>Smashed a Palm Tungsten <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/TungstenDestruction/">with a hammer</a> out of frustration,
  attempted to use a <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/TreoBluetoothHeadsets/">Bluetooth headset with my Treo</a> and dreamed of a
  <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/DreamGadget/">better gadget</a>.</li>
<li>Hoping to <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/MatrixWorkouts/">avoid the gym</a>, I got into <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Kettlebells/">kettlebells for fitness</a>,
  and even thought about starting a <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Gireviki/">kettlebell community</a>.</li>
<li>Saved <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Guitar(2f)Gravedigger/">guitar</a> <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Guitar(2f)WildMountainThyme/">tabs</a> I played with the intention of
  <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/LibTab/">doing something techy</a> with them later.</li>
</ul>
<p>Embarassing and endearing, <code>wiki.z3.ca</code> serves as a time capsule of my late
teens and early twenties. Je me souviens.</p>

        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Short posts using split Markdown</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2017/short-posts-using-split-markdown"/>
    
    <updated>2017-05-28T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2017/short-posts-using-split-markdown</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p><a href="https://github.com/borismus/lightning">Lightning</a>, the static blog generator that powers this site, is
awesome for long form content. But it does not work well for short form content,
since creating each post requires a bunch of up-front effort:</p>
<ol>
<li>
<p>I navigate to the right place, recalling the current year (!) and deciding on
   the slug for the post (eg. <code>content/posts/2017/how-to-fix-the-world</code>).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>I manually create the <code>index.md</code> file and then specify the redundant
   human-readable title and the posted date within it:</p>
<pre><code>How to Fix the World
===
posted: May 28, 2017

Listen to me, I have the answers.
</code></pre>
</li>
</ol>
<p>After writing the post, the title will inevitably have changed, so I rename the
slug to match: <code>mv how-to-fix-the-world how-to-slightly-improve-the-world</code>.
Finally I publish and tweet, and hopefully the world becomes infinitesimally
better.</p>
<p>I once tried to <a href="/easier-link-blogging/">make it easier to keep a lightning-style link blog</a>, but
ended up scrapping the solution because it was buggy and required a Mac.</p>
<h2>Split markdown pages</h2>
<p>My aim was to remove the up-front costs I described above. Appending to the top
of an existing file and having the engine automatically generate a slug based on
the title seemed like the right approach. This means that one markdown file
results in multiple HTML pages. The latest <a href="https://github.com/borismus/lightning">Lightning</a> has been
updated with split markdown files, and refactored into classes, making it easier
to add features in the future. To give a sense of what these split markdown
files look like, take a look at <a href="https://github.com/borismus/smus.com/blob/master/notes_all.md">this file</a>.</p>
<p>Split markdown files power two new sections on this site: a [book
reviews section]<a href="/books">books</a>, and a <a href="/notes">notes section</a>. I'm hoping that this
added convenience will encourage me to write shorter, more focused posts with
increasing frequency.</p>

        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Analogies from the industrial revolution</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2017/analogies-from-the-industrial-revolution"/>
    
    <updated>2017-05-24T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2017/analogies-from-the-industrial-revolution</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>Several centuries after the industrial revolution, machines still can't do all
physical things humans can, not even by a long shot. Drawing a masterwork,
singing an aria, playing a musical instrument, manipulating a soft object,
cutting hair, taking care of the sick are all examples of human-only tasks. The
industrial revolution gave machines the ability to do crude, physically
demanding work at scale, but it did not address all of physicality.</p>
<p>Just like the industrial revolution did not automate all aspects of physical
work, there is good reason to believe that the AI revolution will not solve
all aspects of intellectual work. Where the line will be drawn remains to be
seen, but I would bet that one aspect of human cognition that isn't really at
risk from any immediate AI-based disruption are creative pursuits. Many well
respected professions like doctor, lawyer, and engineer have both a rote
component that lends itself easily to automation, and a creative one. Some
examples:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Curing patients boils down to the application of known heuristics to
  triage specific cases, but if you are a MD-PhD studying a new area of medicine
  or tackling a new disease, it's a much more creative and speculative process. </p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The legal profession involves finding the right precedents relevant to the case
  at hand, but articulating a convincing argument or deciding how to work out a
  new situation where there are now laws yet? Creativity.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Designing a marketing webpage for a clothing brand is pretty formulaic. But
  inventing way of solving a problem using new technology? Totally creative. </p>
</li>
</ul>

        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>