<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
      xml:lang="en"
      xml:base="https://smus.com">
  <title>Boris Smus (Notes)</title>
  <link href="https://smus.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://smus.com"/>
  <updated>2020-02-12T09:15:17-00:00</updated>
  <id>https://smus.com/atom.xml</id>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Books highlights of 2019</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2019/books-highlights-of-2019/"/>
    
    <updated>2019-12-31T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2019/books-highlights-of-2019/</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>I’ve been reading and summarizing for five years now (cue Ratatat). I’m not sure that it’s helped much with retention, but at the very least, having an easily searchable corpus of my book-related notes is worthwhile.</p>

<p>A decent year for fiction, I finally read <a href="/books/invisible-cities-by-italo-calvino/">Invisible Cities</a>, which I enjoyed not viscerally, but more as an art piece. I liked <a href="/books/the-fiddler-is-a-good-woman/">The Fiddler is a Good Woman</a> for the author’s ability to retell the same sordid tale from multiple perspectives. <a href="http://localhost:5500/books/diamond-age-by-stephenson-audio/">Diamond Age</a> was a collection of incredible ideas and surprisingly relevant for my job. I also enjoyed <a href="/books/hyperion-by-dan-simmons-audio/">Hyperion</a>, especially Sol Weintraub’s tale, which touched me deeply. <a href="/books/the-fifth-season-by-n-k-jemisin/">The Fifth Season</a> was interesting, but I have some identitarian reservations. I think my overall fiction highlight was <a href="/books/the-odyssey-translated-by-emily-wilson-audio/">Homer’s Odyssey translated by Emily Wilson</a>.</p>

<p>I read two non-fiction books which were a little too extreme for my tastes: <a href="/books/deschooling-society-by-ivan-illich">Deschooling Society</a>, which just read like an angry and ill considered screed and <a href="/books/radical-markets-by-posner-and-weyl/">Radical Markets</a>, which had some really interesting ideas, but presented as a whole seemed ridiculous. I really enjoyed <a href="/books/timefulness-by-marcia-bjornerud-audio/">Timefulness</a>, a whirlwind overview of geology, and <a href="/books/range-by-david-epstein-audio/">Range</a>, an ode to generalists. The standout non-fiction for me was <a href="/books/seeing-like-a-state-by-james-scott/">Seeing Like a State</a>, which will continue to turn over in my mind for years to come. I listened to fewer history lectures than usual, but can wholeheartedly recommend <a href="/books/the-story-of-medieval-england-audio/">The Story of Medieval England</a>. Instead, I focused on parenting books, which are pretty bad as a genre. That said, <a href="/books/the-new-father/">The New Father</a> served as a worthwhile companion to skim during the first year of Eliana’s life, and <a href="/books/yes-brain-by-siegel-and-bryson/">Yes Brain</a> had practical suggestions for digesting mindfulness into something that small children might be able to understand.</p>

<p>I also begun a new long-term book summarization project, which is to digest <a href="">Asimov's Chronology of Science and Discovery</a>, and visualize it as a Civ-style tech tree. Hopefully I’ll have something to report on that front in 2020!</p>


        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Article highlights of 2019</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2019/article-highlights-of-2019/"/>
    
    <updated>2019-12-31T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2019/article-highlights-of-2019/</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>I’m still using Instapaper for reading online things, although in 2020, my aim is to read articles (even) less, in favor of books.</p>

<ul>
<li>Try to install a radar system with one job: Searching for chances to give a compliment. <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/everybody-is-stupid-except-you/201812/compliments-how-get-happy-and-make-better-world">Compliments: How to Get Happy and Make a Better World</a></li>
<li>Warren Buffett’s metric of success is “Do the people you care about love you back?” <a href="https://www.gatesnotes.com/About-Bill-Gates/Year-in-Review-2018">What I learned at work this year</a></li>
<li>As Edelman points out, if YouTube really cared about our intentions and values, when we logged on to learn ukulele it would try to serve that need — and then send us off to practice! <a href="https://time.com/5505431/internet-feel-awful-dignity/">The Internet Can Make Us Feel Awful. It Doesn't Have to Be That Way</a></li>
<li>Wisdom as the ultimate virtue. Really solid framing in favor of centrism. <a href="https://www.shanesnow.com/articles/values/">How to be good: A theory about Virtues &amp; Values</a>
\<!--more--></li>
<li>From 1200 to 1745, 21-year-olds would reach an average age of anywhere between 62 and 70 years. <a href="https://www.bbc.com/future/article/20181002-how-long-did-ancient-people-live-life-span-versus-longevity">Do we really live longer than our ancestors?</a></li>
<li>Nick Cave isn’t just an awesome musician, but is also quite eloquent. “What we are actually listening to is human limitation and the audacity to transcend it.” <a href="https://www.brainpickings.org/2019/01/24/nick-cave-music-ai/">Music, Feeling, and Transcendence: Nick Cave on AI, Awe, and the Splendor of Our Human Limitations</a></li>
<li>Seismic air guns are widely used to map the sea floor. They are incredibly loud and disruptive to ocean fauna. <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/01/22/science/oceans-whales-noise-offshore-drilling.html">Oceans Are Getting Louder, Posing Potential Threats to Marine Life</a></li>
<li>Unlike traditional two-by-four lumber, cross-laminated timber (CLT) consists of layers of wood glued together to form solid, thick panels that can be made in custom dimensions for anything from walls and floors to beams and roofs. CLT is being used to build mid-rise buildings, including big swaths of Google Sidewalk in Toronto. <a href="https://www.financialexpress.com/industry/skyscrapers-made-of-wood-make-a-return-nudged-by-google/1482316/">Skyscrapers made of wood make a return, nudged by google</a></li>
<li>Peter Turchin: “the way forward to sustaining and increasing the well-being of large segments of population is not to abolish government, but to evolve institutions that keep bureaucrats working for the benefit of the population, rather than themselves.” <a href="http://peterturchin.com/cliodynamica/an-anarchist-view-of-human-social-evolution/">An Anarchist View of Human Social Evolution</a></li>
<li>The scary thing about GPT-2-generated text is that it flows very naturally if you’re just skimming. <a href="https://srconstantin.wordpress.com/2019/02/25/humans-who-are-not-concentrating-are-not-general-intelligences/">Humans Who Are Not Concentrating Are Not General Intelligences</a></li>
<li>I disagree with Stratechery that the web is better today than it was when we were punching monkeys, but he writes terrifyingly about Spotify’s role in today’s podcast marketplace. <a href="https://stratechery.com/2019/spotifys-podcast-aggregation-play/">Spotify’s Podcast Aggregation Play</a></li>
<li>A stark look at the rising costs of digital goods and their implications for working poor. <a href="https://reallifemag.com/well-played-store-credit/">Video games are teaching users how to enjoy perpetually renting consumer goods rather than owning them</a></li>
<li>I thought the Albedo effect only applied to melting ice caps, but as it turns out, it also applies to clouds! <a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/cloud-loss-could-add-8-degrees-to-global-warming-20190225/">A World Without Clouds</a></li>
<li>What came first, the moralizing God or the complex society? Evidence points to the latter, followed by Gods-as-divine-policemen. <a href="https://gizmodo.com/humans-built-complex-societies-before-they-invented-mor-1833436320">Humans Built Complex Societies Before They Invented Moral Gods</a></li>
<li>The American public is broadly pessimistic about its country’s future, and this pessimism correlates with education level. <a href="https://www.pewsocialtrends.org/2019/03/21/public-sees-an-america-in-decline-on-many-fronts/">Looking to the Future, Public Sees an America in Decline on Many Fronts</a></li>
<li>As wealthy kids are growing up with less screen time, poor kids are growing up with more. <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/03/23/sunday-review/human-contact-luxury-screens.html">Human Contact Is Now a Luxury Good</a></li>
<li>Stop building to ship until you’ve first built to learn. <a href="https://uxdesign.cc/building-to-learn-977a8cd88ced?">https://uxdesign.cc/building-to-learn-977a8cd88ced?</a></li>
<li>A charitable look at Post-modernism holds that there is no privileged lens with which to view the world; that even empiricism is suspect, because it too has a tendency to reproduce and reify the power structures in which in exists. <a href="https://socratic-form-microscopy.com/2019/04/03/post-modernism-and-political-diversity/">https://socratic-form-microscopy.com/2019/04/03/post-modernism-and-political-diversity/</a></li>
<li>Texas produces more wind power than every other state in the country, four times as much as the runner-up, California. <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2019/04/11/magazine/climate-change-exxon-renewable-energy.html?mtrref=www.instapaper.com&amp;gwh=A83B2941A03E83BDCAE36DF6FD0D3189&amp;gwt=pay&amp;assetType=REGIWALL">https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2019/04/11/magazine/climate-change-exxon-renewable-energy.html?mtrref=www.instapaper.com&amp;gwh=A83B2941A03E83BDCAE36DF6FD0D3189&amp;gwt=pay&amp;assetType=REGIWALL</a></li>
<li>While I disagree that there may be a difference between personal and professional values, I found this brief article to be a useful exercise. <a href="https://blog.alexmaccaw.com/a-value-driven-life">https://blog.alexmaccaw.com/a-value-driven-life</a></li>
<li>Formidable pays employees $20/hr for contributions (outside of normal work time) to OSS and tech communities or even a personal hack project purely for fun and learning, as long as it’s released under an OSI license. <a href="https://formidable.com/blog/2019/sauce-program/">https://formidable.com/blog/2019/sauce-program/</a></li>
<li>Look at how everyone else is doing it (the likely local maxima) and then find a better way. <a href="https://www.nateliason.com/blog/local-maxima">https://www.nateliason.com/blog/local-maxima</a></li>
<li>A look into some of Duolingo’s limitations. Learning a language with an app should be a starting point, not the end.<a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/05/04/smarter-living/500-days-of-duolingo-what-you-can-and-cant-learn-from-a-language-app.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2019/05/04/smarter-living/500-days-of-duolingo-what-you-can-and-cant-learn-from-a-language-app.html</a></li>
<li>A Facebook co-founder wants the US government to fix Facebook. <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/05/09/opinion/sunday/chris-hughes-facebook-zuckerberg.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2019/05/09/opinion/sunday/chris-hughes-facebook-zuckerberg.html</a></li>
<li>How might we design mediums in which “reading” is the same as “understanding”? <a href="https://andymatuschak.org/books/">https://andymatuschak.org/books/</a></li>
<li>Safe playgrounds lead to boredom, which tends toward rash stunts like turning somersaults on top of climbing frames and standing on the shoulders of others on the swings. So let’s make playgrounds a little more dangerous! <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/05/10/well/family/adventure-playgrounds-junk-playgrounds.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2019/05/10/well/family/adventure-playgrounds-junk-playgrounds.html</a></li>
<li>What Republicans want to do with I.C.E. and border walls, wealthy progressive Democrats are doing with zoning and NIMBYism. Ouch. <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/05/22/opinion/california-housing-nimby.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2019/05/22/opinion/california-housing-nimby.html</a></li>
<li>We were certain that more communication would make everything better. Arrogantly, we ignored history and learned a lesson that has been in the curriculum since the Tower of Babel. <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/why-we-love-tech-defense-difficult-industry/">https://www.wired.com/story/why-we-love-tech-defense-difficult-industry/</a></li>
<li>What are signs that a player is alive? One strong sign is a player doing things outside of their domain. For example, Putin is a live player. The Russian state is doing things they haven’t done in a long time, like annexing Crimea… <a href="https://medium.com/@samo.burja/live-versus-dead-players-2b24f6e9eae2">https://medium.com/@samo.burja/live-versus-dead-players-2b24f6e9eae2</a></li>
<li>San Francisco is a stunningly beautiful and continuously innovative city, cursed to always be considered one or two generations past its peak, like a rowboat chasing the horizon. <a href="https://www.sfchronicle.com/oursf/article/San-Francisco-isn-t-what-it-used-to-be-13901994.php">https://www.sfchronicle.com/oursf/article/San-Francisco-isn-t-what-it-used-to-be-13901994.php</a></li>
<li>The hallmark of sociological storytelling is if it can encourage us to put ourselves in the place of any character. GoT used to be like that, but then turned into a story about heroes. <a href="https://blogs.scientificamerican.com/observations/the-real-reason-fans-hate-the-last-season-of-game-of-thrones/">https://blogs.scientificamerican.com/observations/the-real-reason-fans-hate-the-last-season-of-game-of-thrones/</a></li>
<li>An attempt to integrate cybernetics, counterculture, computing, and design. <a href="http://www.dubberly.com/articles/cybernetics-and-counterculture.html">http://www.dubberly.com/articles/cybernetics-and-counterculture.html</a></li>
<li>If AI were a great storyteller, it would be an alien bard who has studied our planet from orbit and still doesn’t get it; but the tales it tells embarrass us with their insights all the same. <a href="https://emshort.blog/2019/04/04/can-ai-tell-a-good-story/">https://emshort.blog/2019/04/04/can-ai-tell-a-good-story/</a></li>
<li>Quadratic Voting is too complicated for the average person, but the idea of having a finite number of tokens to distribute amongst a set of important issues is a good one. <a href="https://lawreview.uchicago.edu/publication/qv-or-not-qv-question-some-skepticism-about-radical-egalitarian-voting-markets">https://lawreview.uchicago.edu/publication/qv-or-not-qv-question-some-skepticism-about-radical-egalitarian-voting-markets</a></li>
<li>A whole, unmilled tree can support 50 percent more weight than the largest piece of lumber milled from the same tree. <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2009/11/05/garden/05tree.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2009/11/05/garden/05tree.html</a></li>
<li>Where do ideas come from? <a href="https://nadiaeghbal.com/ideas">https://nadiaeghbal.com/ideas</a></li>
<li>Cliff Mass correctly predicted that we’d have fewer wildfires in the PNW, great example of regression towards the mean. <a href="https://cliffmass.blogspot.com/2019/05/will-puget-sound-experience-another.html">https://cliffmass.blogspot.com/2019/05/will-puget-sound-experience-another.html</a></li>
<li>Bungalows in places like Wallingford and Ballard that many now find charming were widely criticized as cheap when they began popping up in the early part of the 20th century. Who knows how Seattle’s modern builds will age? <a href="https://www.seattletimes.com/business/real-estate/a-teardown-a-day-bulldozing-the-way-for-bigger-homes-in-seattle-suburbs/">https://www.seattletimes.com/business/real-estate/a-teardown-a-day-bulldozing-the-way-for-bigger-homes-in-seattle-suburbs/</a></li>
<li>That skyscraper in Vancouver prominently seen from Granville bridge (northbound) is also designed by big.dk. <a href="https://www.dezeen.com/2018/11/30/movie-big-heatherwick-google-hq-progress/">https://www.dezeen.com/2018/11/30/movie-big-heatherwick-google-hq-progress/</a></li>
<li>Half of parents are fathers, yet 99% of the research on parenting focuses on mothers. <a href="https://www.bbc.com/future/article/20190606-how-to-be-a-good-father-to-a-newborn-son-or-daughter">https://www.bbc.com/future/article/20190606-how-to-be-a-good-father-to-a-newborn-son-or-daughter</a></li>
<li>Massive migration of G+ accounts from Google accounts gave people the impression G+ was a “ghost town.” <a href="https://onezero.medium.com/why-google-failed-4b9db05b973b">https://onezero.medium.com/why-google-failed-4b9db05b973b</a></li>
<li>Identify and avoid cargo cults in design thinking. <a href="https://medium.com/designing-atlassian/when-design-becomes-a-cargo-cult-2bb9a50aad53">https://medium.com/designing-atlassian/when-design-becomes-a-cargo-cult-2bb9a50aad53</a></li>
<li>80% of the aviation industry's emissions come from passenger flights longer than 1,500km - a distance no electric airliner could yet fly. <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/business-48630656">https://www.bbc.com/news/business-48630656</a></li>
<li>‘Sleeping beauties’ are papers which didn’t have much influence early but come to be appreciated and important later. <a href="https://news.uchicago.edu/story/new-model-reveals-forgotten-influencers-and-sleeping-beauties-science">https://news.uchicago.edu/story/new-model-reveals-forgotten-influencers-and-sleeping-beauties-science</a></li>
<li>Our superpower is not raw intelligence but our ability to learn through imitation. Aggregated over generations, this becomes culture.<a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2019/06/04/book-review-the-secret-of-our-success/">https://slatestarcodex.com/2019/06/04/book-review-the-secret-of-our-success/</a></li>
<li>Banned about 70 years ago in Seattle, parent-in-law apartments were again allowed across the city starting in 1994 and backyard cottages since 2010. <a href="https://www.seattletimes.com/seattle-news/politics/seattle-city-council-oks-more-and-larger-backyard-cottages-restricts-mcmansions/">https://www.seattletimes.com/seattle-news/politics/seattle-city-council-oks-more-and-larger-backyard-cottages-restricts-mcmansions/</a></li>
<li>The Baumol effect: “A violinist can always choose to stop playing violin, retrain for a while, and work in a factory instead. Maybe in 1826, when factory owners were earning $1.14/hour and violinists were earning $5/hour, so no violinists would quit and retrain. But by 2010, factory workers were earning $26.44/hour, so if violinists were still only earning $5 they might all quit and retrain.” <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2019/06/10/book-review-the-prices-are-too-dmn-high/">https://slatestarcodex.com/2019/06/10/book-review-the-prices-are-too-dmn-high/</a></li>
<li>Mistake theorists treat politics as science, engineering, or medicine. The State is diseased. Conflict theorists treat politics as war. Different blocs with different interests. <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2018/01/24/conflict-vs-mistake/">https://slatestarcodex.com/2018/01/24/conflict-vs-mistake/</a></li>
<li>It’s hard to separate the threat that technology poses from the threat that capitalism poses. <a href="https://www.gq.com/story/ted-chiang-exhalation-interview">https://www.gq.com/story/ted-chiang-exhalation-interview</a></li>
<li>Convenience is a value, and one we hold personally. Maybe it’s worth reconsidering this. <a href="https://onezero.medium.com/the-tyranny-of-convenience-2e7fa145ab4">https://onezero.medium.com/the-tyranny-of-convenience-2e7fa145ab4</a></li>
<li>We don’t want hectoring morality tales, as evidenced by The Odyssey’s exceeding popularity compared to Plato’s Republic. We want stories that let us be other characters: strong and cunning, defiant or afraid, good or bad or somewhere in between. <a href="https://putanumonit.com/2019/06/25/playstation-odysseys/">https://putanumonit.com/2019/06/25/playstation-odysseys/</a></li>
<li>A scene with active technological evolution has what musician Brian Eno called scenius. <a href="https://breakingsmart.substack.com/p/following-the-scenius">https://breakingsmart.substack.com/p/following-the-scenius</a></li>
<li>The Antidisciplinarathon is a compelling format to quickly broaden one’s purview, ramp up on new fields, and meet new interesting people. <a href="http://hypotext.co/antidisciplinarathon">http://hypotext.co/antidisciplinarathon</a></li>
<li>The vast resources of Silicon Valley have too often been applied to the problem of “what is my mother no longer doing for me?” <a href="https://slate.com/culture/2019/06/life-hacking-productivity-tech-silicon-valley-hacking-life-book-review.html">https://slate.com/culture/2019/06/life-hacking-productivity-tech-silicon-valley-hacking-life-book-review.html</a></li>
<li>AFAICT, Deinstitutionalisation => Homelessness. <a href="https://www.npr.org/2019/07/12/736612514/seattle-faces-backlash-after-easing-up-on-punishing-crimes-involving-mental-illn">https://www.npr.org/2019/07/12/736612514/seattle-faces-backlash-after-easing-up-on-punishing-crimes-involving-mental-illn</a></li>
<li>We would like to think there is some quick hack, or that we can learn something with it feeling like a simple game, but the true is that real learning is hard work and frustrating. <a href="https://medium.com/@gjdickens/distraction-disguised-as-learning-duolingo-codeacademy-and-why-you-should-get-back-to-basics-99a22a9e2c33">https://medium.com/@gjdickens/distraction-disguised-as-learning-duolingo-codeacademy-and-why-you-should-get-back-to-basics-99a22a9e2c33</a></li>
<li>China seems unlikely to do personalized learning well, but appear to be far ahead in many aspects of optimizing education. <a href="https://www.technologyreview.com/s/614057/china-squirrel-has-started-a-grand-experiment-in-ai-education-it-could-reshape-how-the/">https://www.technologyreview.com/s/614057/china-squirrel-has-started-a-grand-experiment-in-ai-education-it-could-reshape-how-the/</a></li>
<li>Some studies seem to indicate that not only do students retain less when reading digitally, they’re more likely to overestimate how well they comprehended the material. <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/digital-textbooks-radical-transformation/">https://www.wired.com/story/digital-textbooks-radical-transformation/</a></li>
<li>Because the 737 has kept the same name for 50 years, the FAA certification of the fourth-generation 737 in 2017 involved only light-touch approval. The only really rigorous test-result underpinnings were those of the 1967 machine. <a href="https://www.edge.org/conversation/timothy_taylor-polythetics-and-the-boeing-737-max">https://www.edge.org/conversation/timothy_taylor-polythetics-and-the-boeing-737-max</a></li>
<li>Criticize the existence of billionaires in general, their spending on yachts or mansions. But if you only criticize billionaires when they’re trying to save lives, you risk collateral damage to everything we care about. <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2019/07/29/against-against-billionaire-philanthropy/">https://slatestarcodex.com/2019/07/29/against-against-billionaire-philanthropy/</a></li>
<li>A resurrected Franklin wouldn’t have a news job inside The Washington Post; he’d have an anonymous Twitter account with a huge following that he’d use to routinely troll political opponents. <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/journalism-isnt-dying-its-returning-its-roots/">https://www.wired.com/story/journalism-isnt-dying-its-returning-its-roots/</a></li>
<li>Tech workers might not realize that their opposition to the work their companies do on military technology does not change the decision-making of the American leaders who choose to go to war. <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/08/28/opinion/military-war-tech-us.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2019/08/28/opinion/military-war-tech-us.html</a></li>
<li>AI-writer centaurs are super interesting. <a href="https://www.vox.com/future-perfect/2019/8/30/20840194/ai-art-fiction-writing-language-gpt-2">https://www.vox.com/future-perfect/2019/8/30/20840194/ai-art-fiction-writing-language-gpt-2</a></li>
<li>“Isn’t school for learning math and science and reading,” he asked us one day, “not for teachers to tell us what to think about society?” <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2019/10/when-the-culture-war-comes-for-the-kids/596668/">https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2019/10/when-the-culture-war-comes-for-the-kids/596668/</a></li>
<li>Study after study has shown open offices to foster seclusion more than innovation. People in an open office put on headphones, talk less, and feel terrible. <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/09/25/opinion/wework-adam-neumann.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2019/09/25/opinion/wework-adam-neumann.html</a></li>
<li>Great summary of arguments in favor of and also against Sortition - the system whereby members of representative bodies are picked at random, like jurors.<a href="http://edmundgriffiths.com/sortition.html">http://edmundgriffiths.com/sortition.html</a></li>
<li>Rather than maintaining my own lawn, much better to have a smaller garden and live right beside a great park? <a href="https://earther.gizmodo.com/lawns-are-an-ecological-disaster-1826070720">https://earther.gizmodo.com/lawns-are-an-ecological-disaster-1826070720</a></li>
<li>We’re not merely lighting a match to the Amazon and imperiling everything that lives in it with extinction, but also summoning creatures long dead to return to Earth’s surface and give up the ancient energy they took to the grave. <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/science/archive/2019/08/amazon-fire-earth-has-plenty-oxygen/596923/">https://www.theatlantic.com/science/archive/2019/08/amazon-fire-earth-has-plenty-oxygen/596923/</a></li>
<li>In the last 20 years, some Inuit communities who had never seen robins before have had to invent a name for them: “Koyapigaktoruk.” <a href="https://earthsky.org/earth/decoding-climate-change-signals-arctic-treeline-tundra-alaska">https://earthsky.org/earth/decoding-climate-change-signals-arctic-treeline-tundra-alaska</a></li>
<li>Yedoma consists of thick layers of soil packed around gigantic lodes of embedded ice. Because Yedoma contains so much ice, it can melt quickly — reshaping the landscape as sudden lakes form and hillsides collapse. <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/graphics/2019/national/climate-environment/climate-change-siberia/">https://www.washingtonpost.com/graphics/2019/national/climate-environment/climate-change-siberia/</a></li>
<li>Wikis are just editable web pages; Twitter is just a way of sharing very short form writing; and Facebook is just a way of sharing writing and pictures with friends. Indeed, writing itself is just a clever way of ordering a small number of symbols on a page. While a medium may be simple, that doesn’t mean it’s not profound. <a href="https://numinous.productions/ttft/">https://numinous.productions/ttft/</a></li>
<li>For middle-class and poor families, the picture is different. Federal income taxes have also declined modestly for these families, but they haven’t benefited much if at all from the decline in the corporate tax or estate tax. <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2019/10/06/opinion/income-tax-rate-wealthy.html">https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2019/10/06/opinion/income-tax-rate-wealthy.html</a></li>
<li>The idea of the Anthropocene inflates our own importance by promising eternal geological life to our creations. It is of a thread with our species’ peculiar, self-styled exceptionalism. <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/science/archive/2019/08/arrogance-anthropocene/595795/">https://www.theatlantic.com/science/archive/2019/08/arrogance-anthropocene/595795/</a></li>
<li>To Western ears, the combination of C and F# is grating, but Tsimane listeners rated this chord just as likeable as other chords that Westerners would interpret as more pleasant, such as C and G. <a href="https://cosmosmagazine.com/biology/perception-of-musical-pitch-varies-across-cultures">https://cosmosmagazine.com/biology/perception-of-musical-pitch-varies-across-cultures</a></li>
<li>It doesn’t seem too soon to ask: Is the vision of the VR or AR headset as a widespread consumer device just a dead branch hanging off technology’s evolutionary tree? <a href="https://www.fastcompany.com/90418190/the-one-thing-google-didnt-talk-about-at-its-keynote">https://www.fastcompany.com/90418190/the-one-thing-google-didnt-talk-about-at-its-keynote</a></li>
<li>Some examples of people quickly accomplishing ambitious things together. <a href="https://patrickcollison.com/fast">https://patrickcollison.com/fast</a></li>
<li>On-device AI could be clutch for detecting illegal logging. <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/10/15/climate/indonesia-logging-deforestation.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2019/10/15/climate/indonesia-logging-deforestation.html</a></li>
<li>Technology that’s Actually Yours could be the next great counter-trend. <a href="https://alexdanco.com/2019/10/26/everything-is-amazing-but-nothing-is-ours/">https://alexdanco.com/2019/10/26/everything-is-amazing-but-nothing-is-ours/</a></li>
<li>Utrecht has a bike garage with sensors on the racks, making finding a free spot during rush hour much easier. <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2017/09/06/world/europe/bicycling-utrecht-dutch-love-bikes-worlds-largest-bike-parking-garages.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2017/09/06/world/europe/bicycling-utrecht-dutch-love-bikes-worlds-largest-bike-parking-garages.html</a></li>
<li>By pushing a highly political agenda the Anxious, Social-Justice, Partisan (ASP) movement is undermining bipartisan efforts--and nothing important will be done unless both sides of the aisle are involved. <a href="https://cliffmass.blogspot.com/2019/10/the-real-climate-debate.html">https://cliffmass.blogspot.com/2019/10/the-real-climate-debate.html</a></li>
<li>The party launched the app, called Study the Great Nation, containing articles and videos about Xi’s activities or his ideology, “Xi Jinping Thought.” There is even a sense of competition, with users earning points for reading articles and commenting on them, and a leader board showing how users are faring in quizzes. <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/world/asia_pacific/chinese-app-on-xis-ideology-allows-data-access-to-100-million-users-phones-report-says/2019/10/11/2d53bbae-eb4d-11e9-bafb-da248f8d5734_story.html">https://www.washingtonpost.com/world/asia_pacific/chinese-app-on-xis-ideology-allows-data-access-to-100-million-users-phones-report-says/2019/10/11/2d53bbae-eb4d-11e9-bafb-da248f8d5734_story.html</a></li>
<li>Younger Palestinians were interested (in improving relations with Israel), but that there were none well-established enough in their careers yet to withstand the blowback. <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/11/20/us/israel-arab-dialog.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2019/11/20/us/israel-arab-dialog.html</a></li>
<li>Clustering meetings and scheduling them near breaks is ideal. One of the best times is near the end of the day, or right before lunch. <a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/makersschedule.html">http://www.paulgraham.com/makersschedule.html</a></li>
<li>Terrifying: ISPs would recognize the obsolescence of the internet and support the Trinet only, driven by market demand for optimal user experience from GOOG-FB-AMZN. <a href="https://staltz.com/the-web-began-dying-in-2014-heres-how.html">https://staltz.com/the-web-began-dying-in-2014-heres-how.html</a></li>
<li>Saildrones are autonomous sailboats that act as mobile weather stations. Could we take advantage of this capability to improve observations of important storms? <a href="https://cliffmass.blogspot.com/2019/11/can-autonomous-weather-observation.html">https://cliffmass.blogspot.com/2019/11/can-autonomous-weather-observation.html</a></li>
<li>Prediction is overrated. What we really should be striving for, with our social science, is ability to bring about desirable outcomes and to avoid unwanted outcomes. <a href="http://peterturchin.com/cliodynamica/psychohistory-and-cliodynamics/">http://peterturchin.com/cliodynamica/psychohistory-and-cliodynamics/</a></li>
<li>If until now you were used to moving along roads and sidewalks, forget it! From now on we all walk through walls! <a href="http://www.bldgblog.com/2010/01/nakatomi-space/">http://www.bldgblog.com/2010/01/nakatomi-space/</a></li>
<li>What would it take to create an effective developmental learning environment for humanity? <a href="https://glazkov.com/2019/08/11/a-classroom-for-humanity/">https://glazkov.com/2019/08/11/a-classroom-for-humanity/</a></li>
<li>Great mathematicians each had their own strategies for generating ideas. Erdős sought hyper-focussed vigilance, Poincaré described lying in bed in a half-dream state as the ideal condition, Descartes famously loved to lounge in bed in the morning and think. <a href="https://www.newyorker.com/culture/annals-of-inquiry/the-myth-and-magic-of-generating-new-ideas?verso=true">https://www.newyorker.com/culture/annals-of-inquiry/the-myth-and-magic-of-generating-new-ideas?verso=true</a></li>
<li>On the Estonian border, another anekdot goes, a border guard is filling out Putin’s entry form. “Occupation?” the officer asks. “Not today,” Putin replies. “Just tourism.” <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/ideas/archive/2019/11/russian-jokes-tell-deeper-truths-about-putin-and-trump/602713/">https://www.theatlantic.com/ideas/archive/2019/11/russian-jokes-tell-deeper-truths-about-putin-and-trump/602713/</a></li>
<li>The Reigns mechanic requires making pragmatic choices to stay alive, not always being ideologically consistent, and working to find a way out over course of generations, slowly discovering one’s true nature and power. <a href="https://emshort.blog/2018/01/24/reigns-her-majesty/">https://emshort.blog/2018/01/24/reigns-her-majesty/</a></li>
<li><a href="http://mkremins.github.io/blog/gardening-games/">In exploration games, to spend time in a place is to deplete it, to make it less and less interesting until there’s no longer any reason to stay. In gardening games, to spend time in a place is to enrich it.</a> </li>
<li>The intersection of Science Fiction and Religion often yields greatness. <a href="https://urbigenous.net/library/nine_billion_names_of_god.html">https://urbigenous.net/library/nine_billion_names_of_god.html</a></li>
</ul>


        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Avoiding local maximums</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2019/avoiding-local-maximums/"/>
    
    <updated>2019-05-22T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2019/avoiding-local-maximums/</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>Easier said than done.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/local-maxima.png" alt="Don't focus on local maxima: easier said than done." /></p>


        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Reading in 2018</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2019/reading-in-2018/"/>
    
    <updated>2019-01-10T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2019/reading-in-2018/</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>I read and listened to a few <a href="/books">books</a> in 2018. My highlights include
speculative fiction stories from Chinese authors: <a href="/books/the-truth-of-fact-the-truth-of-feeling-by-ted-chiang/">Ted
Chiang</a>, <a href="/books/three-body-problem-by-liu-cixin-audio/">Liu
Cixin</a>, <a href="/books/infinite-planets/">Ken Liu's translations
of</a>, Chen Qiufan, Xia Jia, Hao Jingfang. Also really
enjoyed <a href="/books/player-of-games-by-iain-m-banks/">Player of Games</a> and <a href="/books/darkness-at-noon-by-arthur-koestler-audio/">Darkness
at Noon</a>. On the non-fiction
front, I listened to two excellent history lectures: one on <a href="/books/the-fall-and-rise-of-china-audio/">modern
China</a>, another on the <a href="/books/living-the-french-revolution-audio/">French
Revolution</a>. I also read a pair of
books describing cyclical views of history: <a href="/books/the-fourth-turning-by-howe-and-strauss/">The Fourth
Turning</a> and a more scientific
take, <a href="/books/war-and-peace-and-war-by-peter-turchin/">War and Peace and War</a>.
A standout non-fiction favorite was <a href="/books/impro-by-keith-johnstone/">Impro</a>,
which I will definitely be returning to.</p>

<p>Most of my internet reading happens through Instapaper, which affords me a 
handy chronicle of articles that I enjoyed. Here are a few of them (excerpts are
not endorsements):</p>

<!--more-->

<ul>
<li>Between 1900 and 1910, Seattle’s population tripled, from just over 80,000 to
more than 230,000 people. <a href="http://archive.kuow.org/post/story-behind-seattles-obsession-craftsman-homes">The Story Behind Seattle's Obsession With Craftsman
Homes</a></li>
<li>The demo drew rave reviews from the technology press. <a href="https://www.1843magazine.com/technology/the-daily/no-googles-pixel-buds-wont-change-the-world">No, Google’s Pixel Buds
won’t change the
world</a></li>
<li>That’s home. That’s us. On it everyone you love, everyone you know, everyone
you ever heard of, every human being who ever was, lived out their lives.
<a href="https://www.brainpickings.org/2012/12/10/pale-blue-dot-motion-graphics/">Carl Sagan’s Pale Blue Dot, Animated in Motion
Graphics</a></li>
<li>Our choice is not between "regulation" and "no regulation." The code
regulates. It implements values, or not. It enables freedoms, or disables
them. It protects privacy, or promotes monitoring. <a href="https://harvardmagazine.com/2000/01/code-is-law-html">Code Is
Law</a></li>
<li>In other words: AIs are best at choosing answers. Humans are best at choosing
questions. <a href="https://jods.mitpress.mit.edu/pub/issue3-case">How To Become A
Centaur</a></li>
<li>Today’s belief in ineluctable certainty is the true innovation-killer of our
age. In this environment, the best an audacious manager can do is to develop
small improvements to existing systems — climbing the hill, as it were, toward
a local maximum, trimming fat, eking out the occasional tiny innovation — like
city planners painting bicycle lanes on the streets as a gesture toward
solving our energy problems. <a href="https://www.wired.com/2011/10/stephenson-innovation-starvation/">Innovation
Starvation</a></li>
<li>There is no reason to let a company make so much money while potentially
helping to radicalize billions of people <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2018/03/10/opinion/sunday/youtube-politics-radical.html">YouTube, the Great
Radicalizer</a></li>
<li>Favoring the “soft” aspects of a college application is straightforwardly
beneficial to the more privileged at the expense of the less. <a href="https://jacobinmag.com/2018/03/sat-class-race-inequality-college-admission">The Progressive
Case for the
SAT</a></li>
<li>Science fiction allows us the distance to circumvent issue fatigue in our very
troubled times. <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-017-08674-8">Science fiction when the future is
now</a></li>
<li>Isaiah Berlin, sobered by the 20th century’s failed utopias, has argued for a
more modest liberal pluralism that makes room for multiple, genuinely
conflicting goods. Family and work, solidarity and autonomy, tradition and
innovation are really valuable, and really in tension <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2018/04/steven-pinker-enlightenment-now/554054/">When Truth and Reason
Are No Longer
Enough</a></li>
<li>I am not a relativist; I do not say "I like my coffee with milk and you like
it without; I am in favor of kindness and you prefer concentration camps"
<a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/users/vl/notes/berlin.html">Isaiah Berlin on
Pluralism</a></li>
<li>Unstructured, unsupervised time for play is one of the most important things
we have to give back to kids if we want them to be strong and happy and
resilient. <a href="https://reason.com/archives/2017/10/26/the-fragile-generation">The Fragile
Generation</a></li>
<li>The average net worth among adults in the 95th to 99th percentile is about
$1.7 million. Among the 0.1 percent, it’s about $60 million. Who, exactly, are
the aristocrats again? <a href="https://slate.com/business/2018/05/forget-the-atlantics-9-9-percent-the-1-percent-are-still-the-problem.html">Forget What the Atlantic Is Telling You. The 1 Percent
Are Still the
Problem</a></li>
<li>We are a species that strives not just for survival, but also for
significance. We want lives that matter. <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2018/06/23/opinion/sunday/suicide-rate-existential-crisis.html">Is This an Existential
Crisis?</a></li>
<li>To support triangulation, we recommend a shift to a contributorship model,
similar to the credits that roll at the end of a film — a long list of
individuals with their contributions described fully and specifically <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-018-01023-3">Robust
research needs many lines of
evidence</a></li>
<li>Do whatever you can’t stop thinking about. Documenting your findings in public
(regardless of outcomes!) is a worthy contribution to society, full stop. <a href="https://nadiaeghbal.com/independent-research">The
independent researcher</a></li>
<li>Various studies have identified cooperation as a core theme in popular
narratives across the world. ... nearly 80% of their tales concerned moral
decision making and social dilemmas <a href="http://www.bbc.com/culture/story/20180503-our-fiction-addiction-why-humans-need-stories">Our fiction addiction: Why humans need
stories</a></li>
<li>The transhumanist vision too easily reduces all of reality to data,
concluding that “humans are nothing but information-processing objects.”
<a href="https://medium.com/s/futurehuman/survival-of-the-richest-9ef6cddd0cc1">Survival of the
Richest</a></li>
<li>This means that the mistake must be at the root, at the very basis of human
thinking in the past centuries. ... It could also be called
anthropocentricity, with man seen as the center of everything that exists. <a href="https://www.americanrhetoric.com/speeches/alexandersolzhenitsynharvard.htm">A
World Split
Apart</a></li>
<li>Concoct one story where things get better, one where they get worse, and one
where they get weird. <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2018/09/01/opinion/sunday/how-make-big-decision.html">How to Make a Big
Decision</a></li>
<li>Particularly sad is the belief that the majority of the homeless were drunks,
drug addicts, criminals or thieves. It is true that the category “homeless”
has come to include all of those people, but there are so many, many more who
are none of those things. <a href="https://crosscut.com/2018/09/why-i-started-giving-homeless">Why I started giving to the homeless</a></li>
<li>Perhaps unsurprisingly, Magic Leap is almost entirely built on the visions of
grown men wanting to immerse themselves in fantasy worlds. <a href="https://gizmodo.com/the-magic-leap-con-1829716266">The Magic Leap
Con</a></li>
<li>The really important kind of freedom involves attention, and awareness, and
discipline, and effort, and being able truly to care about other people and to
sacrifice for them, over and over, in myriad petty little unsexy ways, every
day. That is real freedom. The alternative is unconsciousness, the
default-setting, the "rat race"-the constant gnawing sense of having had and
lost some infinite thing. <a href="https://fs.blog/2012/04/david-foster-wallace-this-is-water/">This is Water</a></li>
<li>The big mistake in this pattern of failure is projecting your subjective lack
of comprehension onto the object you are looking at, as “irrationality.” We
make this mistake because we are tempted by a desire for legibility. <a href="https://www.ribbonfarm.com/2010/07/26/a-big-little-idea-called-legibility/">A Big Little Idea Called Legibility</a></li>
<li>There is something sinister and corrupt—Maoist—in the habit of assigning
people to categories. <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/america-is-addicted-to-outrage-is-there-a-cure-1543620811">America Is Addicted to Outrage. Is There a
Cure?</a></li>
<li>Like the open office, the loud restaurant seems to have overstayed its
welcome. That’s because loud restaurants are more profitable. <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2018/11/how-restaurants-got-so-loud/576715/">How Restaurants
Got So
Loud</a></li>
</ul>


        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Against retweets</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2018/against-retweets/"/>
    
    <updated>2018-09-09T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2018/against-retweets/</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p><img src="/assets/against-retweets.png" alt="Create and consume time for content of various lengths." /></p>

<p>One of these data points is not like the other. Also, isn't it neat that common
units of time duration fall nicely onto a logarithmic scale?</p>


        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Make twitter great again?</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2018/make-twitter-great-again/"/>
    
    <updated>2018-09-06T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2018/make-twitter-great-again/</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>I used twitter the most while working in developer relations, mainly sharing
articles about web development that I thought deserved more attention. My feed
consisted of engineers, developer advocates, and web standards folks I
respected, all of whom had something interesting to say. Twitter was my interest
graph, in contrast with Facebook, which was just a poor facsimile of real life
relationships.</p>

<p>As my career and interests shifted, so did the people I followed on twitter.
I started following VR engineers, machine learning researchers, philosophers
and psychologists. But more tweeps meant more tweets. Soon I had a [twitter
list][smartpeople](https://twitter.com/borismus/lists/smartpeople) for people that I had reluctantly unfollowed. They had
interesting things to say, but said them too often.</p>

<p>Following someone on twitter is like having a direct line into their brain. If
they write about a subject you are passionate about, fantastic. If they have
broadly aligning interests, chances are they will turn you on to something neat,
or if you're lucky, life changing. Unfortunately, most of the time, twitter
brains are distracted, anxious, angry, or unhappy. Spastic tweet storms and
political ramblings deserve only one thing, a hearty unfollow.</p>

<p>Twitter's bad design decisions only compound the problem. In "Retweets Are
Trash", Alexis Madrigal <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2018/04/the-case-against-retweets/554078/">writes</a>, "When Twitter introduced a retweet
button, in 2009, suddenly one click could send a post careening through the
network. The automatic retweet took Twitter’s natural tendency for amplification
and cranked it up." Apparently it's not hard to globally disable retweets using
a <a href="https://medium.com/@Luca/how-to-turn-off-retweets-for-everyone-99dd835c10f8">crude hack</a>. Anecdotally, it seems to have made my feed a bit calmer.</p>

<p>A quick update on my <a href="http://smus.com/notes/2018/lynched-on-twitter/">white supremacist spam problem</a>. Time seems to
have sorted it out, and the remaining squawks have been muffled by twitter's
<a href="https://support.twitter.com/articles/20169398">quality filter</a>. I also tried using Mastodon. It was a calming
experience at first, but when I followed a few people and dug around a little
bit, I was dismayed to see most design choices mirroring twitter's. I caught up
on RSS feeds, which I really like. But the RSS ecosystem continues to die. Of
nearly five hundred RSS feeds in my OPML file, more than half are broken links.
Occasionally the links are fixed, causing my reader to choke on a year's worth
of articles from a blog whose existence I've long forgotten about.</p>

<p>I can't quite decide whether or not to use twitter again. I keep thinking that I
once got a lot out of my original use of the platform. If I do return, I'll be
making use of the @reply quality filter, fully disable retweets, and unfollow
more aggressively. Whether this makes twitter great again remains to be seen.</p>


        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Lynched on Twitter</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2018/lynched-on-twitter/"/>
    
    <updated>2018-08-26T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2018/lynched-on-twitter/</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>Last week, a <a href="https://twitter.com/borismus/status/798350680951910400">sarcastic twitter
reply</a> I posted two
years ago was picked up by an account called Blue Check Watch, looking for
verified twitter accounts disparaging white people. As a result, my account has
become inundated by a hybrid human-bot army of white supremacist trolls. Most
responses accused me of anti-white racism, completely missing what I thought was
obviously a sarcastic tone. Sadly, many of the attacks are really nasty and
ad-hominem. One user
<a href="https://twitter.com/CascadianDennis/status/1033190496456269824">posted</a> "Why do
people who say this always look like this?", alongside my twitter profile photo.
Others are
<a href="https://twitter.com/1CE1CEB4BY/status/1033197950703464448">explicitly</a>
<a href="https://twitter.com/NationDixie/status/1033395244014944256">anti-semitic</a>
messages that do not bear repeating here. Ominously, I received an email from
Twitter informing me that they have investigated <strong>my tweet</strong>, flagged for violating
their TOS and "have not taken any action at this time."</p>

<p>Writing my snarky tweet two years ago, I was a bit uncertain whether it was
within the bounds of social acceptability. A white guy telling another
white guy that white guys are "the worst", was intended to poke a bit of fun at
the self-flaggelation associated with progressive politics. There is only so
much self-censorship one can do while still remaining authentic. In a surprising
twist, my tweet was offensive to a group I hadn't even thought about in a way I
could not have predicted, two years after the fact.</p>

<p>Twitter lynchings are not new, but it's different when it happens to you. It has
not had any serious consequences (yet?), and until it does, I will continue to
view this as a funny story, and not something truly traumatic, as it is often
framed in the press. Still, this experience serves as a good reminder of a few
points:</p>

<ol>
<li>Twitter's UI for threaded conversations is terrible, and hardly anyone of my
virtual lynch mob even bothered to look to the tweet I was responding to.</li>
<li>My tweet was five words, twenty four characters. It was meant to be pithy,
because that is how twitter works. But brief posts beget brief responses,
which is fine between friends, but not fine when the whole world is watching.</li>
<li>Relatedly, sarcasm is hard to convey in this situation. Only two responses
suggested that maybe I was being sarcastic, imploring my attackers, "Don't be
lazy."</li>
<li>The fact that tweets have no expiry date means anything you have ever posted
can be used against you in surprising ways. It took two years for my tweet to
be picked up. James Gunn's incriminating posts were ten years old. Social
norms change quickly, and this is one argument in favor of ephemerality.</li>
<li>On that same note, it seems that the white supremacy movement has really
embraced the internet over the last couple of years in some sick symbiosis
with the POTUS. At the same time, it's striking that the result of someone's
pathetic search for anti-white sentiment yielded such a lackluster example.</li>
<li>Despite a general willingness for my views to be challenged, I don't have
energy or desire to engage with this mob. I made no attempts to respond to
any of my attackers. They appear to be victims of confirmation bias, stupid
and/or malicious, and I have little faith that they will listen.</li>
<li>There are some really nasty people on the internet. If triggered, they will
sherlock your religion, your employer, your family, and try to hit you where
it hurts the most.</li>
</ol>

<p>Lynchings aside, I've been trying to use twitter less in favor of consuming and
producing longer form content, like books, blogs, and conversations. Given that
my account is currently being inundated with anti-semitic spam, I have very
little incentive to continue using the service. One thing that has been keeping
me on the platform is the potential reach I can get through 6K followers. I
should remember that in the grand scheme of things, this is a small number, 5
orders of magnitude less than the lovely POTUS. I shouldn't grow attached.</p>

<p>And so, just in time for my tenth twitter anniversary, it's time for me to make
some changes. At the very least, I'll be taking a long break.</p>


        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The difficult middle</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2018/the-difficult-middle/"/>
    
    <updated>2018-07-21T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2018/the-difficult-middle/</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>Monism gives life meaning through a single all-encompassing doctrine. Examples
include some political ideologies, religions, and [variants of
rationality][chapman-rationality](https://meaningness.com/non-theistic-eternalism). History has not been kind to those that have
fervently followed such doctrines. But once you see flaws in Monism, it can be
tempting to decide that life has <a href="https://meaningness.com/extreme-examples-eternalism-and-nihilism">no meaning at all</a>, falling
into the trap of Nihilism.</p>

<p><img src="https://i.imgur.com/WXdU3ef.gif" alt="Stuck" /></p>

<p>The choice between these two extremes is a false one. [Rationalists know
this][third-alternative](https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/erGipespbbzdG5zYb/the-third-alternative). <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Middle_Way">Buddhists know this</a>. Philosophers know
this too. David Chapman writes a <a href="https://meaningness.com/">whole blog</a> devoted to exploring
the space in between. But I have found <a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/users/vl/notes/berlin.html">Isaiah Berlin</a>'s synthesis to
be the most compelling:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Sobered by the 20th century’s failed utopias, <a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/users/vl/notes/berlin.html">Berlin</a>
  argued for a more modest liberal pluralism that makes room for multiple,
  genuinely conflicting goods. Family and work, solidarity and autonomy, tradition
  and innovation are really valuable, and really in tension.  – [Alison
  Gopnik][gopnik](https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2018/04/steven-pinker-enlightenment-now/554054/)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In this view, we are condemned to an eternal balancing act, sometimes peering
too far into the meaningless abyss, and other times relaxing too deeply into
meaningful certainty. On balance, I hope to end up in this difficult middle.</p>


        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Required reading for VR enthusiasts</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2018/required-reading-for-vr-enthusiasts/"/>
    
    <updated>2018-06-03T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2018/required-reading-for-vr-enthusiasts/</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>Several books, movies, and articles have helped to shape my opinions on Virtual
Reality. I've was initially surprised by some former colleagues that it is
possible to view these works as aspirational rather than cautionary. I generally
prefer the dystopian interpretation. </p>

<ul>
<li>📚 Ray Bradbury - <a href="http://www.veddma.com/veddma/Veldt.htm">The Veldt</a></li>
<li>📚 Neil Stephenson - Snow Crash</li>
<li>📚 Stanislav Lem - The Futurological Congress</li>
<li>📚 Vernor Vinge - Rainbow's End</li>
<li>📚 Ernst Kline - Ready Player One</li>
<li>🎥 Black Mirror S3 E2: <a href="http://www.theverge.com/2016/10/25/13401020/black-mirror-season-3-episode-2-playtest-recap">Playtest</a></li>
<li>🎥 The Matrix</li>
<li>🎵 Father John Misty - <a href="https://genius.com/Father-john-misty-total-entertainment-forever-lyrics">Total Entertainment Forever</a></li>
<li>📜 <a href="http://slatestarcodex.com/2014/06/03/asches-to-asches/">Asches to Asches</a></li>
<li>📜 Robert Nozick's <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Experience_machine">experience machine</a></li>
</ul>


        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Balancing technological pessimism</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2018/balancing-technological-pessimism/"/>
    
    <updated>2018-05-16T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2018/balancing-technological-pessimism/</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p><a href="https://pessimists.co/">Pessimists archive</a> is a podcast that chronicles
pessimistic reactions to emerging technology as it was becoming mainstream.
Technology here is defined broadly, covering a broad range of topics: bikes,
coffee, pinball machines, vaccines, recorded music. The podcast is very
accessible, focused more on social and psychological issues and less on the tech
itself. </p>

<!--more-->

<p>In response to unreasonable technological enthusiasm ever present in my
industry, I have myself tended towards pessimism. After we launched Cardboard,
my small HCI team in Google Research became the de facto home of VR at Google.
Once word got out, engineers and designers flocked to our ranks, self selecting
for interest in VR. Suddenly I was surrounded by hundreds of VR enthusiasts,
while I was skeptical about the vision of VR as <a href="https://youtu.be/dxbh-TM5yNc?t=3m">"the last
platform"</a> and concerned about the social
implications of broad VR adoption.</p>

<p>I began to see myself as <a href="https://www.quora.com/World-War-Z-2013-movie/World-War-Z-2013-movie-Do-the-Israelis-really-have-a-10th-man-doctrine">the tenth
man</a>,
posing the question: what if VR isn't really a thing? I ended up much more
excited about <a href="https://atap.google.com/spotlight-stories/">Spotlight Stories</a>
without a headset, thought a bunch about augmented reality through audio, and
became increasingly alienated from my colleagues gushing with optimism, rushing
home to play Vive games in their carefully instrumented basements. This podcast
would sure have helped me put my VR pessimism into perspective. </p>

<p>One critique I had of the podcast concept is hindsight bias. All of the
technologies covered by Pessimists Archive ended up being successful, and time
has proven the doubters wrong. But how many emerging technologies were
successfully booed out of existence, or simply rejected by the market? And how
many market successes come at a significant cost that prescient pessimists
warned us about?  TV and smartphones come to mind.</p>

<p>That said, I highly recommend the podcast series. The episodes are short,
entertaining, and informative. I feel better equipped to recognize and overcome
the traps that ensnared previous generations of techno pessimists.</p>


        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>How rationalists can win</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2018/how-rationalists-can-win/"/>
    
    <updated>2018-04-12T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2018/how-rationalists-can-win/</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>The belief that <a href="https://wiki.lesswrong.com/wiki/Rationality_is_systematized_winning">"rationalists should win"</a> is widely held in the
rationalist community. So: does being a good rationalist actually help you win?
Certainly in some domains, like engineering and science, which focus on
quantification, systematization, and prediction. There, having a hyper-rational
mindset is clearly an advantage. As for winning at life, which I will take that
to mean leading to greater success in survival, evolution, and human
flourishing, I don't think rationality helps very much.</p>

<!--more-->

<p>The rationalist doctrine always favors quantification and optimization over
intuition. From a rationalist perspective, humans are buggy <a href="https://www.wired.com/2016/01/marvin-minskys-marvelous-meat-machine/">computers made of meat</a>. We are full of cognitive biases that cloud our judgement, and
cause us to do reliably poorly on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Newcomb%27s_paradox">simple tasks</a> related to
probability. So even if you don't really know what probability to assign, it's
better to <a href="https://putanumonit.com/">"put a number on it"</a> and then <a href="https://wiki.lesswrong.com/wiki/Shut_up_and_multiply">”shut up and multiply”</a>.</p>

<p>The problem with the above approach lies with the words "systematic" and
"predictable". Herb Simon's idea of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bounded_rationality">Bounded Rationality</a>, suggests that
our human ability to be rational, to systematize and predict is inherently
limited. These limitations may come from our limited brains, but may also be
fundamental in nature. Chaos theory makes it really difficult for even the most
advanced computers to predict even simple systems, such as the position of the
<a href="http://awesci.com/double-pendulum-and-why-we-can-never-predict-weather/">double pendulum</a> after a small amount of time.</p>

<p>The world is far more complicated than one pendulum attached to another.
Insisting on making every decision in life based on a <a href="/making-better-decisions/">series of sound logical steps</a>, one quickly becomes paralyzed by the
complexity of myriad tiny choices. Gerd Gigerenzer's <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ecological_rationality">ecological rationality</a> suggests that many things that appear illogical are actually
done for good reasons, ultimately leading to good outcomes. This idea is
directly at odds with the rational propensity for first knowing what is true
(epistemic rationality), and then making decisions in a series of logical steps.</p>

<p>Instead of being dogmatic about rationality, we should be better
consequentialists. Consider outcomes. Are rationalists more satisfied with their
lives than non-rationalists? Are they more productive?  Do they have fewer
regrets later in life? Do they have better relationships? Make more money?  Have
happier children? Impact their domains of knowledge more effectively?</p>

<p>It <a href="http://slatestarcodex.com/2018/04/02/are-the-amish-unhappy-super-happy-just-meh/">is hard to answer</a> the above questions definitively, but suppose we
had solid data, and it was clear that, Buddhists were more relaxed, Protestants
more productive, Amish happier, and Singularitarians more innovative than other
groups. Imagine we had a sense of expected consequences of being an adherent to
each type of lifestyle. Imagine further that you could take a personality test
and see how likely you would be to benefit from each. Then the rational thing to
do would be to choose one of the irrational doctrines to follow based on
expected outcomes if you were an adherent.</p>

<p>Of course, you want to remain open to changing your mind, so allow yourself to
indulge fully your chosen beliefs for a while. At the top of every year, wake up
as late as your doctrine allows and nurse your hangover, unless your beliefs
prevented you from drinking the night before. If your beliefs favors ice baths,
partake in the polar bear plunge. Then take a moment to re-evaluate your
beliefs.</p>


        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>A respectful truce?</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2017/a-respectful-truce/"/>
    
    <updated>2017-08-24T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2017/a-respectful-truce/</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>It's a fact that men greatly outnumber women in software engineering. As for
why, there is a fundamental disagreement between social constructivists and
evolutionary psychologists. </p>

<!--more-->

<p>Constructivists say that it’s because of systematic oppression against women.
Boys in the 80s grew up with computers, learned programming and made life a
living hell for their female classmates in CS101. <a href="http://www.npr.org/sections/money/2014/10/21/357629765/when-women-stopped-coding">Planet Money</a> has the
scoop. Evolutionary psychologists say that it’s because men and women have
evolutionarily caused <a href="https://heterodoxacademy.org/2017/08/10/the-google-memo-what-does-the-research-say-about-gender-differences/">differences in interests</a> and point to studies
indicating that progressive countries have larger gender representation gaps
because women are free to choose <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2017/08/07/contra-grant-on-exaggerated-differences/">careers based on interest</a>. I find
it likely that both positions contribute in part to the gender representation
disparity. Compelling arguments can be made for and against both, and both are
rooted in academic disciplines <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Replication_crisis">that are dangerously squishy</a>. As a
result, I don’t think we currently have a good scientific way of determining
this.</p>

<p>So what; science, schmience! Followers of the evo psych and constructivism are
at war. One continuously pisses the other off with their inflamatory rhetoric.
It is true that white males are historically privileged, but hammering “white
male privelege” into their heads predictably puts white males into a defensive
stance. Similarly, discussing how evo psych means that women are less interested
and therefore less capable of software engineering will predictably annoy
females, especially those rightfully proud of their software engineering
prowess, and tired of dealing with similar allegations for their whole career.</p>

<p>I've spent way too much time reading and thinking about this lately, and it
saddens me to conclude that the wisest course of action is to avoid discussing
this topic entirely (oops, too late). Scott Aaronson, Sarah Constantin and
Stacey Jeffery propose a <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=3389">respectful truce</a> between the two camps.
Advocates of evolutionary psychology should:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>do everything they can to foster diversity, including by creating environments
  that are welcoming for women, and by supporting affirmative action, women-only
  scholarships and conferences, and other diversity policies and also agree
  never to talk in public about possible cognitive-science explanations for
  gender disparities in which careers people choose, or overlapping bell curves,
  or anything else potentially inflammatory."</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Meanwhile, social constructivists should:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>avoid libelling [white men] as misogynist monsters, who must be scaring all
  the women away with their inherently gross, icky, creepy, discriminatory
  brogrammer maleness.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Truce?</p>


        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The end of endings</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2017/the-end-of-endings/"/>
    
    <updated>2017-07-31T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2017/the-end-of-endings/</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>Despite the obnoxious title, <a href="https://a16z.com/2017/07/15/popularity-addiction-thompson-alter/">this a16z podcast</a> was unusually insightful.</p>

<p>One big theme in the podcast can be summarized as an end of endings: a trend
away from one story with a coherent, finite arc, towards something neverending.
Amorphous TV shows like Lost, as well as Hollywood's discovery that a coherent
franchise like Star Wars can be milked for many more dollars are examples of
this. The stats backs it up: Hollywood moved from 10% of the hits of the 90s
being sequels to 50% today, as can be seen in the <a href="http://www.boxofficemojo.com/yearly/">box office data</a>.
Looking at TV shows through the same lens, each show is a one hour long movie,
followed by tens of sequels. And successful franchises aim to immerse their fans
(especially kids) into their universe with figurines, games, lunch boxes, bed
sheets.</p>

<p>The end of endings also shows up in user interfaces, and is epitomized by the
infinite scroller. Millions of souls fixate on the next pretty picture, the next
baby picture, the next outrage. Entertainment that never ends!</p>

<p>This is interesting in the context of attention. In the realm of meditation, the
challenge is to focus on something mundane, like your breath. In the realm of
entertainment, the challenge is to snap out of an immersive world carefully
constructed to consume your attention for as long as possible.</p>


        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Intelligence, aliens, and self-improvement</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2017/intelligence-aliens-and-self-improvement/"/>
    
    <updated>2017-07-10T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2017/intelligence-aliens-and-self-improvement/</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>I recently enjoyed a podcast about intelligence, aliens and learning where Kevin
Kelly was interviewed by Sam Harris. Here are some things I liked about it:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Kelly makes a great argument that with text we already have no way of knowing
what is true. We have to rely on the source. My fears of audio and video fake
news are reduced.</p></li>
<li><p>It's obvious that the world is changing quickly, which means lifelong learning
is necessary. One thing I haven't systematically understood is how I learn
best. How would you even figure that out?</p></li>
<li><p>Chimpanzees are amazing at <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zsXP8qeFF6A">short term spatial
memory</a>, and do better than
humans in these cognitive tasks on average.</p></li>
<li><p>Currently, the best Chess players are human-computer hybrids. Harris claims
that computers alone will eventually be better than these hybrids, but 
his claim that "the ape will just be adding noise" is unsubstantiated.</p></li>
<li><p>About mid-way, the two discuss the analogy between AI and aliens. I haven't
thought of this either. But I wondered how salient that analogy was given that we
have a largely shared environment with whatever AIs we create. To the extent
that the AIs truly are alien, I wonder how much of a unifying force these
alien AIs could be for humanity. </p></li>
<li><p>I strongly agreed with Kelly when he says that building machine systems
enhances our self-understanding. Building VR rendering and head tracking
systems, you benefit from some human visual perception basics. Human
psychology is critical for building user interfaces. You need an understanding
of how human hearing works to build good lossy audio compression.</p></li>
<li><p>An interesting thought experiment that superscedes Asimov's laws of robotics:
what if we built AGIs that were terribly worried about what people think. Then
we reduce the machine menace problem to merely the evils of humanity. </p></li>
</ul>


        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Convincing the inconvincible</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2017/convincing-the-inconvincible/"/>
    
    <updated>2017-06-20T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2017/convincing-the-inconvincible/</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>I highly recommend two <a href="http://loveandradio.org/2014/02/the-silver-dollar/">podcast</a> <a href="http://loveandradio.org/2017/02/how-to-argue/">episodes</a> on the theme "how to argue",
featuring Daryl Davis, <em>the</em> black friend of white supremacists. Mr. Davis is
remarkably lucid in dealing with very difficult issues, and presents great tips
for convincing the inconvincible. </p>

<ol>
<li><p>Gather your information. Understand their position as well as you do your
own. Expect to hear things you will disagree with and keep your cool. </p></li>
<li><p>Invite them. Have a conversation not a debate. Debates get people's guards
up. Instead seek to understand them. People want to be heard and speak their
mind freely without retaliation. </p></li>
<li><p>Look for commonality. You can find something in 5 minutes and then build on
it. Look to other issues. Politics? As you find more commonality the
differences matter less. </p></li>
<li><p>Talking is not fighting. When the talking stops the ground becomes fertile
for violence (cf. Sam Harris). The longer you talk the more commonalities you
can find. </p></li>
<li><p>Patience.</p></li>
<li><p>Make a good first impression. Be respectful.</p></li>
<li><p>Don't be condescending or insulting even when you hear things you don't like.
Expect opinions that are ridiculous and facts that are wrong. Keep cool. </p></li>
<li><p>Don't explain somebody else's movement. Let them explain it and address the
points that they themselves define. Let them finish and don't cut them off
even though you probably know a lot about their ideas already. </p></li>
</ol>

<blockquote>
  <p>"While you are actively learning about someone else you are passively teaching
  them about yourself." – Daryl Davis</p>
</blockquote>


        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Remembering my personal wiki</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2017/remembering-my-personal-wiki/"/>
    
    <updated>2017-06-01T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2017/remembering-my-personal-wiki/</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>Before I started writing this blog, I used <a href="https://moinmo.in">MoinMoin</a> as a personal wiki.
It was self-hosted on a Linux box in my parents' basement. I used it for
everything: jotting down ideas, as a calendar, storing guitar tabs, tracking
workout routines, course planning, and personal finances. I wrote on the wiki
actively from about 2002 to about 2008. Here are some blasts from the past:</p>

<ul>
<li>My Lego fandom started to shift from into robotics. To be clear,
this is just a fancy way of saying that I was still <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Bartender/">playing</a> <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/CardDealer/">with</a>
<a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/VerticalCrossBeams/">legos</a> into my early twenties.</li>
<li>Origami interests also shifted into the <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/OrigamiSoftware/">digital realm</a>.</li>
<li>I <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Network/">maintained a network</a> of about ten Linux boxes named after
<a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Aleph/">Hebrew</a> <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Zayin/">letters</a>. What a pain in the ass!</li>
<li>Wrote a few computer games, like this uninspired <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/ArcadeTank/">tank game</a>, and this
totally awesome <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Sponge/">pong variant</a> that was played inside a sphere.</li>
<li>Discovered <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Second-system_effect">second system syndrome</a> when trying to rewrite [a web based
RPG][alienation](http://wiki.z3.ca/Alienation/) I originally wrote in 2000.</li>
<li>Had some interesting, still relevant <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/GpsRpg/">ideas foreshadowing</a> Augmented
Reality gaming.</li>
<li>Catalogued delicious Japanese food in <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/JapaneseRestaurants/">Vancouver</a>.</li>
<li>Smashed a Palm Tungsten <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/TungstenDestruction/">with a hammer</a> out of frustration,
attempted to use a <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/TreoBluetoothHeadsets/">Bluetooth headset with my Treo</a> and dreamed of a
<a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/DreamGadget/">better gadget</a>.</li>
<li>Hoping to <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/MatrixWorkouts/">avoid the gym</a>, I got into <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Kettlebells/">kettlebells for fitness</a>,
and even thought about starting a <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Gireviki/">kettlebell community</a>.</li>
<li>Saved <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Guitar(2f)Gravedigger/">guitar</a> <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Guitar(2f)WildMountainThyme/">tabs</a> I played with the intention of
<a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/LibTab/">doing something techy</a> with them later.</li>
</ul>

<p>Embarassing and endearing, <code>wiki.z3.ca</code> serves as a time capsule of my late
teens and early twenties. Je me souviens.</p>


        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Short posts using split Markdown</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2017/short-posts-using-split-markdown/"/>
    
    <updated>2017-05-28T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2017/short-posts-using-split-markdown/</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p><a href="https://github.com/borismus/lightning">Lightning</a>, the static blog generator that powers this site, is
awesome for long form content. But it does not work well for short form content,
since creating each post requires a bunch of up-front effort:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>I navigate to the right place, recalling the current year (!) and deciding on
the slug for the post (eg. <code>content/posts/2017/how-to-fix-the-world</code>).</p></li>
<li><p>I manually create the <code>index.md</code> file and then specify the redundant
human-readable title and the posted date within it:</p>

<pre><code>How to Fix the World
===
posted: May 28, 2017

Listen to me, I have the answers.
</code></pre></li>
</ol>

<p>After writing the post, the title will inevitably have changed, so I rename the
slug to match: <code>mv how-to-fix-the-world how-to-slightly-improve-the-world</code>.
Finally I publish and tweet, and hopefully the world becomes infinitesimally
better.</p>

<p>I once tried to <a href="/easier-link-blogging/">make it easier to keep a lightning-style link blog</a>, but
ended up scrapping the solution because it was buggy and required a Mac.</p>

<h2>Split markdown pages</h2>

<p>My aim was to remove the up-front costs I described above. Appending to the top
of an existing file and having the engine automatically generate a slug based on
the title seemed like the right approach. This means that one markdown file
results in multiple HTML pages. The latest <a href="https://github.com/borismus/lightning">Lightning</a> has been
updated with split markdown files, and refactored into classes, making it easier
to add features in the future. To give a sense of what these split markdown
files look like, take a look at <a href="https://github.com/borismus/smus.com/blob/master/notes_all.md">this file</a>.</p>

<p>Split markdown files power two new sections on this site: a [book
reviews section][books](/books), and a <a href="/notes">notes section</a>. I'm hoping that this
added convenience will encourage me to write shorter, more focused posts with
increasing frequency.</p>


        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Analogies from the industrial revolution</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="https://smus.com/notes/2017/analogies-from-the-industrial-revolution/"/>
    
    <updated>2017-05-24T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>https://smus.com/notes/2017/analogies-from-the-industrial-revolution/</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>Several centuries after the industrial revolution, machines still can't do all
physical things humans can, not even by a long shot. Drawing a masterwork,
singing an aria, playing a musical instrument, manipulating a soft object,
cutting hair, taking care of the sick are all examples of human-only tasks. The
industrial revolution gave machines the ability to do crude, physically
demanding work at scale, but it did not address all of physicality.</p>

<p>Just like the industrial revolution did not automate all aspects of physical
work, there is good reason to believe that the AI revolution will not solve
all aspects of intellectual work. Where the line will be drawn remains to be
seen, but I would bet that one aspect of human cognition that isn't really at
risk from any immediate AI-based disruption are creative pursuits. Many well
respected professions like doctor, lawyer, and engineer have both a rote
component that lends itself easily to automation, and a creative one. Some
examples:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Curing patients boils down to the application of known heuristics to
triage specific cases, but if you are a MD-PhD studying a new area of medicine
or tackling a new disease, it's a much more creative and speculative process. </p></li>
<li><p>The legal profession involves finding the right precedents relevant to the case
at hand, but articulating a convincing argument or deciding how to work out a
new situation where there are now laws yet? Creativity.</p></li>
<li><p>Designing a marketing webpage for a clothing brand is pretty formulaic. But
inventing way of solving a problem using new technology? Totally creative. </p></li>
</ul>


        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>