<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
      xml:lang="en"
      xml:base="http://smus.com">
  <title>Boris Smus (Notes)</title>
  <link href="http://smus.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://smus.com"/>
  <updated>2017-12-21T10:33:08-00:00</updated>
  <id>http://smus.com/atom.xml</id>
  
  <entry>
    <title>A respectful truce?</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="/notes/2017/a-respectful-truce/"/>
    
    <updated>2017-08-24T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>http://smus.com/notes/2017/a-respectful-truce/</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>It's a fact that men greatly outnumber women in software engineering. As for
why, there is a fundamental disagreement between social constructivists and
evolutionary psychologists. </p>

<p>Constructivists say that it’s because of systematic oppression against women.
Boys in the 80s grew up with computers, learned programming and made life a
living hell for their female classmates in CS101. <a href="http://www.npr.org/sections/money/2014/10/21/357629765/when-women-stopped-coding">Planet Money</a> has the
scoop. Evolutionary psychologists say that it’s because men and women have
evolutionarily caused <a href="https://heterodoxacademy.org/2017/08/10/the-google-memo-what-does-the-research-say-about-gender-differences/">differences in interests</a> and point to studies
indicating that progressive countries have larger gender representation gaps
because women are free to choose <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2017/08/07/contra-grant-on-exaggerated-differences/">careers based on interest</a>. I find
it likely that both positions contribute in part to the gender representation
disparity. Compelling arguments can be made for and against both, and both are
rooted in academic disciplines <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Replication_crisis">that are dangerously squishy</a>. As a
result, I don’t think we currently have a good scientific way of determining
this.</p>

<p>So what; science, schmience! Followers of the evo psych and constructivism are
at war. One continuously pisses the other off with their inflamatory rhetoric.
It is true that white males are historically privileged, but hammering “white
male privelege” into their heads predictably puts white males into a defensive
stance. Similarly, discussing how evo psych means that women are less interested
and therefore less capable of software engineering will predictably annoy
females, especially those rightfully proud of their software engineering
prowess, and tired of dealing with similar allegations for their whole career.</p>

<p>I've spent way too much time reading and thinking about this lately, and it
saddens me to conclude that the wisest course of action is to avoid discussing
this topic entirely (oops, too late). Scott Aaronson, Sarah Constantin and
Stacey Jeffery propose a <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=3389">respectful truce</a> between the two camps.
Advocates of evolutionary psychology should:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>do everything they can to foster diversity, including by creating environments
  that are welcoming for women, and by supporting affirmative action, women-only
  scholarships and conferences, and other diversity policies and also agree
  never to talk in public about possible cognitive-science explanations for
  gender disparities in which careers people choose, or overlapping bell curves,
  or anything else potentially inflammatory."</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Meanwhile, social constructivists should:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>avoid libelling [white men] as misogynist monsters, who must be scaring all
  the women away with their inherently gross, icky, creepy, discriminatory
  brogrammer maleness.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Truce?</p>


        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The end of endings</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="/notes/2017/the-end-of-endings/"/>
    
    <updated>2017-07-31T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>http://smus.com/notes/2017/the-end-of-endings/</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>Despite the obnoxious title, <a href="https://a16z.com/2017/07/15/popularity-addiction-thompson-alter/">this a16z podcast</a> was unusually insightful.</p>

<p>One big theme in the podcast can be summarized as an end of endings: a trend
away from one story with a coherent, finite arc, towards something neverending.
Amorphous TV shows like Lost, as well as Hollywood's discovery that a coherent
franchise like Star Wars can be milked for many more dollars are examples of
this. The stats backs it up: Hollywood moved from 10% of the hits of the 90s
being sequels to 50% today, as can be seen in the <a href="http://www.boxofficemojo.com/yearly/">box office data</a>.
Looking at TV shows through the same lens, each show is a one hour long movie,
followed by tens of sequels. And successful franchises aim to immerse their fans
(especially kids) into their universe with figurines, games, lunch boxes, bed
sheets.</p>

<p>The end of endings also shows up in user interfaces, and is epitomized by the
infinite scroller. Millions of souls fixate on the next pretty picture, the next
baby picture, the next outrage. Entertainment that never ends!</p>

<p>This is interesting in the context of attention. In the realm of meditation, the
challenge is to focus on something mundane, like your breath. In the realm of
entertainment, the challenge is to snap out of an immersive world carefully
constructed to consume your attention for as long as possible.</p>


        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Intelligence, aliens, and self-improvement</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="/notes/2017/intelligence-aliens-and-self-improvement/"/>
    
    <updated>2017-07-10T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>http://smus.com/notes/2017/intelligence-aliens-and-self-improvement/</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>I recently enjoyed a podcast about intelligence, aliens and learning where Kevin
Kelly was interviewed by Sam Harris. Here are some things I liked about it:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Kelly makes a great argument that with text we already have no way of knowing
what is true. We have to rely on the source. My fears of audio and video fake
news are reduced.</p></li>
<li><p>It's obvious that the world is changing quickly, which means lifelong learning
is necessary. One thing I haven't systematically understood is how I learn
best. How would you even figure that out?</p></li>
<li><p>Chimpanzees are amazing at <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zsXP8qeFF6A">short term spatial
memory</a>, and do better than
humans in these cognitive tasks on average.</p></li>
<li><p>Currently, the best Chess players are human-computer hybrids. Harris claims
that computers alone will eventually be better than these hybrids, but 
his claim that "the ape will just be adding noise" is unsubstantiated.</p></li>
<li><p>About mid-way, the two discuss the analogy between AI and aliens. I haven't
thought of this either. But I wondered how salient that analogy was given that we
have a largely shared environment with whatever AIs we create. To the extent
that the AIs truly are alien, I wonder how much of a unifying force these
alien AIs could be for humanity. </p></li>
<li><p>I strongly agreed with Kelly when he says that building machine systems
enhances our self-understanding. Building VR rendering and head tracking
systems, you benefit from some human visual perception basics. Human
psychology is critical for building user interfaces. You need an understanding
of how human hearing works to build good lossy audio compression.</p></li>
<li><p>An interesting thought experiment that superscedes Asimov's laws of robotics:
what if we built AGIs that were terribly worried about what people think. Then
we reduce the machine menace problem to merely the evils of humanity. </p></li>
</ul>


        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Convincing the inconvincible</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="/notes/2017/convincing-the-inconvincible/"/>
    
    <updated>2017-06-20T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>http://smus.com/notes/2017/convincing-the-inconvincible/</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>I highly recommend two <a href="http://loveandradio.org/2014/02/the-silver-dollar/">podcast</a> <a href="http://loveandradio.org/2017/02/how-to-argue/">episodes</a> on the theme "how to argue",
featuring Daryl Davis, <em>the</em> black friend of white supremacists. Mr. Davis is
remarkably lucid in dealing with very difficult issues, and presents great tips
for convincing the inconvincible. </p>

<ol>
<li><p>Gather your information. Understand their position as well as you do your
own. Expect to hear things you will disagree with and keep your cool. </p></li>
<li><p>Invite them. Have a conversation not a debate. Debates get people's guards
up. Instead seek to understand them. People want to be heard and speak their
mind freely without retaliation. </p></li>
<li><p>Look for commonality. You can find something in 5 minutes and then build on
it. Look to other issues. Politics? As you find more commonality the
differences matter less. </p></li>
<li><p>Talking is not fighting. When the talking stops the ground becomes fertile
for violence (cf. Sam Harris). The longer you talk the more commonalities you
can find. </p></li>
<li><p>Patience.</p></li>
<li><p>Make a good first impression. Be respectful. </p></li>
<li><p>Don't be condescending or insulting even when you hear things you don't like.
Expect opinions that are ridiculous and facts that are wrong. Keep cool. </p></li>
<li><p>Don't explain somebody else's movement. Let them explain it and address the
points that they themselves define. Let them finish and don't cut them off
even though you probably know a lot about their ideas already. </p></li>
</ol>

<blockquote>
  <p>"While you are actively learning about someone else you are passively teaching
  them about yourself." – Daryl Davis</p>
</blockquote>


        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Remembering my personal wiki</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="/notes/2017/remembering-my-personal-wiki/"/>
    
    <updated>2017-06-01T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>http://smus.com/notes/2017/remembering-my-personal-wiki/</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>Before I started writing this blog, I used <a href="https://moinmo.in">MoinMoin</a> as a personal wiki.
It was self-hosted on a Linux box in my parents' basement. I used it for
everything: jotting down ideas, as a calendar, storing guitar tabs, tracking
workout routines, course planning, and personal finances. I wrote on the wiki
actively from about 2002 to about 2008. Here are some blasts from the past:</p>

<ul>
<li>My Lego fandom started to shift from into robotics. To be clear,
this is just a fancy way of saying that I was still <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Bartender/">playing</a> <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/CardDealer/">with</a>
<a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/VerticalCrossBeams/">legos</a> into my early twenties.</li>
<li>Origami interests also shifted into the <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/OrigamiSoftware/">digital realm</a>.</li>
<li>I <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Network/">maintained a network</a> of about ten Linux boxes named after
<a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Aleph/">Hebrew</a> <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Zayin/">letters</a>. What a pain in the ass!</li>
<li>Wrote a few computer games, like this uninspired <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/ArcadeTank/">tank game</a>, and this
totally awesome <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Sponge/">pong variant</a> that was played inside a sphere.</li>
<li>Discovered <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Second-system_effect">second system syndrome</a> when trying to rewrite <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Alienation/">a web based
RPG</a> I originally wrote in 2000.</li>
<li>Had some interesting, still relevant <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/GpsRpg/">ideas foreshadowing</a> Augmented
Reality gaming.</li>
<li>Catalogued delicious Japanese food in <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/JapaneseRestaurants/">Vancouver</a>.</li>
<li>Smashed a Palm Tungsten <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/TungstenDestruction/">with a hammer</a> out of frustration,
attempted to use a <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/TreoBluetoothHeadsets/">Bluetooth headset with my Treo</a> and dreamed of a
<a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/DreamGadget/">better gadget</a>.</li>
<li>Hoping to <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/MatrixWorkouts/">avoid the gym</a>, I got into <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Kettlebells/">kettlebells for fitness</a>,
and even thought about starting a <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Gireviki/">kettlebell community</a>.</li>
<li>Saved <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Guitar(2f)Gravedigger/">guitar</a> <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Guitar(2f)WildMountainThyme/">tabs</a> I played with the intention of
<a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/LibTab/">doing something techy</a> with them later.</li>
</ul>

<p>Embarassing and endearing, <code>wiki.z3.ca</code> serves as a time capsule of my late
teens and early twenties. Je me souviens.</p>


        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Short posts using split Markdown</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="/notes/2017/short-posts-using-split-markdown/"/>
    
    <updated>2017-05-28T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>http://smus.com/notes/2017/short-posts-using-split-markdown/</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p><a href="https://github.com/borismus/lightning">Lightning</a>, the static blog generator that powers this site, is
awesome for long form content. But it does not work well for short form content,
since creating each post requires a bunch of up-front effort:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>I navigate to the right place, recalling the current year (!) and deciding on
the slug for the post (eg. <code>content/posts/2017/how-to-fix-the-world</code>).</p></li>
<li><p>I manually create the <code>index.md</code> file and then specify the redundant
human-readable title and the posted date within it:</p>

<pre><code>How to Fix the World
===
posted: May 28, 2017

Listen to me, I have the answers.
</code></pre></li>
</ol>

<p>After writing the post, the title will inevitably have changed, so I rename the
slug to match: <code>mv how-to-fix-the-world how-to-slightly-improve-the-world</code>.
Finally I publish and tweet, and hopefully the world becomes infinitesimally
better.</p>

<p>I once tried to <a href="/easier-link-blogging/">make it easier to keep a lightning-style link blog</a>, but
ended up scrapping the solution because it was buggy and required a Mac.</p>

<h2>Split markdown pages</h2>

<p>My aim was to remove the up-front costs I described above. Appending to the top
of an existing file and having the engine automatically generate a slug based on
the title seemed like the right approach. This means that one markdown file
results in multiple HTML pages. The latest <a href="https://github.com/borismus/lightning">Lightning</a> has been
updated with split markdown files, and refactored into classes, making it easier
to add features in the future. To give a sense of what these split markdown
files look like, take a look at <a href="https://github.com/borismus/smus.com/blob/master/notes_all.md">this file</a>.</p>

<p>Split markdown files power two new sections on this site: a <a href="/books">book
reviews section</a>, and a <a href="/notes">notes section</a>. I'm hoping that this
added convenience will encourage me to write shorter, more focused posts with
increasing frequency.</p>


        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Analogies from the industrial revolution</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="/notes/2017/analogies-from-the-industrial-revolution/"/>
    
    <updated>2017-05-24T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>http://smus.com/notes/2017/analogies-from-the-industrial-revolution/</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>Several centuries after the industrial revolution, machines still can't do all
physical things humans can, not even by a long shot. Drawing a masterwork,
singing an aria, playing a musical instrument, manipulating a soft object,
cutting hair, taking care of the sick are all examples of human-only tasks. The
industrial revolution gave machines the ability to do crude, physically
demanding work at scale, but it did not address all of physicality.</p>

<p>Just like the industrial revolution did not automate all aspects of physical
work, there is good reason to believe that the AI revolution will not solve
all aspects of intellectual work. Where the line will be drawn remains to be
seen, but I would bet that one aspect of human cognition that isn't really at
risk from any immediate AI-based disruption are creative pursuits. Many well
respected professions like doctor, lawyer, and engineer have both a rote
component that lends itself easily to automation, and a creative one. Some
examples:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Curing patients boils down to the application of known heuristics to
triage specific cases, but if you are a MD-PhD studying a new area of medicine
or tackling a new disease, it's a much more creative and speculative process. </p></li>
<li><p>The legal profession involves finding the right precedents relevant to the case
at hand, but articulating a convincing argument or deciding how to work out a
new situation where there are now laws yet? Creativity.</p></li>
<li><p>Designing a marketing webpage for a clothing brand is pretty formulaic. But
inventing way of solving a problem using new technology? Totally creative. </p></li>
</ul>


        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>