<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
      xml:lang="en"
      xml:base="http://smus.com">
  <title>Boris Smus (Notes)</title>
  <link href="http://smus.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://smus.com"/>
  <updated>2017-06-14T14:13:42-00:00</updated>
  <id>http://smus.com/atom.xml</id>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Remembering my personal wiki</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="/notes/2017/remembering-my-personal-wiki/"/>
    
    <updated>2017-06-01T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>http://smus.com/notes/2017/remembering-my-personal-wiki/</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>Before I started writing this blog, I used <a href="https://moinmo.in">MoinMoin</a> as a personal wiki.
It was self-hosted on a Linux box in my parents' basement. I used it for
everything: jotting down ideas, as a calendar, storing guitar tabs, tracking
workout routines, course planning, and personal finances. I wrote on the wiki
actively from about 2002 to about 2008. Here are some blasts from the past:</p>

<ul>
<li>My Lego fandom started to shift from into robotics. To be clear,
this is just a fancy way of saying that I was still <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Bartender/">playing</a> <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/CardDealer/">with</a>
<a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/VerticalCrossBeams/">legos</a> into my early twenties.</li>
<li>Origami interests also shifted into the <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/OrigamiSoftware/">digital realm</a>.</li>
<li>I <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Network/">maintained a network</a> of about ten Linux boxes named after
<a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Aleph/">Hebrew</a> <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Zayin/">letters</a>. What a pain in the ass!</li>
<li>Wrote a few computer games, like this uninspired <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/ArcadeTank/">tank game</a>, and this
totally awesome <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Sponge/">pong variant</a> that was played inside a sphere.</li>
<li>Discovered <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Second-system_effect">second system syndrome</a> when trying to rewrite <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Alienation/">a web based
RPG</a> I originally wrote in 2000.</li>
<li>Had some interesting, still relevant <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/GpsRpg/">ideas foreshadowing</a> Augmented
Reality gaming.</li>
<li>Catalogued delicious Japanese food in <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/JapaneseRestaurants/">Vancouver</a>.</li>
<li>Smashed a Palm Tungsten <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/TungstenDestruction/">with a hammer</a> out of frustration,
attempted to use a <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/TreoBluetoothHeadsets/">Bluetooth headset with my Treo</a> and dreamed of a
<a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/DreamGadget/">better gadget</a>.</li>
<li>Hoping to <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/MatrixWorkouts/">avoid the gym</a>, I got into <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Kettlebells/">kettlebells for fitness</a>,
and even thought about starting a <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Gireviki/">kettlebell community</a>.</li>
<li>Saved <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Guitar(2f)Gravedigger/">guitar</a> <a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/Guitar(2f)WildMountainThyme/">tabs</a> I played with the intention of
<a href="http://wiki.z3.ca/LibTab/">doing something techy</a> with them later.</li>
</ul>

<p>Embarassing and endearing, <code>wiki.z3.ca</code> serves as a time capsule of my late
teens and early twenties. Je me souviens.</p>


        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Short posts using split Markdown</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="/notes/2017/short-posts-using-split-markdown/"/>
    
    <updated>2017-05-28T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>http://smus.com/notes/2017/short-posts-using-split-markdown/</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p><a href="https://github.com/borismus/lightning">Lightning</a>, the static blog generator that powers this site, is
awesome for long form content. But it does not work well for short form content,
since creating each post requires a bunch of up-front effort:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>I navigate to the right place, recalling the current year (!) and deciding on
the slug for the post (eg. <code>content/posts/2017/how-to-fix-the-world</code>).</p></li>
<li><p>I manually create the <code>index.md</code> file and then specify the redundant
human-readable title and the posted date within it:</p>

<pre><code>How to Fix the World
===
posted: May 28, 2017

Listen to me, I have the answers.
</code></pre></li>
</ol>

<p>After writing the post, the title will inevitably have changed, so I rename the
slug to match: <code>mv how-to-fix-the-world how-to-slightly-improve-the-world</code>.
Finally I publish and tweet, and hopefully the world becomes infinitesimally
better.</p>

<p>I once tried to <a href="/easier-link-blogging/">make it easier to keep a lightning-style link blog</a>, but
ended up scrapping the solution because it was buggy and required a Mac.</p>

<h2>Split markdown pages</h2>

<p>My aim was to remove the up-front costs I described above. Appending to the top
of an existing file and having the engine automatically generate a slug based on
the title seemed like the right approach. This means that one markdown file
results in multiple HTML pages. The latest <a href="https://github.com/borismus/lightning">Lightning</a> has been
updated with split markdown files, and refactored into classes, making it easier
to add features in the future. To give a sense of what these split markdown
files look like, take a look at <a href="https://github.com/borismus/smus.com/blob/master/notes_all.md">this file</a>.</p>

<p>Split markdown files power two new sections on this site: a <a href="/books">book
reviews section</a>, and a <a href="/notes">notes section</a>. I'm hoping that this
added convenience will encourage me to write shorter, more focused posts with
increasing frequency.</p>


        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Analogies from the industrial revolution</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="/notes/2017/analogies-from-the-industrial-revolution/"/>
    
    <updated>2017-05-24T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>http://smus.com/notes/2017/analogies-from-the-industrial-revolution/</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>Several centuries after the industrial revolution, machines still can't do all
physical things humans can, not even by a long shot. Drawing a masterwork,
singing an aria, playing a musical instrument, manipulating a soft object,
cutting hair, taking care of the sick are all examples of human-only tasks. The
industrial revolution gave machines the ability to do crude, physically
demanding work at scale, but it did not address all of physicality.</p>

<p>Just like the industrial revolution did not automate all aspects of physical
work, there is good reason to believe that the AI revolution will not solve
all aspects of intellectual work. Where the line will be drawn remains to be
seen, but I would bet that one aspect of human cognition that isn't really at
risk from any immediate AI-based disruption are creative pursuits. Many well
respected professions like doctor, lawyer, and engineer have both a rote
component that lends itself easily to automation, and a creative one. Some
examples:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Curing patients boils down to the application of known heuristics to
triage specific cases, but if you are a MD-PhD studying a new area of medicine
or tackling a new disease, it's a much more creative and speculative process. </p></li>
<li><p>The legal profession involves finding the right precedents relevant to the case
at hand, but articulating a convincing argument or deciding how to work out a
new situation where there are now laws yet? Creativity.</p></li>
<li><p>Designing a marketing webpage for a clothing brand is pretty formulaic. But
inventing way of solving a problem using new technology? Totally creative. </p></li>
</ul>


        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>