<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
      xml:lang="en"
      xml:base="http://smus.com">
  <title>Boris Smus (Notes)</title>
  <link href="http://smus.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://smus.com"/>
  <updated>2017-05-28T16:45:28-00:00</updated>
  <id>http://smus.com/atom.xml</id>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Short posts using split markdown pages</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="/notes/2017/short-posts-using-split-markdown-pages/"/>
    
    <updated>2017-05-28T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>http://smus.com/notes/2017/short-posts-using-split-markdown-pages/</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p><a href="https://github.com/borismus/lightning">Lightning</a> is awesome for long form content because it lets you
gather all of the assets you want to include in your post together in one
directory, place it alongside the markdown <code>index.md</code>, and put the content out
there in a single bundle. But it does not work well for short form content,
since it requires a bunch of up-front effort:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>New posts go to <code>content/posts/2017/how-to-fix-the-world</code>. This involves
navigating to the right place, recalling the current year (!) and deciding on
the slug for the post.</p></li>
<li><p>Creation of the <code>index.md</code> file and then specifying the somewhat redundant
human-readable title and the posted date:</p>

<pre><code>How to Fix the World
===
posted: May 28, 2017

Listen to me, I have the answers.
</code></pre></li>
</ol>

<p>Then, after writing the post, the title will inevitably have changed, so I
typically have to rename the slug to match: <code>mv how-to-fix-the-world
how-to-slightly-improve-the-world</code>. Finally I publish and tweet, and hopefully
the world becomes infinitesimally better.</p>

<h2>Split markdown pages</h2>

<p>My aim was to remove the up-front costs I described above. Appending to the top
of an existing file and having the engine automatically generate a slug based on
the title seemed like the right approach. This means one markdown results in
multiple HTML pages. This is the conceptual inverse of <a href="http://fletcher.github.io/MultiMarkdown-5/transclusion.html">MultiMarkdown
transclusion</a>, which lets you create extra long articles from multiple
markdown files. I've also refactored <a href="https://github.com/borismus/lightning">Lightning</a> into classes, making
it easier to add features in the future.</p>

<p>Split markdown files power two new sections on <a href="http://smus.com">http://smus.com</a>: a <a href="/books">book
reviews section</a>, and a <a href="/notes">notes section</a>. I'm hoping that this will
encourage me to write shorter, more focused posts with increasing frequency. To
give a sense of what these split markdown files look like, take a look at the
<a href="https://github.com/borismus/smus.com/blob/master/notes_all.md">notes markdown</a>.</p>


        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Analogies from the industrial revolution</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="/notes/2017/analogies-from-the-industrial-revolution/"/>
    
    <updated>2017-05-24T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>http://smus.com/notes/2017/analogies-from-the-industrial-revolution/</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>Several centuries after the industrial revolution, machines still can't do all
physical things humans can, not even by a long shot. Drawing a masterwork,
singing an aria, playing a musical instrument, manipulating a soft object,
cutting hair, taking care of the sick are all examples of human-only tasks. The
industrial revolution gave machines the ability to do crude, physically
demanding work at scale, but it did not address all of physicality.</p>

<p>Just like the industrial revolution did not automate all aspects of physical
work, there is good reason to believe that the AI revolution will not solve
all aspects of intellectual work. Where the line will be drawn remains to be
seen, but I would bet that one aspect of human cognition that isn't really at
risk from any immediate AI-based disruption are creative pursuits. Many well
respected professions like doctor, lawyer, and engineer have both a rote
component that lends itself easily to automation, and a creative one. Some
examples:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Curing patients boils down to the application of known heuristics to
triage specific cases, but if you are a MD-PhD studying a new area of medicine
or tackling a new disease, it's a much more creative and speculative process. </p></li>
<li><p>The legal profession involves finding the right precedents relevant to the case
at hand, but articulating a convincing argument or deciding how to work out a
new situation where there are now laws yet? Creativity.</p></li>
<li><p>Designing a marketing webpage for a clothing brand is pretty formulaic. But
inventing way of solving a problem using new technology? Totally creative. </p></li>
</ul>


        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>