<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
      xml:lang="en"
      xml:base="http://smus.com">
  <title>Boris Smus (Notes)</title>
  <link href="http://smus.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://smus.com"/>
  <updated>2017-05-26T17:49:25-00:00</updated>
  <id>http://smus.com/atom.xml</id>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Analogies from the industrial revolution</title>
    <author><name>Boris Smus</name></author>
    <link href="/notes/2017/analogies-from-the-industrial-revolution/"/>
    
    <updated>2017-05-24T09:00:00-00:00</updated>
    
    <id>http://smus.com/notes/2017/analogies-from-the-industrial-revolution/</id>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
      <div>
        <p>Several centuries after the industrial revolution, machines still can't do all
physical things humans can, not even by a long shot. Drawing a masterwork,
singing an aria, playing a musical instrument, manipulating a soft object,
cutting hair, taking care of the sick are all examples of human-only tasks. The
industrial revolution gave machines the ability to do crude, physically
demanding work at scale, but it did not address all of physicality.</p>

<p>Just like the industrial revolution did not automate all aspects of physical
work, there is good reason to believe that the AI revolution will not solve
all aspects of intellectual work. Where the line will be drawn remains to be
seen, but I would bet that one aspect of human cognition that isn't really at
risk from any immediate AI-based disruption are creative pursuits. Many well
respected professions like doctor, lawyer, and engineer have both a rote
component that lends itself easily to automation, and a creative one. Some
examples:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Curing patients boils down to the application of known heuristics to
triage specific cases, but if you are a MD-PhD studying a new area of medicine
or tackling a new disease, it's a much more creative and speculative process. </p></li>
<li><p>The legal profession involves finding the right precedents relevant to the case
at hand, but articulating a convincing argument or deciding how to work out a
new situation where there are now laws yet? Creativity.</p></li>
<li><p>Designing a marketing webpage for a clothing brand is pretty formulaic. But
inventing way of solving a problem using new technology? Totally creative. </p></li>
</ul>


        
      </div>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>